<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><plecoflash formatversion="2" creator="Pleco User 19125399" generator="Pleco 2.0 Flashcard Exporter" platform="Android" created="1743979850"><cards><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">房间</headword><headword charset="tc">房間</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">fang2jian1</pron><defn>noun room 一套房间 yī tào fángjiān a suite; an apartment; a flat</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="20821504"/><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">公寓</headword><headword charset="tc">公寓</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">gong1yu4</pron><defn>noun 1 apartment; flat; condominium 2 dated lodging house</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="21724672"/><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">收到</headword><headword charset="tc">收到</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shou1//dao4</pron><defn>verb receive; get; achieve; obtain 收到一封信 Shōudào yī fēng xìn receive a letter 收到良好效果 shōudào liánghǎo xiàoguǒ get good results</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30278656"/><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">发件人</headword><headword charset="tc">發件人</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">fa1jian4ren2</pron><defn>(mail or email) sender</defn></entry><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">你好</headword><headword charset="tc">你好</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ni3hao3</pron><defn>common phrase hello; hi; how are you [common form of greeting, used at any time of day, requiring the same phrase as an answer; also used at the beginning of letters]</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27304960"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">你</headword><headword charset="tc">你</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ni3</pron><defn>pronoun 1 you [second person singular] 你爸 nǐ bà your Dad 你带了多少钱？ Nǐ dài le duōshao qián？ How much money do you have on you? 2 you [second person plural] 你方 nǐ fāng your side; you 你校 nǐ xiào your school 3 [referring to any person] you; one; anyone 碰到这么一个人, 你有什么办法？ Pèngdào zhème yī ge rén, nǐ yǒu shénme bànfǎ？ What can you do with a person like that? 4 [with 我 or 他 in parallel structures to indicate several or many people behaving the same way] 三个人你看看我, 我看看你, 谁也不说话。 Sān ge rén nǐ kànkan wǒ,  wǒ kàn kàn nǐ, shuí yě bù shuōhuà. The three of them kept looking at each other without saying a word. 你一言, 我一语, 大家谈得很热闹。 Nǐ yī yán,  wǒ yī yǔ, dàjiā tán de hěn rènao. A lively conversation ensued with everybody joining in.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27304704"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">好</headword><headword charset="tc">好</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hao3</pron><defn>adjective 1 good; fine; nice (opp. 坏) 好人 hǎorén nice person 祖国的好儿子 Zǔguó de hǎo érzi worthy (or fine) son of our country 庄稼长得真好。 Zhuāngjia zhǎng de zhēn hǎo. The crops are growing well. 2 friendly; kind 好朋友 Hǎo péngyou good (or great) friend 他们对我真好。 Tāmen duì wǒ zhēn hǎo. They are really kind to me. 俩孩子又好了。 Liǎ háizi yòu hǎo le. The two children are friends again. 3 be in good health; get well 你好哇！ Nǐ hǎo wa! How are you? 我的病好了。 Wǒ de bìng hǎo le. I’m well (or all right) now. 4 be ready; done 饭好了。 Fàn hǎo le. The food (or rice) is ready. 5 [after verbs to indicate finishing or finishing satisfactorily] 我把他的病治好了。 Wǒ bǎ tā de bìng zhì hǎo le. I cured his illness. 这件事他做不好。 Zhè jiàn shì tā zuò bù hǎo. He can’t do this job well. 坐好吧, 要开会了。 Zuò hǎo ba, yào kāihuì le. Take your seats, please. The meeting is going to begin. 6 [before verbs to denote what is satisfying] good; easy 好吃 hǎochī good to eat—delicious 暖瓶放在这儿好拿。 Nuǎnpíng fàng zài zhèr hǎo ná. It’s handy to have the thermos here. 这本书可不好买。 Zhè běn shū kě bù hǎo mǎi. This book is not easily available. 这个问题好回答。 Zhège wèntí hǎo huídá. This question is easy to answer. 7 [at the beginning of a sentence or clause, to express agreement, disapproval, surprise, etc.] 好, 就这么办。 Hǎo, jiù zhème bàn. OK, it’s settled. 好了, 不要再说了。 Hǎo le, bùyào zài shuō le. All right, no need to say any more. 好！ 那得多少钱！ Hǎo! Nà dé duōshao qián! Gosh! How much money will that cost! 好,  这下可麻烦了。 Hǎo, zhè xià kě máfan le. Well, we’re in for trouble now. 
adverb 1 [before adjectives with exclamatory force] very; quite; so 好大的工程！ Hǎo dà de gōngchéng! What a huge project! 你好大胆子。 Nǐ hǎo dà dǎnzi. You are so daring. 2 dialect [before adjectives in the same way as 多] to what extent; how 火车站离这儿好远？ Huǒchēzhàn lí zhèr hǎo yuǎn？ How far is the railway station from here? 3 [before indefinite time or numbers] quite 好半天 hǎobàntiān quite a while 好几个 hǎojǐgè quite a few 好几天 hǎojǐtiān quite a few days 
verb produce favourable effects 这事可好了他了。 Zhè shì kě hǎo le tā le. This will benefit him. 
auxiliary 1 the better to; in order to; so that 把她的地址告诉我, 我好找她。 Bǎ tā de dìzhǐ gàosu wǒ, wǒ hǎo zhǎo tā. Tell me her address so that I can go and see her. 今儿早点睡, 明儿好早起赶火车。 Jīnr zǎodiǎn shuì, míngr hǎo zǎoqǐ gǎn huǒchē. Let’s turn in early, so as to get up early tomorrow to catch the train. 2 dialect may; can; should 我好进来吗？ Wǒ hǎo jìnlai ma？ May I come in? 时间不早了, 你好走了。 Shíjiān bù zǎo le, nǐhǎo zǒu le. It’s getting late. You ought to get going.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22429952"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">请问</headword><headword charset="tc">請問</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">qing3wen4</pron><defn>verb 1 courteous excuse me; please 请问, 到火车站怎么走？ Qǐngwèn, dào huǒchēzhàn zěnme zǒu？ Excuse me, but could you tell me how to get to the station? 2 we should like to ask; it may be asked; one may ask 请问, 要不是改革开放, 我们的经济建设能有今天吗？ Qǐngwèn,  yào bù shì gǎigé kāifàng, wǒmen de jīngjì jiànshè néng yǒu jīntiān ma？ I’d like to ask, without reform and the open policy, could our economic development be what it is today?</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="28674560"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">请</headword><headword charset="tc">請</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">qing3</pron><defn>verb 1 request; ask 请人来修机器 Qǐng rén lái xiū jīqì get sb. to repair the machine; get the machine repaired 请他进来。 Qǐng tā jìnlai. Ask him in. 请你多加指导。 Qǐng nǐ duō jiā zhǐdǎo. It is hoped you will give us guidance. 2 invite; engage 请医生 qǐng yīshēng send for a doctor 请总工程师来讲课 qǐng zǒnggōngchéngshī lái jiǎngkè invite the chief engineer to give a lecture 3 courteous please 请坐。 Qǐngzuò. Won’t you sit down? or Please be seated. 请安静。 Qǐng ānjìng. Be quiet, please. 请速回信。 Qǐngsùhuíxìn. Please reply as soon as possible. 4 dated buy holy sacrificial things, such as joss sticks, candles, paper horses and Buddha shrines</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="28669952"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">问</headword><headword charset="tc">問</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">wen4</pron><defn>verb 1 ask; inquire (opp. 答) 问个问题 wèn ge wèntí ask (or pose) a question 不懂就问。 Bù dǒng jiù wèn. Ask when you don’t know. 他在食堂问了一下开饭的时间。 Tā zài shítáng wèn le yīxià kāifàn de shíjiān. He inquired about meal times at the canteen. 2 ask (or inquire) after 他信里问起你。 Tā xìn lǐ wèn qǐ nǐ. He asks after you in his letter. 帮我问教授们好。 bāng wǒ wèn jiàoshòu men hǎo. Please give my regards to the professors. 3 interrogate; examine 审问 shěnwèn interrogate; question 4 hold responsible; intervene 出了事唯你是问。 Chū le shì wéi nǐ shì wèn. You’ll be held responsible if anything goes wrong. 5 Chinese medicine (one of the four methods of diagnosis) interrogate 
preposition ask (sb.) for sth. 我去问他借那本书。 Wǒ qù wèn tā jiè nà běn shū. I’ll ask him to lend me the book. 
noun 1 literary message; letter; news 音问 yīnwèn message; news; tidings 2 question 发问 fāwèn ask (or pose) a question</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="32372736"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">叫</headword><headword charset="tc">叫</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jiao4</pron><defn>verb 1 cry; shout 大叫一声 dà jiào yī shēng give a loud cry; shout; cry out loudly 2 call; greet 外边有人叫你。 Wàibian yǒu rén jiào nǐ. Somebody outside is calling you. 这孩子很腼腆, 不爱叫人。 Zhè háizi hěn miǎntiǎn, bù ài jiào rén. The child is shy and doesn’t like to greet people. 3 hire; order 叫个出租车 jiào ge chūzūchē hire (or call) a taxi 叫一份外卖的比萨饼 jiào yī fèn wàimài de bǐsàbǐng order a takeaway pizza 4 name; call 人们叫他小张。 Rénmen jiào tā xiǎo zhāng. People call him Xiao Zhang. 他叫什么名儿？ Tā jiào shénme míngr？ What’s his name? 这棉花长得真叫棒。 Zhè miánhua zhǎng de zhēn jiào bàng. That’s what I call a really good crop of cotton. 这能叫虚心接受批评吗？ zhè néng jiào xūxīn jiēshòu pīpíng ma? Can this be called readiness to accept criticism? 
adjective dialect male (animal) See 24034560叫驴jiao4lv2叫驴 
verb 1 ask; order; tell 叫他进来吗？ Jiào tā jìnlai ma？ Shall I ask him (to come) in? 医生叫她卧床休息。 Yīshēng jiào tā wòchuáng xiūxi. The doctor told her to stay in bed. 2 permit; allow 他哥哥不叫他去。 Tā gēge bù jiào tā qù. His brother did not allow him to go. 
preposition [in a passive sentence to introduce the doer of the action] 叫你猜着了。 Jiào nǐ cāizháo le. You’ve guessed right. 你叫雨淋湿了吗？ Nǐ jiào yǔ lín shī le ma？ Did you get wet?</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="24030464"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">什么</headword><headword charset="tc">什麼</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shen2me5</pron><defn>pronoun 1 [before a noun or by itself] what 什么时候啦？ Shénme shíhou la？ What time is it? 什么叫超现实主义？ Shénme jiào chāoxiànshízhǔyì？ What is surrealism? 你找什么？ Nǐ zhǎo shénme？ What are you looking for? 你找什么人？ Nǐ zhǎo shénme rén？ Who are you looking for? 她喜欢做什么工作？ Tā xǐhuan zuò shénme gōngzuò？ What sort of job would she like to take? 什么风把你吹来的？ shénme fēng bǎ nǐ chuī lái de? What fortunate breeze blew you here? 2 something; anything 我想吃点儿什么。 Wǒ xiǎng chī diǎnrshénme. I want something to eat. 没有什么, 您不必介意。 Méiyǒu shénme, nín bùbì jièyì. Never mind, it’s nothing. 你读过他的什么作品吗？ Nǐ dú guò tā de shénme zuòpǐn ma？ Have you read any of his books? 我讲不出什么新鲜玩意儿。 Wǒ jiǎng bù chū shénme xīnxiān wányìr. There won’t be anything new in my story. 种什么花结什么果。 zhòng shénme huājié shénme guǒ. As the flower so the fruit. 3 [before 也 or 都] any; every 他什么都不怕。 Tā shénme dōu bù pà. He’s afraid of nothing. 经理正忙着, 什么人也不见。 Jīnglǐ zhèng mángzhe, shénme rén yě bù jiàn. The manager is too busy to see anybody. 时间比什么都宝贵。 Shíjiān bǐ shénme dōu bǎoguì. Time is more precious than anything else. 4 [used correlatively with another 什么] whatever 有什么, 咱们就吃什么。 Yǒu shénme, zánmen jiù chī shénme. We’ll eat whatever we can find. 我有什么说什么, 绝对没有保留。 Wǒ yǒu shénme shuō shénme, juéduì méiyǒu bǎoliú. I’ll just say what’s on my mind, withholding nothing. 5 [expressing anger, surprise, censure or negation] 什么！ 没有水？ Shénme! Méiyǒu shuǐ？ What! No water? 他知道什么！ Tā zhīdao shénme! What the hell does he know? 你说的是什么话！ Nǐ shuō de shì shénme huà! You’re talking sheer nonsense! 笑什么？有什么可笑的？ Xiào shénme？ Yǒu shénme kěxiào de？ What’s so funny? 你说呀！ 装什么哑巴？ Nǐ shuō ya! Zhuāng shénme yǎba？ Speak up! Stop playing dumb. 你嚷嚷什么！ 有话好好儿的对她说嘛。 Nǐ rāngrang shénme! Yǒu huà hǎohāor de duì tā shuō ma. Stop shouting! Speak to her nicely. 6 [expressing disapproval or disagreement] 什么不懂！ 装糊涂就是了。 Shénme bù dǒng! Zhuāng hútu jiùshìle. What do you mean—not understand? You’re just pretending. 年轻什么呀, 我都五十多了。 Niánqīng shénme ya, wǒ dōu wǔshí duō le. Young indeed! I’m past 50 already. 给您添麻烦了！ —— 麻烦什么！ Gěi nín tiān máfan le! —— Máfan shénme! Sorry to have troubled you.—It’s nothing. 7 things like; such as; and so on; and what not 什么缝缝补补, 洗洗涮涮, 都是奶奶的事儿。 Shénme féngféngbǔbǔ,  xǐ xǐ shuàn shuàn, dōu shì nǎinai de shìr. In our house it’s Grandma who does all the sewing, mending, washing and what not. 什么乒乓球啊, 羽毛球啊, 篮球啊, 他都会玩。 Shénme Pīngpāngqiú a,  yǔmáoqiú a,  lánqiú a, tā dōu huì wán. He can play table tennis, badminton, basketball, anything.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="29771776"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">名字</headword><headword charset="tc">名字</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ming2zi5</pron><defn>noun 1 name; given name 您叫什么名字？ Nín jiào shénme míngzi？ What’s your name? or May I know your name? 2 name (of a thing) 这种花的名字很特别。 Zhèzhǒng huā de míngzi hěn tèbié. This flower has a strange name. 3 dated linguistics noun</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26914048"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">我</headword><headword charset="tc">我</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">wo3</pron><defn>pronoun 1 I; me 2 we; us 敌退我追。 dí tuì wǒ zhuī. We pursue the enemy if they retreat. 3 my; our 我方 wǒfāng our side; we 我国 wǒguó our country 我家 wǒjiā my family; my home 我军 wǒjūn our army 4 [with 你 in parallel structures] one; anyone 大家你帮我, 我帮你, 很快就把活儿干完了。 Dàjiā nǐ bāng wǒ,  wǒ bāng nǐ, hěn kuài jiù bǎ huór gàn wán le. Everyone pitched in and the job was soon done. 5 self 忘我 wàngwǒ oblivious of oneself 自我 zìwǒ self; oneself</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="32397056"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">呢</headword><headword charset="tc">呢</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ne5</pron><defn>auxiliary 1 [at the end of a special, alternative, or rhetorical question] 你刚才到哪儿去了呢？ Nǐ gāngcái dào nǎr qù le ne？ Where were you just now? 你到底认不认得她呢？ Nǐ dào dǐ rèn bù rèn de tā ne？ Do you know her or not? 你对这件事是赞成呢, 还是反对呢？ Nǐ duì zhè jiàn shì shì zànchéng ne, hái shì fǎnduì ne？ Are you for or against this? 他们都有任务了, 我呢？ Tāmen dōu yǒu rènwu le, wǒ ne? They’ve got assignments, what about me? 我错在哪儿呢？ Wǒ cuò zài nǎr ne？ What is my mistake? 我怎么能不记得呢？ Wǒ zěnme néng bù jìde ne？ How could I forget this? 这点子事, 何必大惊小怪呢？ Zhè diǎnzi shì, hébì dàjīngxiǎoguài ne？ Why get so excited over such a little thing? 2 [at the end of a declarative sentence to reinforce the assertion] 远得很, 有好几千里地呢。 Yuǎn de hěn, yǒu hǎo jǐqiān lǐ dì ne. It’s a long way off—thousands of li away. 3 [at the end of a declarative sentence to indicate the continuation of an action or a state] 他还在生气呢。 Tā hái zài shēngqì ne. He’s still angry. 张先生, 有人找你呢。 Zhāng xiānsheng, yǒurén zhǎo nǐ ne. Mr Zhang, somebody is looking for you. 4 [used to mark a pause] 不下雨呢, 就去;下雨呢, 就不去。 Bù xià yǔ ne,  jiù qù ； xiàyǔ ne, jiù bù qù. If it doesn’t rain, we’ll go; if it does, we won’t. 如今呢, 可比以往任何时候都要强。 Rújīn ne, kě bǐ yǐwǎng rènhé shíhou dōu yào qiáng. As for the present, things are far better than at any time in the past.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27237376"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">认识</headword><headword charset="tc">認識</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ren4shi5</pron><defn>verb know; understand; recognize 认识自己的错误 rènshi zìjǐ de cuòwù see (or realize) one’s mistake 认识世界, 改造世界 Rènshi shìjiè, gǎizào shìjiè understand the world and change it 他不认识这种草药。 Tā bù rènshi zhèzhǒng cǎoyào. He doesn’t recognize this kind of medical herb. 
noun philosophy understanding; knowledge; cognition 感性认识 gǎnxìngrènshi perceptual knowledge 理性认识 lǐxìngrènshi rational knowledge</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="29052160"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">很</headword><headword charset="tc">很</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hen3</pron><defn>adverb very; very much; quite 很满意 Hěn mǎnyì feel very satisfied; feel quite pleased 很有道理 hěn yǒu dàoli contain much truth; be quite correct 这几天热得很。 Zhè jǐ tiān rè de hěn. It’s been very hot these last few days. 他这个人好得很。 Tā zhège rén hǎo de hěn. He’s a very good man. 他觉得很不好受。 Tā juéde hěn bù hǎoshòu. He felt very bad. 我家离学校很近。 Wǒ jiā lí xuéxiào hěn jìn. I live quite near the school. 我近来身体不很好。 Wǒ jìnlái shēntǐ bù hěn hǎo. I haven’t felt very well recently. 现在他口袋里很有几个钱。 Xiànzài tā kǒudài lǐ hěn yǒu jǐ ge qián. He’s made himself quite a nice little pile. 这故事发生在很久很久以前。 Zhè gùshi fāshēng zài hěn jiǔ hěn jiǔ yǐqián. The story took place a long long time ago.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22606848"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">高兴</headword><headword charset="tc">高興</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">gao1xing4</pron><defn>adjective glad; happy; cheerful (opp. 伤心) 看到孩子们有进步, 他心里很高兴。 kàndào háizimen yǒu jìnbù, tā xīnli hěn gāoxìng. He was very pleased to see that the kids had made progress. 小强高高兴兴地上学去了。 Xiǎo qiáng gāogāoxìngxìng de shàngxué qù le. Xiao Qiang cheerfully went off to school. 两人谈得可高兴了。 Liǎng rén tán de kě gāoxìng le. The two of them chatted merrily. 我们昨天玩得真高兴。 Wǒmen zuótiān wán de zhēn gāoxìng. We had a wonderful time yesterday. 
verb 1 be glad; be happy; be cheerful 他平时话不多, 高兴时才说上几句。 Tā píngshí huà bù duō, gāoxìng shí cái shuōshàng jǐ jù. He’s usually reticent and only talks a little when in high spirits. 把这消息告诉你爷爷, 叫他老人家也高兴高兴。 Bǎ zhè xiāoxi gàosu nǐ yéye, jiào tā lǎorenjia yě gāoxìng gāoxìng. Tell Grandpa the good news so that he can share our joy. 他们高兴得太早了。 Tāmen gāoxìng de tài zǎo le. They rejoiced too soon. 2 be willing to; be happy to 你不高兴就甭去了。 Nǐ bù gāoxìng jiù béng qùle. You needn’t go if you don’t feel like it. 他就是高兴看电影, 对看戏不感兴趣。 Tā jiùshì gāoxìng kàn diànyǐng, duì kànxì bù gǎn xìngqù. He’s fond of seeing films, and not at all interested in watching plays.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="21519104"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">小姐</headword><headword charset="tc">小姐</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xiao3jie3</pron><defn>noun 1 dated young (unmarried) lady 2 Miss 张小姐 zhāng xiǎojie Miss Zhang 3 euphemistic prostitute; street girl</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33186817"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">对不起</headword><headword charset="tc">對不起</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">dui4bu5qi3</pron><defn>common phrase I&apos;m sorry; sorry; excuse me; pardon me; I beg your pardon 对不起, 给你添麻烦了。 Duìbuqǐ, gěi nǐ tiān máfan le. Sorry to have given you so much trouble. 对不起, 是我的错。 Duìbuqǐ, shì wǒ de cuò. I am sorry, it was my fault. 对不起, 我得走了。 Duìbuqǐ, wǒ děi zǒu le. Excuse me, but I must go now. 对不起, 请你再讲一遍好吗？ Duìbuqǐ, qǐng nǐ zài jiǎng yī biàn hǎo ma？ I beg your pardon, would you repeat what you said? or I beg your pardon? 
verb let sb. down; unworthy of; unfair to (opp. 对得起) 球队输了球, 大伙儿觉得对不起教练。 Qiúduì shū le qiú, dàhuǒr juéde duìbuqǐ jiàoliàn. The team lost and felt they had let the coach down. 他对不起她, 本来答应跟她结婚, 后来却把她甩了。 Tā duìbuqǐ tā, běnlái dāying gēn tā jiéhūn, hòulái què bǎ tā shuǎile. He treated her shabbily by first promising to marry her and then jilting her.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="20383232"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">姓</headword><headword charset="tc">姓</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xing4</pron><defn>noun surname; family (or clan) name “张”是大姓。 “zhāng” shì dà xìng. “Zhang” is a common Chinese surname. 
verb be surnamed 他姓王。 Tā xìng wáng. He is surnamed Wang. or His surname is Wang. 您贵姓？——敝姓陈。 Nín guìxìng？ —— bì xìng chén. May I know your surname? — (My surname is) Chen. 姓“资”还是姓“社” xìng “zī” háishixìng “shè” socialist or capitalist; pertaining to socialism or capitalism</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33549056"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">中文</headword><headword charset="tc">中文</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Zhong1wen2</pron><defn>noun Chinese (language or writing) (opp. 外文) 中文书刊 Zhōngwén shūkān books and magazines in Chinese 中文系 Zhōngwénxì Chinese department 中文信息处理 Zhōngwén xìnxī chǔlǐ Chinese data processing</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="36386560"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">是</headword><headword charset="tc">是</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shi4</pron><defn>verb 1 [used like “be” before nouns or pronouns to identify, describe or amplify the subject] 我是医生。 wǒ shì yīshēng. I am a doctor. 《阿Ｑ正传》的作者是鲁迅。 《Ā Q Zhèng Zhuàn》 de zuòshì shì Lǔ Xùn. The author of The True Story of Ah Q is Lu Xun. 他真心爱的是你。 Tā zhēn xīn&apos;ài de shì nǐ. You are the girl he truly loves. 她还是一身中学生打扮。 Tā háishì yī shēn zhōngxuéshēng dǎban. She still dresses like a high school girl. 2 [after nouns denoting place or position to express existence] 遍地是鲜花。 Biàn dì shì xiānhuā. The place is covered with flowers. 前面是一片稻田。 Qiánmian shì yī piàn dàotián. There is a stretch of rice fields ahead. 他满身是汗。 Tā mǎnshēn shì hàn. He is sweating all over. 3 [with 的 at the end of the sentence, to indicate category, characteristic, etc.] 我是教书的。 Wǒ shì jiāoshū de. I am a teacher. 那儿的房屋是木头的。 Nàr de fángwū shì mùtou de. The houses there are built of wood. 马路边净是看热闹的。 Mǎlù biān jìng shì kàn rènao de. The street was crowded with people watching the excitement. 4 [emphasizing a certain part of a sentence] a [before the subject to stress it] 是谁告诉你的？ Shì shuí gàosu nǐ de？ Who told you? 花瓶是我妹妹摔破的。 Huāpíng shì wǒ mèimei shuāi pò de. It was my sister who broke the vase. b [after a verb or adjective plus 的, to stress the predicate] 说的正是你。 Shuō de zhèngshì nǐ. It’s you we are talking about. 可惜的是浪费了这么多时间。 Kěxī deshì làngfèi le zhème duō shíjiān. It’s a pity we’ve wasted so much time. 麻烦的是他生病来不了。 Máfan de shì tā shēngbìng láibuliǎo. The trouble is he’s taken ill and can’t come. c [before the object, adverbial, etc. to be stressed] 我是专程去看老王的。 Wǒ shì zhuānchéng qù kàn lǎo wáng de. I made a special trip to see Lao Wang. 他们看的是话剧, 不是电影。 Tāmen kàn de shì huàjù, bù shì diànyǐng. They went to see a play, not a film. or What they saw was a play, not a film. 好好的一次郊游搞成这样子, 都是你！ Hǎo hǎo de yī cì jiāoyóu gǎo chéng zhè yàngzi, dōu shì nǐ! It was all your fault the outing became such a flop. d [pronounced with stress; indicating certainty] 他是去了。 Tā shì qù le. He did go. 天气是冷。 Tiānqì shì lěng. It is cold indeed. 他的工作效率是高。 Tā de gōngzuò xiàolǜ shì gāo. He is really efficient. 5 be just right 这场雨下的是时候。 Zhè cháng yǔ xià de shì shíhou. This rain has come at just the right time. 工具放的不是地方。 Gōngjù fàng de bù shì dìfāng. The tools are not put in the right place. 6 [before nouns at the beginning of the sentence, followed by 都 or 就] every; all; any 是公众的事, 大家都要关心。 Shì gōngzhòng de shì, dàjiā dōu yào guānxīn. Whatever concerns the public concerns us all. 是什么样的老师, 就教出什么样的学生。 Shì shénmeyàng de lǎoshī, jiù jiào chū shénmeyàng de xuésheng. Like teacher, like student. 是什么种子, 就开出什么花。 Shì shénme zhǒngzi, jiù kāi chū shénme huā. Each kind of seed produces its own flowers. 7 [between two identical words] a [used together with 就 or 总 to indicate actuality] 事实总是事实, 谁也否认不了的。 Shìshí zǒng shì shìshí, shuí yě fǒurèn bùliǎo de. Facts are facts, and no one can deny them. 不懂就是不懂, 不要装懂。 Bù dǒng jiù shì bù dǒng, bùyào zhuāng dǒng. If you don’t know, you don’t know, don’t pretend. b [in a clause of concession] 工作忙是忙, 可是大家很愉快。 Gōngzuò máng shì máng, kě shì dàjiā hěn yúkuài. We are busy to be sure, but every one is very happy. 诗是好诗, 就是长了点儿。 Shī shì hǎo shī, jiùshì cháng le diǎnr. It is a good poem all right, but it’s a bit too long. 这东西旧是旧, 但还可以用。 Zhè dōngxi jiù shì jiù, dàn hái kěyǐ yòng. Yes, it’s old, but it can still be used. c [in two parallel clauses to indicate mutual exclusiveness] 他是他, 我是我, 我们毫不相干。 Tā shì tā,  wǒ shì wǒ, wǒmen háobùxiānggān. He is he, I am I; we have nothing to do with each other. d [in two or three parallel clauses to indicate thoroughness or excellence of performance] 他演得真好, 表情是表情, 身段是身段, 做功是做功。 Tā yǎn de zhēn hǎo,  biǎoqíng shì biǎoqíng,  shēnduàn shì shēnduàn, zuògōng shì zuò gōng. He is a marvellous actor; his expressions, movements, and gestures are the best. 8 [in yes-no questions] 你是不是明天去游泳？ (= 你是明天去游泳不是？) Nǐ shì bù shì míngtiān qù yóuyǒng？ (or) nǐ shì míngtiān qù yóuyǒng bù shì？ Are you going swimming tomorrow? 9 [in alternative questions] 你坐火车呢, 还是坐汽车？ Nǐ zuò huǒchē ne, hái shì zuò qìchē? Are you going by train or by bus? 这件事是真是假, 谁也搞不清。 Zhè jiàn shì shì zhēn shì jiǎ, shuí yě gǎo bù qīng. Nobody knows whether it’s true or not. 
verb 1 [in affirmative answers] yes; right 是, 我就去。 Shì, wǒ jiù qù. Yes, I’ll go right away. 是, 我们一定完成任务。 Shì, wǒmen yīdìng wánchéng rènwu. Right, we will complete the task. 2 literary praise; justify See 30253568是古非今shi4gu3fei1jin1是古非今 
adjective correct; right 你说得是。 Nǐ shuō de shì. What you said is right. or You are quite right. 应当早做准备才是。 Yīngdāng zǎo zuò zhǔnbèi cái shì. Preparing early is the right thing to do. or It’s right to prepare early. 
noun right (opp. 非) See 30252288是非shi4fei1是非 
pronoun literary this; that 如是 rúshì like this 由是可知 Yóu shì kězhī from this you can see 是日天气晴朗。 Shì rì tiānqì qínglǎng. It was fine that day. or It was a fine day.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30251008"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">你们</headword><headword charset="tc">你們</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ni3men5</pron><defn>pronoun 1 you [second person plural] 你们干护士工作的真是够辛苦的。 nǐmen gàn hùshi gōngzuò de zhēnshì gòu xīnkǔ de. You nurses are really working very hard. 这就是你们的责任所在。 Zhè jiùshì nǐmen de zérèn suǒzài. This is where your responsibility lies. 2 colloquial [in the same way as 你 1 2] 你们奶奶多大岁数了？ Nǐmen nǎinai duō dà suìshu le？ How old is your grandmother? 你们组最近情况怎么样？ Nǐmen zǔ zuìjìn qíngkuàng zěnmeyàng？ How is your group getting along these days?</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27305216"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">大家</headword><headword charset="tc">大家</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">da4jia1</pron><defn>pronoun all; everybody 大家知道, 中国是一个发展中国家。 Dàjiā zhīdao, Zhōngguó shì yī ge fāzhǎnzhōng guójiā. As everybody knows, China is a developing country. 我报告大家一个好消息。 Wǒ bàogào dàjiā yī ge hǎo xiāoxi. I have some good news for you all. 
noun 1 great master; authority 书法大家 shūfǎ dà jiā great master of calligraphy 2 old and well-known family; distinguished (or prominent) family 大家闺秀 dàjiāguīxiù girl from a good family; well-bred girl; lady</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19435520"/><catassign category="Lektion1"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">早上好</headword><headword charset="tc">早上好</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zao3 shang5 hao3</pron><defn> 早 early; soon; morningRadical: 日; Stroke count: 6; HSK level: 2; General Standard: #419; Frequency rank: 462 上 top; superior, highest; go up, send upRadical: 一; Stroke count: 3; HSK level: 1; General Standard: #36; Frequency rank: 16 好 good, excellent, fine; wellRadical: 女; Stroke count: 6; HSK level: 1; General Standard: #581; Frequency rank: 82</defn></entry><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">日本</headword><headword charset="tc">日本</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Ri4ben3</pron><defn>Japan</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="29074176"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">人</headword><headword charset="tc">人</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ren2</pron><defn>noun 1 human being; person; people 活人 huórén living person 人对自然界的认识 Rén duì zìránjiè de rènshi man’s knowledge of nature 团结得像一个人 tuánjié de xiàng yī ge rén (of many people) be united as one 来人了。 lái rén le. Someone has come. or There come some people. 他家有几口人？ Tā jiā yǒu jǐ kǒu rén？ How many people are there in his family? 屋里有人吗？ Wū lǐ yǒurén ma？ Is there anyone inside? 2 adult human being 长大成人 zhǎngdà chéngrén grow up into an adult; be grown to manhood 3 other people; other(s) 他待人诚恳。 Tā dàirén chéngkěn. He’s sincere in his dealings with people. 这个座位有人吗？ Zhè ge zuòwèi yǒurén ma？ Is this seat occupied? 自己做错了事, 不应该怪人。 Zìjǐ zuò cuò liǎoshì, bù yīnggāi guàirén. When one has done something wrong one should not blame it on others. 4 [used rhetorically in place of the first personal pronoun, often expressing displeasure] 别小看人！ Bié xiǎokàn rén! Don’t look down on me! 真叫人着急。 Zhēn jiào rén zháojí. It really worries me. 5 person considered as a worker or employee; hand; manpower 人来了吗？ rén lái le ma? Have they come? 我们这里正缺人。 Wǒmen zhèlǐ zhèng quē rén. We are short-handed at the moment. 6 physical, psychological, or moral quality or condition of a given individual; personality 他人很好。 Tā rén hěn hǎo. He’s a very nice man. 这两天我人不太舒服。 Zhè liǎng tiān wǒ rén bù tài shūfu. I haven’t been feeling very well lately. 他人在那儿, 心却想着别的事。 Tā rén zài nàr, xīn què xiǎngzhe bié de shì. He was there all right, but his mind was elsewhere. 7 everybody; each 人各有所喜。 rén gè yǒusuǒ xǐ. Everyone has his liking. 8 [as a suffix] person of certain places, jobs or properties; person engaging in certain activity 四川人 Sìchuān rén native of Sichuan 文化人 wénhuàrén man of letters; intellectual 音乐人 yīnyuèrén musician; person engaging in music 他是你什么人？ Tā shì nǐ shénmerén? What is your relation with him? 9 real person; true man; man of integrity 是人就得说人话。 Shì rén jiùděi shuō rén huà. A real man should talk like a real man. 这是人做的事吗？ Zhè shì rén zuò de shì ma? Can this be the behaviour of a true man?</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="28962304"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">吗</headword><headword charset="tc">嗎</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ma5</pron><defn>auxiliary 1 [at the end of a question] 你找我有事吗？ Nǐ zhǎo wǒ yǒu shì ma？ Do you want to see me about something? 明天他来吗？ Míngtiān tā lái ma？ Will he come tomorrow? 下午有会吗？ Xiàwǔ yǒu huì ma？ Is there a meeting this afternoon? 2 [as a pause in a sentence before introducing the main point] 特殊情况吗, 还得特殊对待。 Tèshū qíngkuàng ma, hái dé tèshū duìdài. Special cases, of course, need special consideration. 这件事吗, 其实也不能怪他。 Zhè jiàn shì ma, qíshí yě bù néng guài tā. This problem, actually, is not his fault. 3 [at the end of a rhetorical question] 你发这么大脾气像话吗？ Nǐ fā zhème dà píqi xiànghuà ma？ Aren’t you ashamed of flying into such a rage? 你难道没看见我正忙着吗？ Nǐ nándào méi kànjian wǒ zhèng mángzhe ma？ Don’t you see I’m busy at the moment? 这不是很明白的吗？ Zhè bù shì hěn míngbai de ma？ Isn’t this perfectly clear?</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26467328"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">不</headword><headword charset="tc">不</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">bu4</pron><defn>adverb 1 [before verbs, adjectives, and other adverbs; never before the verb 有] not; won&apos;t; not want to 我不会。 Wǒ bù huì. I don’t know how. 我不去。 Wǒ bù qù. I’m not going. or I won’t go. 他不是学生。 Tā bù shì xuésheng. He isn’t a student. 他的病不(很)严重。 Tā de bìng bù (hěn) yánzhòng. His illness is not (very) serious. 他昨天不来, 可是今天来了。 Tā zuótiān bù lái, kěshì jīntiān lái le. He didn’t come yesterday, but came today. 2 [before certain nouns to form an adjective] un-; in- 不法 bùfǎ illegal; lawless 不轨 bùguǐ against the law 不道德 bùdàodé immoral 不自在 bùzìzai ill at ease; uncomfortable 3 [used alone or with a particle in responses] not so; no 您再吃一点儿吧。——不了, 谢谢。 Nín zài chī yīdiǎnr ba. —— Bù liǎo, xièxie. How about having some more? —No more, thanks. 他不知道吧？——不, 他知道。 Tā bù zhīdao ba？ —— bù, tā zhīdao. He doesn’t know, does he? —Yes, he does. 他是上海人。——不是吧。 Tā shì Shànghǎi rén. ——bù shìba. He comes from Shanghai. —No, I don’t think so. 他知道吗？——不, 他不知道。 Tā zhīdao ma？ —— bù, tā bù zhīdao. Does he know? —No, he doesn’t. 4 colloquial [at the end of a sentence to indicate a question] 你要咖啡不？ Nǐ yào kāfēi bù? Some coffee? 他现在身体好不？ Tā xiànzài shēntǐ hǎo bù？ Is he in good health now? 5 [between a verb and its complement] cannot 打不开 dǎbùkāi unable to open 进不去 jìnbùqù cannot go in 拿不动 nábùdòng (find sth.) too heavy to carry 6 [inserted within a reduplication, usu. preceded by 什么] no matter (how, where, etc.) 什么难学不难学, 我保证学会。 Shénme nán xué bù nán xué, wǒ bǎozhèng xuéhuì. No matter how hard I’ll learn it. 什么学历不学历, 要有真才实学才行。 Shénme xuélì bù xuélì, yào yǒu zhēncáishíxué cái xíng. Formal schooling is all very well, but what matters is real knowledge and ability. 7 [used correlatively with 就] if not... (then...); either...or 他这会儿不(是)在教室, 就(是)在图书馆。 Tā zhèhuìr bù shì zài jiàoshì, jiùshì zài túshūguǎn. At this time, he’s either in the classroom or in the library. 晚上他不是看书, 就是看报。 Wǎnshang tā bù shì kànshū, jiùshì kànbào. In the evening he either reads a book or a newspaper. 8 [in polite formulas only] don&apos;t; needn&apos;t 不谢。 bù xiè. Don’t mention it.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="17886464"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">哪里</headword><headword charset="tc">哪裡</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">na3li5</pron><defn>pronoun 1 where 你哪里不舒服？ Nǐ nǎli bù shūfu？ What is bothering you? or Where do you feel pain? 你到哪里去？ Nǐ dào nǎli qù？ Where are you going? 你是哪里人？ Nǐ shì nǎli rén？ Where are you from? 2 wherever; where 哪里最艰苦就在哪里干 nǎli zuì jiānkǔ jiù zài nǎli gàn go where is hardest 哪里有压迫, 哪里就有反抗。 Nǎli yǒu yāpò, nǎli jiù yǒu fǎnkàng. Where there is oppression, there is resistance. 3 [in rhetorical questions to express negation] 我哪里知道他会改变主意的？ Wǒ nǎli zhīdao tā huì gǎibiàn zhǔyi de？ How was I to know he should change his mind? 4 polite expression [a polite reply to a compliment] 你的英语说得真好。——哪里, 哪里。 Nǐ de Yīngyǔ shuō de zhēn hǎo. —— Nǎli, nǎli. You speak very good English. — I’m flattered. 你对我们帮助很大。——哪里, 哪里。 Nǐ duì wǒmen bāngzhù hěn dà. —— Nǎli, nǎli. You helped us a lot. — It was nothing.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27121920"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">哪</headword><headword charset="tc">哪</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">na3</pron><defn>pronoun 1 [in questions] which; what 你学的是哪国语言？ Nǐ xué de shì nǎ guó yǔyán？ What foreign language are you studying? 我们这里有两位姓张的, 您要找的是哪一位？ Wǒmen zhèlǐ yǒu liǎng wèi xìng zhāng de, nín yào zhǎo de shì nǎ yī wèi？ We’ve got two Zhangs here. Which one do you want? 2 [in statements to indicate sth. indefinite] whichever; any that 哪天有空就请过来。 Nǎ tiān yǒukòng jiù qǐng guòlai. Come over whenever you are free. 你喜欢哪件就拿哪件。 Nǐ xǐhuannǎ jiàn jiù ná nǎ jiàn. Take whichever you prefer. 
adverb [in rhetorical questions to express negation] 哪有这样的事？ Nǎ yǒu zhèyàng de shì？ Nothing of the sort (or kind)! 没有昨天的流血牺牲, 哪有今天的幸福生活？ Méiyǒu zuótiān de liúxuè xīshēng, nǎ yǒu jīntiān de xìngfú shēnghuó? Without past sacrifices how could we have such a happy life today?</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27120384"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">中国</headword><headword charset="tc">中國</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Zhong1guo2</pron><defn>noun China 中国大陆 Zhōngguó dàlù Chinese mainland; mainland of China 中国画 Zhōngguóhuà traditional Chinese painting 中国话 Zhōngguóhuà Chinese (language) 中国结 zhōngguójié traditional Chinese knot 中国热 Zhōngguórè Sinomania (great interest in Chinese culture) 中国人 Zhōngguórén Chinese 中国网 Zhōngguó wǎng Chinaweb 中国学 zhōngguóxué Sinology 中国字 zhōngguózì Chinese characters; Chinese writing 中国餐馆 Zhōngguó cānguǎn Chinese restaurant 中国象棋 Zhōngguó xiàngqí Xiangqi; Chinese chess 中国猿人 Zhōngguó yuánrén Peking Man 中国概念股 Zhōngguó gàiniàn gǔ “China Concept” shares (sold on the Hong Kong stock market by a large Hong Kong firm whose business is based in China) 中国工程院 Zhōngguó Gōngchéngyuàn Chinese Academy of Engineering 中国共产党 Zhōngguó Gòngchǎndǎng Communist Party of China (CPC); the Chinese Communist Party 中国科学院 Zhōngguó Kēxuéyuàn Chinese Academy of Sciences 中国同盟会 Zhōngguó Tóngménghuì United League of China (1905-1912, predecessor of the Kuomintang 国民党) 中国证监会 Zhōngguó Zhèngjiànhuì China Securities Regulatory Commission 中国工农红军 Zhōngguó Gōng-Nóng Hóngjūn Chinese Workers’and Peasants’ Red Army (1928-1937); the Red Army 中国人民解放军 Zhōngguó Rénmín Jiěfàngjūn Chinese People’s Liberation Army (PLA) 中国人民志愿军 Zhōngguórénmínzhìyuànjūn Chinese People’s Volunteers 中国社会科学院 Zhōngguó Shèhuì Kēxuéyuàn Chinese Academy of Social Sciences 中国新经济峰会 Zhōngguó xīn jīngjì fēnghuì China New Economy Summit 中国移动互联网 Zhōngguó yídòng hùliánwǎng China Mobile Net; CM Net 中国工农民主政府 Zhōngguó Gōng-Nóng Mínzhǔ Zhèngfǔ Chinese Workers’ and Peasants’ Democratic Government (in the revolutionary base areas during the Second Revolutionary Civil War, 1927-1937) 中国出口商品交易会 Zhōngguó chūkǒu shāngpǐn jiāoyìhuì China Export Commodities Fair (Guangzhou Fair) 中国共产主义青年团 Zhōngguó Gòngchǎnzhǔyì Qīngniántuán Communist Youth League of China 中国人民政治协商会议 Zhōngguó Rénmín Zhèngzhì Xiéshāng Huìyì Chinese People’s Political Consultative Conference (CPPCC)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="36360192"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">国</headword><headword charset="tc">國</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">guo2</pron><defn>noun 1 country; nation; state 大国 dàguó a big country 强国 qiángguó a powerful nation 诸侯国 zhūhóu guó feudal states 保家卫国 bǎojiāwèiguó protect our homes and defend our country 利国利民 lìguólìmín benefit both country and people; good for the country and for the people 2 best of the nation See 22188288国手guo2shou3国手;22186496国色guo2se4国色 3 abbreviation Kuomintang (KMT) 国共两党 Guó Gòngliǎngdǎng KMT and CPC 4 (Guó) a surname 
adjective 1 of the state; national See 22161408国花guo2hua1国花 2 of our country; Chinese See 22161664国画guo2hua4国画</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22154752"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">英国</headword><headword charset="tc">英國</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Ying1guo2</pron><defn>noun Britain; England; UK 英国护照 Yīngguó hùzhào British passport</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34809344"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">住</headword><headword charset="tc">住</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zhu4</pron><defn>verb 1 live; reside; stay 住城外 Zhù chéngwài live in the suburbs 住旅馆 zhù lǚguǎn stay at a hotel 对面没人住。 Duìmiàn méi rén zhù. Nobody lives opposite me. 他住在北京。 Tā zhù zài Běijīng. He lives in Beijing. 我住这间屋。 Wǒ zhù zhè jiān wū. I live in this room. or This is my room. 我们住上了新房。 Wǒmen zhù shàng le xīnfáng. We’ve moved into a new house. 2 stop; cease 雨住了。 Yǔ zhù le. The rain has stopped. 等风住了再走。 Děng fēng zhù le zài zǒu. Go when the wind drops. 3 [after a verb] firmly; to a stop 支持不住 zhīchíbuzhù cannot withstand; cannot hold out 拿住了, 别撒手。 Ná zhù le, bié sāshǒu. Hold tight and don’t let go. 她挡住了我的去路。 Tā dǎngzhù le wǒ de qù lù. She blocked my way. 这一下你可把我问住了。 Zhè yī xià nǐ kě bǎ wǒ wèn zhù le. You’ve got me there. or I don’t know what to say. 听到这个消息我一下子愣住了。 Tīngdào zhège xiāoxi wǒ yīxiàzi lèng zhù le. I was struck dumb at the news. 悠扬的小提琴声把我吸引住了。 Yōuyáng de xiǎotíqín shēng bǎ wǒ xīyǐn zhù le. The beautiful notes of a violin held me spellbound.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="36591104"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">在</headword><headword charset="tc">在</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zai4</pron><defn>verb 1 exist; be alive 人在人情在。 Rén zài rénqíng zài. Friendship lasts as long as the person remains. 他父亲还在, 母亲早就不在了。 Tā fùqin hái zài, mǔqin zǎo jiù bù zài le. His father is still alive, but his mother passed away long ago. 她人已去, 但精神永在。 tā rén yǐqù, dàn jīngshén yǒng zài. She is gone, but her spirit lives on. 问题还在, 并没有解决。 Wèntí hái zài, bìng méiyǒu jiějué. The problem still exists and is not resolved yet. 2 be at, in, or on (a place) 你去那儿找他, 他准在。 Nǐ qù nàr zhǎo tā, tā zhǔn zài. Go and see him; he’s sure to be there. 他在家, 不在这儿。 Tā zài jiā, bù zài zhèr. He’s at home, not here. 你的钢笔在桌子上呢。 Nǐ de gāngbǐ zài zhuōzi shàng ne. Your pen is on the table. 我父母在农村。 Wǒ fùmǔ zài nóngcūn. My parents are in the countryside. 3 depend on; rest with 去不去在你自己。 Qù bù qù zài nǐ zìjǐ. It’s up to you whether to go or not. 收不收他在学校领导。 Shōu bù shōu tā zài xuéxiào lǐngdǎo. His admittance rests with the school authorities. 学习好, 主要在自己努力。 Xuéxí hǎo, zhǔyào zài zìjǐ nǔlì. Getting good results in one’s studies depends mainly on one’s own efforts. 4 lie in; consist in 工作人员不在多, 而在有效率。 Gōngzuò rényuán bù zài duō, ér zài yǒu xiàolǜ. A staff need not be large but it must be efficient. 她美就美在那双眼睛。 Tā měi jiù měi zài nà shuāng yǎnjing. Her charm lies in her eyes. 我们的希望在青年一代。 Wǒmen de xīwàng zài qīngnián yīdài. Our hopes lie in the younger generation. 学习贵在坚持。 Xuéxí guì zài jiānchí. Persistence is vital to study. 这首诗妙在含蓄而不明言。 Zhè shǒu shī miào zài hánxù ér bù míng yán. The appeal of this poem lies in inference rather than direct statement. 5 join or belong to an organization; be a member of an organization 在组织 Zài zǔzhī belong to a certain organization 6 be on the job or at the post See 35602688在职zai4zhi2在职 
preposition 1 at, in, or on (a place or time) 在会上发言 Zài huì shàng fāyán speak at a meeting 狗在地上打滚儿。 Gǒu zài dìshang dǎgǔnr. The dog rolled on the ground. 他在工厂工作。 Tā zài gōngchǎng gōngzuò. He works in a factory. 事情发生在去年。 Shìqing fāshēng zài qùnián. It happened last year. 阳光照射在水面上。 Yángguāng zhàoshè zài shuǐmiàn shàng. The sunlight fell on the water. 运动会安排在四月份。 Yùndònghuì ānpái zài Sìyuè fèn. The sports meet will be some time in April. 2 according to; in terms of 在党内 zài dǎngnèi within (or inside) the Party 在此期间 zài cǐ qījiān during this period 在理论上 zài lǐlùn shàng in theory; theoretically 在我看来 Zài wǒ kànlai in my opinion; as I see it 在这方面 zài zhè fāngmiàn in this respect 在国际事务中 zài guójì shìwù zhōng in international affairs 在全国范围内 zài quánguó fànwéi nèi throughout the country 在这种情况下 zài zhèzhǒng qíngkuàng xià under these circumstances 在党中央的领导下 zài dǎngzhōngyāng de lǐngdǎo xià under the leadership of the Party Central Committee 在和平共处五项原则的基础上 zài hépíng gòngchǔ wǔ xiàng yuánzé de jīchǔ shàng on the basis of the Five Principles of Peaceful Coexistence 
adverb 1 [indicating action in progress] 他在看电视。 Tā zài kàn diànshì. He’s watching TV. 他在干什么？——他还在睡觉呢。 Tā zài gàn shénme？ —— tā hái zài shuìjiào ne. What’s he doing? —He’s still sleeping. 她在游泳。 Tā zài yóuyǒng. She is swimming. 2 [used together with 所 (suǒ) and often followed by 不 (bù) to indicate emphasis] See 35597056在所不辞zai4suo3bu4ci2在所不辞;35597312在所不惜zai4suo3bu4xi1 在所不惜</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35592192"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">伦敦</headword><headword charset="tc">倫敦</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Lun2dun1</pron><defn>London</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26321408"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">北京</headword><headword charset="tc">北京</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Bei3jing1</pron><defn>Beijing</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="17345024"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">他们</headword><headword charset="tc">他們</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ta1men5</pron><defn>pronoun 1 they or them (referring to people) 他们俩 tāmenliǎ the two of them 他们仨 tāmen sā the three of them 他们的意图 tāmen de yìtú their intentions 他们家有一架钢琴。 Tāmen jiā yǒu yī jià gāngqín. They have a piano at home. 他们刚来, 你找他们去。 Tāmen gāng lái, nǐ zhǎo tāmen qù. They’ve just come, you may see them now. 他们三位都是国际知名的科学家。 tāmen sān wèi dōu shì guójì zhīmíng de kēxuéjiā. The three scientists are world-renowned. 2 [before or after nouns for emphasis] 他们弟兄都是钳工。 Tāmen dìxiong dōu shì qiángōng. The two brothers are fitters. 他们湖南人喜欢吃辣的。 Tāmen Húnán rén xǐhuan chī là de. These Hunanese are fond of hot food. 赵先生, 钱先生他们都下班走了。 Zhào xiānsheng, qián xiānshengtāmen dōu xiàbān zǒu le. Both Mr Zhao and Mr Qian have left the office for the day. 3 [after the name or title of a person] and the others 队长他们都在体育馆里练球。 Duìzhǎng tāmen dōu zài tǐyùguǎn lǐ liàn qiú. The captain and his team (or men) are in the gym practising.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="31040000"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">电影</headword><headword charset="tc">電影</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">dian4ying3</pron><defn>noun film; movie; motion picture 彩色电影 cǎisè diànyǐng colour movie 黑白电影 hēi-bái diànyǐng black-and-white movie 有声电影 yǒushēng diànyǐng sound film 无声电影 wúshēng diànyǐng silent film</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="20029440"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">明星</headword><headword charset="tc">明星</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ming2xing1</pron><defn>noun 1 archaic Venus 2 famous performer; star 电影明星 diànyǐng míngxīng film (or movie) star 足球明星 zúqiú Míngxīng football star 全明星队 quán Míngxīng duì all-star team 3 dated society lady (or butterfly) 4 famous enterprise; well-known business 明星企业 míngxīng qǐyè famous (or well-known) enterprise</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26935040"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">但是</headword><headword charset="tc">但是</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">dan4shi4</pron><defn>conjunction but; yet; still; nevertheless 一项宏大但是不切实际的计划 Yī xiàng hóngdà dànshì bùqièshíjì de jìhuà a grandiose but impracticable plan 他虽然能干, 但是这个问题太难, 他也不好解决。 tā suīrán nénggàn, dànshì zhège wèntí tài nán, tā yě bù hǎo jiějué. He’s an able man, but the problem is too hard for him. 不能听从你, 但是我感谢你说了这番话。 Bùnéng tīngcóng nǐ, dànshì wǒ gǎnxiè nǐ shuō le zhèfān huà. I can’t follow your advice. Nevertheless, thank you for giving it.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19614720"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">美国</headword><headword charset="tc">美國</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Mei3guo2</pron><defn>noun the United States of America (USA); the United States; America 美国国会 Měiguó Guóhuì the US Congress</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26651392"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">青岛</headword><headword charset="tc">青島</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Qing1dao3</pron><defn>Qingdao, subprovincial city in Shandong</defn></entry><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">香港</headword><headword charset="tc">香港</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Xiang1gang3</pron><defn>noun 1 Hong Kong (or Hongkong) Island 2 entire Hong Kong area (including Hong Kong Island, Kowloon (九龙) and the New Territories (新界))</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33036032"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">法国</headword><headword charset="tc">法國</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Fa3guo2</pron><defn>France; French</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="20645120"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">德国</headword><headword charset="tc">德國</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">De2guo2</pron><defn>Germany</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19776000"/><catassign category="Lektion2"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">她</headword><headword charset="tc">她</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ta1</pron><defn>pronoun she; her 她好久没来这儿了。 Tā hǎojiǔ méi lái zhèr le. She hasn’t been here for a long time. 我明天找她去。 Wǒ míngtiān zhǎo tā qù. I’m going to see her tomorrow.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="31042048"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">他</headword><headword charset="tc">他</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ta1</pron><defn>pronoun 1 he; him; his 他哥 tā gē his elder brother 他俩 tāliǎ the two of them; both 他老婆 tā lǎopo his wife 他家在农村。 Tā jiā zài nóngcūn. His home is in the countryside. 他家是新搬来的。 Tā jiā shì xīn bān lái de. He and his family moved here recently. 他刚才给你送票来了。 Tā gāng cái gěi nǐ sòng piào lái le. He came just now with a ticket for you. 谁没有票, 问他要。 Shuí méi yǒu piào, wèn tā yào. Anyone without a ticket can ask him for one. 2 [for either sex when it is either unknown or unimportant] 从远处看不出他是男是女。 cóng yuǎnchù kànbuchū tā shì nán shì nǚ. I can’t tell if it’s a man or a woman from a distance. 每个孩子都讲了他学习(雷锋)的收获。 Měi ge háizi dōu jiǎng le tā xuéxí Léi Fēng de shōuhuò. Each child described what he or she had learnt (from Lei Feng). 3 [before or after a person&apos;s name for emphasis] 老王他也提前到了。 Lǎo wáng tā yě tíqián dào le. Lao Wang also came early. 这事儿成与不成就看他老张了。 Zhè shìr chéng yǔ bù chéng jiù kàn tā lǎo zhāng le. The success or failure of this all depends on Lao Zhang alone. 4 [used as a meaningless object, for emphasis or in fun] 好好睡他一觉 Hǎohāo shuì tā yī jiào have a good sleep 咱们喝他几杯去。 Zánmen hē tā jǐ bēi qù. Let’s go and have a few drinks. 你写他两三本书, 就出名了。 Nǐ xiě tā liǎng sān běn shū, jiù chūmíng le. If you can publish a couple of books, you’ll become famous. 5 usually literary other; another; some other 别无他求 Bié wú tā qiú have no other request 留作他用 liú zuò tāyòng keep for other uses 此人早已他去。 Cǐ rén zǎoyǐ tā qù. He has long since left. 
noun (Tā) a surname</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="31038720"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">妹妹</headword><headword charset="tc">妹妹</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">mei4mei5</pron><defn>noun 1 younger sister; sister 2 junior female relative of the same generation</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26666752"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">这</headword><headword charset="tc">這</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zhe4</pron><defn>pronoun 1 this 这地方 zhè dìfang this place 这一回 zhè yī huí this time 这就对了。 Zhè jiù duì le. Now you’re on the right track. or Now that’s better. 这是新产品。 zhè shì xīnchǎnpǐn. These are new products. 这究竟是怎么回事？ Zhè jiūjìng shì zěnme huí shì？ What’s all this about? 这才是好孩子！ Zhè cái shì hǎo háizi! That’s a good boy (girl)! or That’s a dear! 这消息我知道了。 Zhè xiāoxi wǒ zhīdao le. I’ve heard that news already. or Yes, so I’ve heard. 2 now 我这就走。 Wǒ zhè jiù zǒu. I’m leaving right now. 他这才知道锻炼身体的好处。 Tā zhè cái zhīdao duànliàn shēntǐ de hǎochu. Only now does he see the benefit of exercise.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35937792"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">弟弟</headword><headword charset="tc">弟弟</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">di4di5</pron><defn>noun younger brother; brother</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19934208"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">和</headword><headword charset="tc">和</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">he2</pron><defn>adjective 1 gentle; mild; kind 温和 wēnhé mild; temperate 2 harmonious; on good terms 和为贵。 Hé wéi guì. Harmony is what matters. 
noun 1 peace 2 (Hé) a surname 
verb sports draw; tie 那盘棋和了。 Nà pán qí hé le. That game of chess ended in a draw. 
conjunction and 我和你 Wǒ hé nǐ you and I 工人和农民 Gōngrén hé nóngmín workers and peasants 
preposition [indicating relationship, comparison, etc.] 和这件事没有关系 Hé zhè jiàn shì méiyǒu guānxi have nothing to do with the matter; bear no relation to it 他和我一样高。 Tā hé wǒ yīyàng gāo. He’s as tall as I. 
noun mathematics sum 两数之和 liǎng shù zhī hé the sum of the two numbers 
verb together with See 22529280和盘托出he2pan2tuo1chu1和盘托出 
noun Japan 汉和词典 hàn hé cídiǎn Chinese-Japanese dictionary</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22523392"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">也</headword><headword charset="tc">也</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ye3</pron><defn>auxiliary classical 1 [at the end of a sentence, indicating an explanation or a judgment] 陈胜者, 阳城人也。(《史记》) Chén shèng zhě, yáng chéng rén yě. Chen Sheng was a native of Yangcheng. 何其毒也！ Héqídúyě! How pernicious! 2 [at the end of a question or rhetorical question] 何也？ Hé yě？ How is that? or Why so? 是可忍, 孰不可忍也？ Shì kě rěn, shú bùkě rěn yě? If this can be tolerated, what cannot? 3 [in the middle of a sentence, marking off a sentence element about which there is to be a statement] 大道之行也, 天下为公。(《礼记》) Dàdào zhī xíng yě, tiānxiàwéigōng. (《Lǐjì》) When the Great Tao prevailed, the whole world was one community. 
adverb 1 also; too; as well; either 你不去, 我也不去。 Nǐ bù qù, wǒ yě bù qù. If you’re not going, I’m not going either. 我妹妹也是售货员。 Wǒ mèimei yě shì shòuhuòyuán. My sister is a shop assistant too. 中国是一个社会主义国家, 也是一个发展中国家。 Zhōngguó shì yī ge shèhuìzhǔyì guójiā, yě shì yī ge fāzhǎnzhōng guójiā. China is a socialist country, and a developing country as well. 2 [for emphasis, often before a negative expression] 她一天假也没请过。 Tā yī tiān jià yě méi qǐng guò. She has never asked for leave, not even for a day. 他忙得连饭也顾不上吃。 Tā máng de lián fàn yě gù bù shàng chī. He is so busy that he can’t even stop for a meal. 3 [used correlatively with 虽然, 即使, etc.] still; yet 你不说我也知道。 Nǐ bù shuō wǒ yě zhīdao. You don’t have to tell me. I know already. 我虽然没见过, 也听人说过。 Wǒ suīrán méi jiàn guò, yě tīng rén shuō guò. I’ve heard about it, though I have never seen it. 我怎么想也想不起来。 Wǒ zěnme xiǎng yě xiǎng bù qǐlai. I simply couldn’t recall it however hard I tried. 4 [in a hesitant or guarded statement] 也只好这样了。 Yě zhǐhǎo zhèyàng le. We’ll have to leave it at that. 他的英语也还可以。 Tā de Yīngyǔ yě hái kěyǐ. His English is passable. 这袋土豆也就一百公斤。 Zhè dài tǔdòu yě jiù yībǎi gōngjīn. This sack of potatoes weighs a hundred kilos at most.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34275840"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">学生</headword><headword charset="tc">學生</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xue2sheng5</pron><defn>noun 1 student; pupil 医科学生 yīkē xuésheng medical student 学生勤奋学习, 就是对老师的报答。 xuésheng qínfèn xuéxí, jiùshì duì lǎoshī de bàodá. A diligent scholar, and the master paid. 2 disciple; follower 3 dialect boy; lad</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33769728"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">记者</headword><headword charset="tc">記者</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ji4zhe3</pron><defn>noun journalist; reporter; correspondent; newsman 本报记者 běnbào jìzhě staff reporter (or correspondent) 采访记者 cǎifǎngjìzhě reporter 随军记者 suíjūn jìzhě war correspondent 特派记者 tèpài jìzhě special correspondent 新华社记者 Xīnhuáshè jìzhě Xinhua correspondent; reporter of the Xinhua News Agency</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="23539968"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">爸爸</headword><headword charset="tc">爸爸</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ba4ba5</pron><defn>noun papa; dad; father</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="16997632"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">做</headword><headword charset="tc">做</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zuo4</pron><defn>verb 1 do; make; produce; manufacture 做结论 zuò jiélún pass a verdict; reach a conclusion 做衣服 zuò yīfu make clothes 做长期打算 zuò chángqī dǎsuan plan for the long term 这种糖是甜菜做的。 Zhèzhǒng táng shì tiáncài zuò de. This sugar is made from beets. 这是你自己做的吗？ Zhè shì nǐ zìjǐ zuò de ma？ Did you make this yourself? 2 cook; prepare 做菜 zuòcài cook a dish 3 do; act; engage in 做好本职工作 zuòhǎo běnzhí gōngzuò do one’s best at one’s job 从点滴的事情做起 cóng diǎndī de shìqing zuò qǐ start with little things 大事做不来, 小事又不做 dàshì zuò bù lái, xiǎoshì yòu bù zuò incapable of big jobs yet despise small ones 照正确的意见去做 zhào zhèngquè de yìjian qù zuò act upon correct views 共做了两万多个劳动日 gòng zuò le liǎngwàn duō ge láodòngrì did a total of more than 20,000 workdays 4 be; become 做演员 zuò yǎnyuán become an actor or actress; go on the stage 后来她做保育员了。 Hòulái tā zuò bǎoyùyuán le. Later she became a child-care worker. 今天开会由你做主席。 Jīntiān kāihuì yóu nǐ zuò zhǔxí. You’ll be the chairman at today’s meeting. 5 write; compose See 37179904做文章zuo4wen2zhang1做文章 6 hold a family (or home) celebration See 37179648做寿zuo4shou4做寿 7 used as; used for 这篇文章可以做教材。 Zhè piān wénzhāng kěyǐ zuò jiàocái. This article may be used as teaching material. 树皮可以做造纸的原料。 Shùpí kěyǐ zuò zàozhǐ de yuánliào. Bark may be used as raw material for paper. 8 form or contract a relationship 做对头 zuò duìtóu set oneself against sb. 做朋友 zuò péngyou make friends with 9 pretend; feign; do sth. for form&apos;s sake See 37181184做样子zuo4yang4zi5做样子 10 dialect kill 把人质做了 bǎ rénzhì zuòle kill the hostage</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="37170176"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">工作</headword><headword charset="tc">工作</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">gong1zuo4</pron><defn>verb work; operate 努力工作 Nǔlì gōngzuò work hard 机器正在工作。 Jīqì zhèng zài gōngzuò. The machine is in operation. 
noun work; job 分配工作 Fēnpèi gōngzuò assign jobs (or work) 做研究工作 zuò yánjiū gōngzuò do research work 他是做消防工作的。 Tā shì zuò xiāofáng gōngzuò de. He works in the fire brigade.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="21680896"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">医生</headword><headword charset="tc">醫生</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">yi1sheng1</pron><defn>noun doctor; medical man 内科医生 nèikē yīshēng physician 实习医生 shíxí yīshēng intern 外科医生 wàikē yīshēng surgeon 主任医生 zhǔrèn yīshēng chief physician 主治医生 zhǔzhì yīshēng doctor in charge 住院医生 zhùyuàn yīshēng resident doctor 全科普通医生 quán kē pǔtōng yīshēng general practitioner</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34460928"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">妈妈</headword><headword charset="tc">媽媽</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ma1ma5</pron><defn>noun 1 colloquial ma; mum; mummy; mother 2 dialect courteous aunt; auntie</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26410240"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">医院</headword><headword charset="tc">醫院</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">yi1yuan4</pron><defn>noun hospital 儿童医院 értóng yīyuàn children’s hospital 综合性医院 zōnghéxìng yīyuàn general hospital</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34463488"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">都</headword><headword charset="tc">都</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">dou1</pron><defn>adverb 1 all 大家都到了吗？ Dàjiā dōu dào le ma？ Is everybody here? 什么都行。 Shénme dōu xíng. Anything will do. 我父母都不在了。 Wǒ fùmǔ dōu bù zài le. My parents are both deceased. 2 [with 是 to show the cause] 都是你, 把他灌成这样。 Dōu shì nǐ, bǎ tā guàn chéng zhèyàng. It’s all your fault making him drunk. 都是你老磨蹭, 害得我们迟到了。 Dōu shì nǐ lǎo móceng, hài de wǒmen chídào le. It is because you dawdled that we were late. 3 even 今天天气真怪, 中午比早晨都冷。 Jīntiān tiānqì zhēn guài, zhōngwǔ bǐ zǎochen dōu lěng. What strange weather, it’s colder at noon than early in the morning! 连他都不知道。 Lián tā dōu bù zhīdao. Even he doesn’t know. 4 already 他都八十岁了, 身子骨还那么硬朗。 Tā dōu bāshí suì le, shēnzi gǔ hái nàme yìnglang. He’s already eighty but still going strong.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="20234496"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">家</headword><headword charset="tc">家</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jia1</pron><defn>noun 1 family; household 张家和王家 Zhāng jiā hé wáng jiā the Zhangs and the Wangs 他全家都是工人。 Tā quánjiā dōu shì gōngrén. They’re all workers in his family. 小区里家家都爱养花。 Xiǎoqū lǐ jiājiā dōu ài yǎnghuā. In this neighbourhood, every family loves growing flowers. 2 home 回家 huíjiā go home 不在家 bù zàijiā not be in; be out 上我家去吧。 Shàng wǒ jiā qù ba. Come to my place. 3 person or family engaged in a certain trade 船家 chuánjiā boatman 4 specialist in a certain field 画家 huàjiā painter 科学家 kēxuéjiā scientist 5 school of thought 儒家 Rújiā Confucian school 6 self-deprecating my [in speaking of relatives older than oneself] See 23637248家父jia1fu4家父 7 (in playing cards, mah-jong, etc.) party; side See 59564771对家dui4jia1对家;29587456上家shang4jia1上家;36692480庄家zhuang1jia5庄家 
adjective domestic; tamed (opp. 野) 家兔 jiātù rabbit 
measure word [for families or business establishments] 两家人家 Liǎng jiā rénjia two families 三家商店 sān jiā shāngdiàn three shops 一家电影院 yī jiā diànyǐngyuàn a cinema</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="23631104"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">的</headword><headword charset="tc">的</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">de5</pron><defn>auxiliary 1 [after an attribute] 铁的纪律 tiě de jìlǜ iron discipline 我的母亲 wǒ de mǔqin my mother 别开他的玩笑了。 Bié kāi tā de wánxiào le. Don’t make fun of him. 2 [forming a noun phrase or nominal expression] 打字的 dǎzì de typist 我爱吃辣的。 Wǒ ài chī là de. I like spicy food. 他说他的, 我干我的。 Tā shuō tā de, wǒ gàn wǒ de. Let him say what he likes; I’ll just get on with my work. 3 [after a verb or between a verb and its object to stress an element of the sentence] 谁买的票？ Shuí mǎi de piào? Who bought the tickets? 他是昨天进的城。 Tā shì zuótiān jìn de chéng. He went to town yesterday. 你嗓子怎么哑了？——唱的。 Nǐ sǎngzi zěnme yā le？ —— chàng de. Why are you so hoarse? — From singing. 4 [at the end of a declarative sentence for emphasis] 你们这两天真够辛苦的。 Nǐmen zhè liǎng tiān zhēn gòu xīnkǔ de. You’ve really been working hard the past few days. 5 [expressing the idea of “of that kind”] 针头线脑的 Zhēntóu-xiànnǎo de things like needles and threads 
VARIANT OF 19760640得de2得 dé 3 verb fit; suit</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19779584"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">照片</headword><headword charset="tc">照片</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zhao4pian4</pron><defn>noun photograph; picture 彩色照片 Cǎisè zhàopiàn colour photograph 加印照片 jiāyìn zhàopiàn print extra copies from a negative; make copies of a print</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35902208"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">哥哥</headword><headword charset="tc">哥哥</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ge1ge5</pron><defn>noun (elder) brother</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="21555712"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">学校</headword><headword charset="tc">學校</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xue2xiao4</pron><defn>noun school; educational institution 高等学校 gāoděng xuéxiào institution of higher learning 师范学校 shīfàn xuéxiào teachers’ (or normal) school 专业学校 zhuānyè xuéxiào specialized (or vocational) school</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33775360"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">老师</headword><headword charset="tc">老師</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">lao3shi1</pron><defn>noun 1 teacher; schoolmaster 2 courteous [in direct address] professor; Mr. (or Mrs., Miss, Ms.) 数学老师 shùxué lǎoshī maths master (or mistress) 老师再见！ lǎoshī zàijiàn Good-bye, Sir (or Madam, Miss)!</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="25455872"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">姐姐</headword><headword charset="tc">姐姐</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jie3jie5</pron><defn>noun elder sister; sister</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="24167424"/><catassign category="Lektion3"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">谁</headword><headword charset="tc">誰</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shei2</pron><defn>(shuí) pronoun 1 who 他是谁？ Tā shì shéi？ Who is he? 他在跟谁说话？ Tā zài gēn shéi shuōhuà？ Who is he talking to? 这是谁的意见？ Zhè shì shéi de yìjian？ Whose idea is this? 2 [in rhetorical questions] who 谁不说他好？ Shéi bù shuō tā hǎo？ Who wouldn’t speak well of him? 谁言寸草心, 报得三春晖。(孟郊《游子吟》) Shéi yán cùncǎo xīn, bào de sānchūn huī. Such kindness of warm sun, can’t be repaid by grass. 3 someone; anyone 你要找谁吗？ Nǐ yào zhǎo shéi ma？ Are you looking for someone? 我没跟谁说话。 Wǒ méi gēn shéi shuōhuà. I didn’t talk to anyone. 有谁能帮助我就好了。 Yǒu shéi néng bāngzhù wǒ jiù hǎo le. If only someone would help me! 4 [before 都 or 也] everyone; anyone 谁也不要。 Shéi yě bùyào. Nobody wants it. 谁都喜欢他。 Shéi dōu xǐhuan tā. Everybody likes him. 5 [repeated in two phrases] whoever 谁污染谁治理的原则 shéi wūrǎn shéi zhìlǐ de yuánzé principle of keeping pollution controlled by whoever making it 谁先到, 谁先吃。 Shéi xiān dào, Shéi xiān chī. Whoever arrives first will eat first. 大家看谁合适就选谁。 Dàjiā kàn shéi héshì jiù xuǎn shéi. You may elect whoever you think is suitable. 6 [as both subject and object to indicate two different people] 他们俩谁也说不服谁。 Tāmen liǎ shéi yě shuō bù fú shéi. Neither of them could convince the other.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="29728512"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">上海</headword><headword charset="tc">上海</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Shang4hai3</pron><defn>noun Shanghai</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="29584896"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">现在</headword><headword charset="tc">現在</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xian4zai4</pron><defn>noun now; at present; today</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="32966400"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">多大</headword><headword charset="tc">多大</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">duo1 da4</pron><defn> 多 much, many; more than, overRadical: 夕; Stroke count: 6; HSK level: 1; General Standard: #507; Frequency rank: 61 大 big, great, vast, large, highRadical: 大; Stroke count: 3; HSK level: 1; General Standard: #32; Frequency rank: 17</defn></entry><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">岁</headword><headword charset="tc">嵗</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">sui4</pron><defn>noun 1 literary year 岁除 suìchú New Year’s Eve 岁杪 suìmiǎo end of the year; year-end 岁末 suìmò end of the year 岁时 suìshí four seasons 岁朝 suìzhāo first day of the lunar New Year 辞旧岁, 迎新年 cí jiù suì, yíng xīnnián ring out the old year and ring in the new 2 literary year&apos;s harvest 歉岁 qiànsuì lean year 3 age 同岁 tóngsuì of the same age 4 literary time 岁月如梭。 suì yuè rúsuō. How time flies. 
measure word year (of age) 三岁女孩儿 sān suì nǚ hái&apos;ér three-year-old girl</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30983936"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">知道</headword><headword charset="tc">知道</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zhi1dao4</pron><defn>verb know; realize; aware of 我不知道这事儿。 Wǒ bù zhīdao zhè shìr. I know nothing about it. 你的意思我知道。 Nǐ de yìsi wǒ zhīdao. I know what you mean. or I see your point. 他们知道问题的严重性。 Tāmen zhīdao wèntí de yánzhòngxìng. They realize the seriousness of the problem. 我们知道在前进的路上还会有困难。 Wǒmen zhīdao zài qiánjìn de lùshang hái huì yǒu kùnnan. We know there will still be difficulties ahead.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="36146945"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">真</headword><headword charset="tc">真</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zhen1</pron><defn>adjective 1 true; real; genuine (opp. 假,伪) 我真的要走了。 Wǒ zhēn de yào zǒu le. It’s true I’m leaving. 这幅宋人的画是真的。 Zhè fú Sòng rén de huà shì zhēn de. This is a genuine Song painting. 2 clear; unmistakable 字音咬得真 zìyīn yǎo de zhēn pronounce words distinctly 你看得真么？ Nǐ kàn de zhēn me？ Can you see clearly? 
adverb really; truly; indeed 真有你的！ Zhēn yǒu nǐ de! That was a smart! 他真信了。 Tā zhēn xìn le. He actually believed it. 你真不害臊。 Nǐ zhēn bù hàisào. You’ve got some nerve! 我真不知道。 Wǒ zhēn bù zhīdao. I really don’t know. 演出真精彩。 yǎnchū zhēn jīngcǎi. The performance was just splendid. 时间过得真快。 Shíjiān guò de zhēn kuài. How time flies! 这家伙真能说。 Zhè jiāhuo zhēn néng shuō. That fellow is very glib. 你通过了考试, 真行！ Nǐ tōngguò le kǎoshì, zhēn xíng! You’ve passed the exams—good for you! 给你添了不少麻烦, 真过意不去。 Gěi nǐ tiān le bùshǎo máfan, zhēn guòyìbùqù. I’m very sorry to have put you to so much trouble. 
noun 1 abbreviation calligraphy regular script 2 portrait; image; exact copy of sth. 写真 xiězhēn portrait 传真 chuánzhēn fax 3 literary natural instincts (or character, disposition); nature; inherent quality; origin See 59954659返璞归真fan3pu2gui1zhen1返璞归真</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35969536"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">高</headword><headword charset="tc">高</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">gao1</pron><defn>adjective 1 tall; high (opp. 低) 这里地势很高。 Zhèlǐ dìshì hěn gāo. The terrain here is very high. 她比小红高一头。 Tā bǐ xiǎo hóng gāo yī tóu. She is a head taller than Xiao Hong. 这片地中间高起一块。 Zhè piàn dì zhōngjiān gāo qǐ yī kuài. There is a mound in the middle of the field. 2 of a high level (or degree); above the average (opp. 低) 高风格 Gāo fēnggé fine style 高年级 gāoniánjí higher (or senior) grades 高速度 gāosùdù high speed 高质量 gāo zhìliàng high (or good) quality 体温高 tǐwēn gāo have a fever 这主意真高！ Zhè zhǔyi zhēn gāo! What a brilliant idea! 他的思想境界比我高。 Tā de sīxiǎng jìngjiè bǐ wǒ gāo. He has nobler thoughts than I. 他的见解比谁都高。 Tā de jiànjiě bǐ shuí dōu gāo. He has more original ideas than others do. 老师对她评价很高。 Lǎoshī duì tā píngjià hěn gāo. The teacher has a high opinion of her (or speaks highly of her). 3 loud; high-pitched 高喊 gāohǎn shout loudly; raise a cry 嗓门儿高 sǎngménr gāo have a loud voice 这首歌对他来说调太高了。 Zhè shǒu gē duì tā lái shuō diào tài gāo le. The song is too high-pitched for him. 4 high-priced; dear; expensive; costly 要价太高 yàojià tài gāo ask (or charge) too high a price 5 courteous your 感谢高情 Gǎnxiè gāo qíng many thanks for your hospitality 6 chemistry containing one more oxygen atom in an acid or a chemical compound See 21503232高锰酸钾gao1meng3suan1jia3高锰酸钾 
noun 1 height; attitude 坝高四十米。 Bà gāo sìshí mǐ. The dam is 40 metres high (or in height). 他身高六英尺。 tā shēn gāo liù yīngchǐ. He is 6 feet tall. 2 (Gāo) a surname</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="21476352"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">帅</headword><headword charset="tc">帥</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shuai4</pron><defn>noun 1 commander in chief 统帅 tǒngshuài com-mander in chief 2 commander in chief, the chief piece in Chinese chess 3 (Shuài) a surname 
adjective 1 beautiful; graceful; smart; dashing 他的字写得真帅。 Tā de zì xiě de zhēn shuài. He writes a beautiful hand. 他的双杠动作可帅了！ Tā de shuānggàng dòngzuò kě shuài le! His movements on the parallel bars were very graceful. 2 handsome; elegant 这小伙子长得真帅！ Zhè xiǎohuǒzi zhǎng de zhēn shuài! What a handsome strapping young man!</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30563328"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">酷</headword><headword charset="tc">酷</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ku4</pron><defn>adjective 1 cruel; oppressive 酷虐 kùnüè ferocious; savage 2 fierce; scorching 酷日 kù rì scorching sun 
adverb very; extremely 酷类 kùlèi be exactly like 
adjective transliteration slang 1 cool; excellent; fashionable; great 酷毙了！ kù bì le! This is cool! 2 stylish and sober; graceful and stern 酷哥 kùgē handsome and stern young fellow 酷语 kùyǔ fashionable words; cool expression 摆酷 bǎikù pretend to be stylish and indifferent; be cool</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="25136640"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">最</headword><headword charset="tc">最</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zui4</pron><defn>adverb 1 [in front of an adjective or a verb] most; -est 最大 zuìdà the biggest 最美 zuì měi the most beautiful 最小 zuìxiǎo the smallest 最不发达国家 zuì bù fādá guójiā the least developed country 最基本的条件 zuì jīběn de tiáojiàn fundamental prerequisites 他最不讲道理。 Tā zuì bù jiǎng dàoli. He’s most unreasonable. 我最喜欢吃巧克力冰激凌。 Wǒ zuì xǐhuan chī qiǎokèlì bīngjilíng. I like chocolate ice cream best. 2 [placed in front of a noun of locality, or a place word] farthest or nearest to (a place) 最东头 zuì dōngtóu farthest to the east; at the very east end 最上头 Zuì shàngtou farthest (or nearest) to the top; at the very top 
noun the utmost; the best (or highest, greatest, etc.) 钻石之最 zuànshí zhī zuì the best (or biggest) of all the diamonds</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="37070848"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">喜欢</headword><headword charset="tc">喜歡</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xi3huan5</pron><defn>verb like; love; be fond of; be keen on 喜欢看电视 Xǐhuan kàn diànshì like watching TV 我喜欢热闹。 Wǒ xǐhuan rènao. I like company. 这孩子真讨人喜欢。 Zhè háizi zhēn tǎo rén xǐhuan. What a lovable child! 她最不喜欢吹吹拍拍。 Tā zuì bù xǐhuan chuī chuī pāipāi. She loathes bragging and flattery. 
adjective happy; elated; filled with joy 听到胜利的消息好不喜欢 Tīngdào shènglì de xiāoxi hǎo bù xǐhuan great elation at the news of victory 快把这好消息告诉奶奶, 让她老人家喜欢喜欢。 Kuài bǎ zhè hǎo xiāoxi gàosu nǎinai, ràng tā lǎorenjia xǐhuan xǐhuan. Quick, tell Grandma the good news and make her happy.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="32732928"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">篮球</headword><headword charset="tc">籃球</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">lan2qiu2</pron><defn>noun basketball 打篮球 dǎ lánqiú play basketball</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="25352192"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">运动员</headword><headword charset="tc">運動員</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">yun4dong4yuan2</pron><defn>sportsman or sportswoman; athlete; player</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35533568"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">姓名</headword><headword charset="tc">姓名</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xing4ming2</pron><defn>noun surname and personal name; full name</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33549312"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">年龄</headword><headword charset="tc">年齡</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">nian2ling2</pron><defn>noun age 年龄不饶人。 Niánlíng bù ráo rén. Age will show itself. or Age will tell. 从马的牙齿可以看出它的年龄。 Cóng mǎ de yáchǐ kěyǐ kànchū tā de niánlíng. You can tell a horse’s age from its teeth. 他参军还不够年龄。 Tā cānjūn hái bùgòu niánlíng. He is too young to join the army.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27333888"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">出生地</headword><headword charset="tc">出生地</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">chu1sheng1di4</pron><defn>birthplace</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="18881280"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">国籍</headword><headword charset="tc">國籍</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">guo2ji2</pron><defn>noun 1 nationality; citizenship 保留国籍 bǎoliú guójí retain one’scitizenship 多重国籍 duōchóngguójí plural (or multiple) nationality 双重国籍 shuāngchóngguójí dual nationality 你是哪国国籍？ Nǐ shì nǎ guó guójí？ What’s your nationality? 他是中国国籍。 Tā shì Zhōngguó guójí. He has Chinese nationality. or He is of Chinese nationality. 2 (of an aircraft, ship, etc.) national identity 国籍不明的飞机 guójí bùmíng de fēijī an unidentified aircraft</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22162688"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">电子邮箱</headword><headword charset="tc">電子郵箱</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">dian4zi3 you2xiang1</pron><defn>email box</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="68478791"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">动物</headword><headword charset="tc">動物</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">dong4wu4</pron><defn>noun animal</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="20215296"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">熊猫</headword><headword charset="tc">熊貓</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xiong2mao1</pron><defn>noun panda</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33584640"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">可爱</headword><headword charset="tc">可愛</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ke3ai4</pron><defn>adjective lovable; likable; lovely; adorable 可爱的祖国 kě&apos;ài de zǔguó beloved motherland 这孩子真可爱！ Zhè háizi zhēn kě&apos;ài! What a cute child!</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="24947456"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">演员</headword><headword charset="tc">演員</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">yan3yuan2</pron><defn>noun actor or actress; performer 配音演员 pèiyīn yǎnyuán dubbing actor (or actress) 挑选演员 tiāoxuǎn yǎnyuán choose the cast</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34082560"/><catassign category="Lektion4"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">电话</headword><headword charset="tc">電話</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">dian4hua4</pron><defn>noun 1 telephone; phone 请别把电话挂上。 Qǐng bié bǎ diànhuà guà shàng. Hold the line, please. 他把电话挂了。 Tā bǎ diànhuà guà le. He hung up. 2 phone call 打电话 dǎ diànhuà make a phone call; phone sb.; call (or ring) sb.; give sb. a ring 他正在打电话。 Tā zhèngzài dǎ diànhuà. He’s on the phone. 有你的电话。 Yǒu nǐ de diànhuà. There’s a call for you. or You’re wanted on the phone.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19998976"/><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">号码</headword><headword charset="tc">號碼</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hao4ma3</pron><defn>noun number 电话号码 diànhuà hàomǎ telephone number</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22451968"/><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">手机</headword><headword charset="tc">手機</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shou3ji1</pron><defn>noun handset; mobile (or cellular) phone (opp. 座机)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="42425778"/><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">多少</headword><headword charset="tc">多少</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">duo1shao5</pron><defn>pronoun 1 how many; how much 这药我每次吃多少？ Zhè yào wǒ měi cì chī duōshao？ How much of the medicine do I take each time? 这一班有多少学生？ Zhè yī bān yǒu duōshao xuésheng？ How many pupils are there in this class? 这里的粮食亩产量是多少？ Zhèlǐ de liángshi mǔchǎnliàng shì duōshao？ What is the per mu yield of grain here? 2 [expressing an unspecified amount or number] 我知道多少说多少。 Wǒ zhīdao duōshao shuō duōshao. I’ll tell all I know. 我跟你说过不知多少次了。 Wǒ gēn nǐ shuō guò bù zhī duōshao cì le. How many times I’ve told you! or I’ve already told you many times.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="20445184"/><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">公园</headword><headword charset="tc">公園</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">gong1yuan2</pron><defn>noun park; public garden 国家公园 guójiāgōngyuán national park</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="21725184"/><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">路</headword><headword charset="tc">路</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">lu4</pron><defn>noun 1 road; path; way 走错路 zǒu cuò lù take the wrong road 上山的路 shàngshān de lù path up the mountain 此路不通。 Cǐlùbùtōng! Dead End. 2 journey; distance 一小时走二十里路 Yī xiǎoshí zǒu èrshí lǐ lù cover 20 li an hour 路很远。 Lù hěn yuǎn. It’s a long way. 路漫漫其修远兮, 吾将上下而求索。(屈原《离骚》) lù mànmàn qí xiū yuǎn xī, wú jiāng shàng-xià ér qiú suǒ. Long, long had been my road and far, far was the journey; | I would go up and down to seek my heart’s desire. 3 way; means 和平之路 Hépíng zhī lù way to peace 我实在没路可走了。 Wǒ shízài méi lù kě zǒu le. I’m really at a dead end. 4 sequence; line; logic 思路 sīlù train of thought 5 region; district 南路货 nán lù huò southern products 外路人 wàilùrén nonlocal people 各路英雄 gè lù yīngxióng people from different places 6 route 三路进军 sān lù jìnjūn advance along three routes 七路公共汽车 qī lù gōnggòng qìchē No.7 bus 7 sort; grade; class 头路货 tóulùhuò top class goods 这一路人 zhè yī lùrén this sort of people 二三路角色 Èr-sān lù juésè a second- or third-class role 哪一路病？ Nǎ yī lù bìng？ What kind of disease is this? 纸有好几路。 Zhǐ yǒu hǎojǐ lù. There are several kinds of paper. 8 (Lù) a surname 
measure word line; row 一路纵队 yīlù zòngduì a column of files; a single column 三路纵队 sān lù zòngduì a column of threes</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26233344"/><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">号</headword><headword charset="tc">號</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hao4</pron><defn>ZEW
Number, Date</defn></entry><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">新</headword><headword charset="tc">新</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xin1</pron><defn>adjective 1 new; fresh; up-to-date (opp. 老, 旧) 新技术 xīnjìshù new (or up-to-date) technique 新品种 xīn pǐnzhǒng new variety 最新消息 zuìxīn xiāoxi the latest news 2 brand new; unused (opp. 旧) 新笔 xīn bǐ new pen 新衣服 xīn yīfu new clothes 3 recently married or just being married 新女婿 Xīn nǚxu man newly married to one’s daughter; daughter’s bridegroom 新媳妇 xīnxífu woman newly married to one’s son; son’s bride 
adverb newly; freshly; recently 新漆的门 xīn qī de mén freshly painted door 新建的工厂 xīnjiàn de gōngchǎng newly built factory 他是新来的。 Tā shì xīn lái de. He’s a new arrival. 这本书是我新买的。 Zhè běn shū shì wǒ xīn mǎi de. This is the book I’ve just bought. 
noun 1 (Xīn) Xin Dynasty (8-23 AD, between the Western Han and the Eastern Han) 2 (Xīn) a surname 3 the new</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33396992"/><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">地址</headword><headword charset="tc">地址</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">di4zhi3</pron><defn>noun address 电邮地址 diànyóudìzhǐ email address 固定地址 gùdìng dìzhǐ permanent address 回信地址 huíxìn dìzhǐ return address 临时地址 línshí dìzhǐ temporary address 通讯地址 tōngxùn dìzhǐ mailing address 转送地址 zhuǎnsòng dìzhǐ forwarding address</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19929600"/><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">大学</headword><headword charset="tc">大學</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">da4xue2</pron><defn>noun 1 university; college 2 (Dàxué) The Great Learning See 30836224四书si4shu1四书</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19491840"/><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">可以</headword><headword charset="tc">可以</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ke3yi3</pron><defn>verb 1 can; may 这间屋子可以住四个人。 Zhè jiān wūzi kěyǐ zhù sì ge rén. This room can accommodate four people. 2 be worth (doing) 这个展览我觉得可以一看。 zhège zhǎnlǎn wǒ juédekěyǐ yī kàn. I think the exhibition is worth a visit. 3 [indicating permission] can; may 你可以走了。 Nǐ kěyǐ zǒu le. You may go. 这里不可以吸烟。 Zhèlǐ bù kěyǐ xīyān. Smoking is not allowed here. or You can’t smoke here. 
adjective colloquial 1 passable; not bad 这篇文章写得还可以。 Zhè piān wénzhāng xiě de hái kěyǐ. This article is pretty good. 2 terrible; awful 你这张嘴真可以啊！ Nǐ zhè zhāngzuǐ zhēn kěyǐ a! What a sharp tongue you’ve got! 他今天忙得真可以。 Tā jīntiān máng de zhēn kěyǐ. He’s awfully busy today.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="24967936"/><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">打电话</headword><headword charset="tc">打電話</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">da3 dian4hua4</pron><defn>make a phone call</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="42424498"/><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">谢谢</headword><headword charset="tc">謝謝</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xie4xie5</pron><defn>verb thank 谢谢！ Xièxie! Thanks! or Thank you! 谢谢你的好意。 Xièxie nǐ de hǎo yì. Thank you for your kindness. 请替我谢谢他。 Qǐng tì wǒ xièxie tā. Please pass on my thanks to him.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33324544"/><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">二月</headword><headword charset="tc">二月</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">er4yue4</pron><defn>noun 1 February 2 the second month of the lunar year; the second moon</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="20582144"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">月</headword><headword charset="tc">月</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">yue4</pron><defn>noun 1 moon 月下散步 yuè xià sànbù take a walk in the moonlight 2 month 本月 běnyuè this month; the current (or present) month 隔月 géyuè every other month 逐月 zhúyuè month by month 月是故乡明。 yuè shì gùxiāng míng. Nowhere as in our native place is the moon so bright. 这孩子才两个月(大)。 Zhè háizi cái liǎng ge yuè. The baby is only two months old. 3 monthly 月(收)入 yuèshōurù monthly income 月(津)贴 yuètiē monthly allowance 月产量 yuèchǎnliàng monthly output 4 fullmoon-shaped; round See 35452672月饼yue4bing5月饼</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35451392"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">生日</headword><headword charset="tc">生日</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">sheng1ri4</pron><defn>noun birthday 过生日 guò shēngri celebrate a birthday 祝你生日快乐！ zhù nǐ shēngri kuàilè! Happy birthday to you!</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="29869313"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">真的</headword><headword charset="tc">真的</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zhen1de5</pron><defn> 真 real, actual, true, genuineRadical: 目; Stroke count: 10; HSK level: 2; General Standard: #1832; Frequency rank: 204 的 possessive, adjectival suffixRadical: 白; Stroke count: 8; HSK level: 1; General Standard: #1155; Frequency rank: 1</defn></entry><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">今天</headword><headword charset="tc">今天</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jin1tian1</pron><defn>noun 1 this day; today 今天上午 jīntiān shàngwǔ this morning 今天下午 jīntiān xiàwǔ this afternoon 一年前的今天 yī nián qián de jīntiān a year ago today 今天是星期天。 Jīntiān shì Xīngqītiān. Today is Sunday. 我今天有客人来。 Wǒ jīntiān yǒu kèren lái. I’m expecting company today. 2 the present time or age; today 今天的青年有不同的道德观念。 Jīntiān de qīngnián yǒu bùtóng de dàodé guānniàn. Young people today (or of today) have different moral values.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="24221952"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">几</headword><headword charset="tc">幾</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ji3</pron><defn>number 1 how many 几点了？ Jǐ diǎn le？ What’s the time? or What time is it? 你几号？ Nǐ jǐ hào？ What’s your number? 四乘六等于几？ Sì chéng liù děngyú jǐ？ What’s four times six? 2 a few; several; some 几十 jǐshí tens; dozens; scores 几万万 jǐ wàn wàn several hundred million; hundreds of millions 说几句话 shuō jǐ jù huà say a few words 有几个人 yǒu jǐ gèrén some people 二十几个人 èrshí jǐ ge rén twenty odd people 十几岁的孩子 shíjǐ suì de háizi teenager 每隔几分钟 měigé jǐ fēnzhōng every few minutes 村子很小, 没有几户人家。 Cūnzi hěn xiǎo, méiyǒu jǐ hù rénjia. The village is quite small, with a few households. 来了十几二十个人。 Lái le shíjǐ èrshí ge rén. About twenty people came. 他过不了几天就会回来的。 Tā guòbuliǎo jǐ tiān jiù huì huílai de. He’ll be back in a couple of days.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="23500800"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">星期天</headword><headword charset="tc">星期天</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xing1qi1tian1</pron><defn>Sunday (Sun.)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33467912"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">星期</headword><headword charset="tc">星期</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xing1qi1</pron><defn>noun 1 week 三个星期 Sān ge xīngqī three weeks 2 [before 日, 一, 二, 三, 四, 五, 六, 几] day of the week 今天星期几？ Jīntiān xīngqī jǐ？ What day (of the week) is it today? 3 abbreviation Sunday (Sun.)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33467136"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">我们</headword><headword charset="tc">我們</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">wo3men5</pron><defn>pronoun we; us</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="32397824"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">吃饭</headword><headword charset="tc">吃飯</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">chi1//fan4</pron><defn>verb 1 eat; have a meal 吃饭防噎 chīfàn fáng yē take care not to choke while eating—be very cautious 吃(过)饭了吗？ Chī guò fàn le ma？ (lit. “Have you eaten?”) Hello! 吃了饭再走吧！ Chī le fàn zài zǒu ba! Don’t go. Stay for dinner. 2 keep alive; make a living 靠打猎吃饭 kào dǎliè chīfàn make a living by hunting 只有增加生产, 才能解决吃饭问题。 Zhǐ yǒu zēngjiā shēngchǎn, cái néng jiějué chīfàn wèntí. Only by increasing production can we feed everyone.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="18665472"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">吃</headword><headword charset="tc">吃</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">chi1</pron><defn>verb 1 eat; take 吃茶 chīchá drink tea 吃糖 chītáng have some sweets 吃药 chīyào take medicine 吃苹果 chī píngguǒ eat an apple 吃得很饱 chī de hěn bǎo have eaten one’s fill; be quite full 2 have one&apos;s meals; eat somewhere 吃食堂 chī shítáng have one’s meals in the mess 3 live on (or off) 吃利息 chī lìxī live on interest 4 annihilate; wipe out 吃掉敌军一个师 chī diào díjūn yī ge shī annihilate an enemy division 吃一个子儿 chī yī gèzir take a piece (in chess) 5 exhaust; be a strain on 吃力 chīlì strenuous; difficult 6 absorb; soak up 茄子很吃油。 Qiézi hěn chī yóu. Eggplants need a lot of oil in cooking. 这种纸不吃墨水。 Zhèzhǒng zhǐ bù chī mòshuǐ. This kind of paper does not absorb ink. 7 suffer; bear; incur 吃黄牌 chī huángpái get a yellow card 连吃败仗 lián chī bàizhàng suffer one defeat after another 腿上吃了一枪 Tuǐ shàng chī le yī qiāng wounded by a shot in the leg 我可不吃这一套。 Wǒ kě bù chī zhè yī tào. I won’t put up with this. or I am not impressed. 
preposition VARIANT OF 17372672被bei4被 [used in a passive structure to introduce either the doer of the action, or the action alone] by 吃笑 chī xiào be laughed at 吃拳头 chī quántou get a beating 吃人耻笑 chī rén chǐxiào be an object of ridicule 
adjective stammer; stutter 口吃 kǒuchī speak with a stammer; stutter</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="18656512"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">去</headword><headword charset="tc">去</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">qu4</pron><defn>verb 1 go; go to (a place) 我去。 Wǒ qù. I’ll go. 他已经去了。 Tā yǐjing qù le. He has already gone. 我要去南京了。 Wǒ yào qù Nánjīng le. I’m going to Nanjing. 我想去南京一趟。 Wǒ xiǎng qù Nánjīng yī tàng. I think I’ll take a trip to Nanjing. 我要去车站接人。 Wǒ yào qù chēzhàn jiē rén. I’m going to the station to meet someone. 他去了三天, 还没回来。 Tā qù le sān tiān, hái méi huílai. He’s been away for three days, and hasn’t come back yet. 昨天已经去了三个人。 Zuótiān yǐjing qù le sān ge rén. Three people went there yesterday. 我去了好几趟, 都没碰到他。 Wǒ qù le hǎojǐ tàng, dōu méi pèngdào tā. I went there several times, but never saw him. 2 cause to go; send there 给她去个电话。 Gěi tā qù ge diànhuà. Give her a call. 我给他去过两封信。 Wǒ gěi tā qù guò liǎng fēng xìn. I sent him two letters. 我们只去了个代表。 Wǒmen zhǐ qù le ge dàibiǎo. We only sent a representative. 已经去了一个电报。 Yǐjing qù le yī ge diànbào. A telegram has been sent (to him). 3 remove; get rid of 去头屑 Qù tóu xiè get rid of dandruff 去殖民化 qù zhímínhuà decolonize 去了皮再吃。 Qù le pí zài chī. Peel it before you eat it. 汽油能去油迹。 Qìyóu néng qù yóujì. Gas is good for taking out oil stains. 裙子太长了, 去两公分吧。 qúnzi tài cháng le, qù liǎng gōngfēn ba. The skirt is too long—shorten it by two centimetres. 这句话去几个字就简洁了。 Zhè jù huà qù jǐ ge zì jiù jiǎnjié le. Take out one or two words and the sentence will be more concise. 4 [before and / or after a verb] go in order to; be going to (do sth. there) 咱们去看电影。(= 咱们看电影去。= 咱们去看电影去。) Zánmen qù kàn diànyǐng. (or) zánmen kàn diànyǐng qù. (or) zánmen qù kàn diànyǐng qù. Let’s go to see a movie. 这件事我去办吧。 Zhè jiàn shì wǒ qù bàn ba Let me (go and) arrange this. 你去打水, 我来生炉子。 Nǐ qù dǎ shuǐ, wǒ lái shēng lúzi. You get some water and I’ll light the stove. 你别管, 让他自己去想办法。 Nǐ bié guǎn, ràng tā zìjǐ qù xiǎng bànfǎ. Don’t bother, let him figure it out for himself. 你们去研究研究, 看该怎么办。 Nǐmen qù yánjiū yánjiū, kàn gāi zěnme bàn. Go and make a study of it, and see what’s the best thing to do. 5 [between two verbal expressions, and / or after the second expression] in order to (do sth. there) 用科学的观点去观察事物 Yòng kēxué de guāndiǎn qù guānchá shìwù look at things from a scientific point of view 他回家吃饭去了。 Tā huíjiā chī fàn qù le. He went home to eat. 她上街去买东西了。(= 她上街买东西去了。= 她上街去买东西去了。) Tā shàngjiē qù mǎi dōngxi le. (or) tā shàngjiē mǎi dōngxi qù le. (or) tā shàngjiē qù mǎi dōngxi qù le. She went to the market to do some shopping. 他提了一桶水去浇花。 Tā tí le yī tǒng shuǐ qù jiāo huā. He took a bucket of water to water the flowers. 6 literary be apart from in space or time 去今五十年 Qù jīn wǔshí nián 50 years ago 两地相去四十里。 Liǎng de xiāng qù sìshí lǐ. The two places are 40 li apart. 7 literary depart from; leave See 28802304去国qu4guo2去国 8 euphemistic pass away; die 老太太昨夜去了。 lǎotàitai zuóyè qù le. The old lady died last night. 
noun abbreviation VARIANT OF 28804096去声qu4sheng1去声 1 falling tone (third of the four tones in classical Chinese pronunciation) 2 falling tone (fourth of the four tones in modern standard Chinese pronunciation) 
adjective just gone (or elapsed) 去秋 qù qiū last autumn 去冬今春 qùdōng jīnchūn last winter and this spring 
adverb dialect [with 了 as an intensive complement to certain adjectives with了] very; extremely 他家远了去了。 Tā jiā yuǎn le qù le. His home is far far away. 那片林子可大了去了。 Nà piàn línzi kě dà le qù le. That’s a really huge forest. 他到过的地方多了去了。 Tā dào guò de dìfang duō le qù le. He’s been to a great many places. 
verb play (a part or character) 他在京剧《闹天宫》里去猴王。 Tā zài Jīngjù 《Nào Tiāngōng》 lǐ qù hóuwáng. He played the Monkey King in the Beijing opera Trouble in Heaven.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="28800256"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">厨房</headword><headword charset="tc">廚房</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">chu2fang2</pron><defn>noun kitchen 厨房设备 chúfáng shèbèi kitchen equipment 厨房用具 chúfáng yòngjù kitchen (or cooking) utensils</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="18926336"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">怎么样</headword><headword charset="tc">怎麼樣</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zen3me5yang4</pron><defn>pronoun colloquial 1 how; what 你觉得怎么样？ Nǐ juéde zěnmeyàng？ How are you feeling? 你能把他怎么样？ Nǐ néng bǎ tā zěnmeyàng？ What can you do to him? or You can’t touch him! 后来这孩子怎么样了？ Hòulái zhè háizi zěnmeyàng le？ What became of the child? 演出的情况怎么样？ Yǎnchū de qíngkuàng zěnmeyàng？ How was the performance? 2 what&apos;s it like; how are things; what do you think 怎么样, 忙吗？抽支烟吧。 Zěnmeyàng, máng ma？ Chōu zhī yān ba. How are things, busy? Have a cigarette. 骑车去怎么样？ Qíchē qù zěnmeyàng？ How (or What) about going by bike? 四个菜, 一个汤, 怎么样？ Sì ge cài,  yī ge tāng, zěnmeyàng？ Four dishes and one soup—what do you think? 3 in a certain way; in any way; no matter how 人家怎么样做, 你也怎么样做。 Rénjia zěnmeyàng zuò, nǐ yě zěnmeyàng zuò. Do as everybody does. 我怎么样做都不对。 Wǒ zěnmeyàng zuò dōu bù duì. No matter what I do, I’m always wrong. 4 [used in the negative as a mild understatement] (not) up to much 她唱歌不怎么样。 Tā chànggē bù zěnmeyàng. She’s not much of a singer. 这个电影不怎么样。 Zhège diànyǐng bù zěnmeyàng. The film is pretty lousy. 他一时不小心, 我们也不好把他怎么样。 Tā yīshí bù xiǎoxīn, wǒmen yě bù hǎo bǎ tā zěnmeyàng. We couldn’t be too hard on him because he was just careless.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35693568"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">那里</headword><headword charset="tc">那裡</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">na4li3</pron><defn>pronoun that place; there 那里出产香蕉。 nàlǐ chūchǎn xiāngjiāo. That place produces bananas. 那里的气候怎么样？ nàlǐ de qìhòu zěnmeyàng？ What’s the weather like there? 我刚从那里回来。 Wǒ gāng cóng nàlǐ huílai. I’ve just come back from there. or I’ve just been there. 这个星期天, 老张那里有个聚会。 zhège Xīngqītiān, lǎo zhāng nàlǐ yǒu ge jùhuì. There’ll be a get-together at Lao Zhang’s place this coming Sunday.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="67262179"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">中餐</headword><headword charset="tc">中餐</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zhong1can1</pron><defn>noun Chinese meal; Chinese food; Chinese cuisine</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="36350720"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">餐</headword><headword charset="tc">餐</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">can1</pron><defn>noun food; meal 西餐 xīcān Western-style food 中餐 Zhōngcān Chinese food 
verb eat 饱餐一顿 bǎocānyīdùn eat and drink to one’s heart’s content; have a good meal 
measure word [for meals] 一日三餐 yīrìsāncān three meals a day</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="18124032"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">好吃</headword><headword charset="tc">好吃</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hao3chi1</pron><defn>adjective tasty; delicious; nice 这道菜好看不好吃。 Zhè dào cài hǎokàn bù hǎochī. The dish looks good but is not tasty.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="61744099"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">没问题</headword><headword charset="tc">没问题</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">mei2 wen4ti2</pron><defn> 没 not, have not, none; drown, sinkRadical: 水; Stroke count: 7; HSK level: 1; General Standard: #867; Frequency rank: 72 问 ask about, inquire afterRadical: 門; Stroke count: 6; HSK level: 2; General Standard: #528; Frequency rank: 137 题 forehead; title, headline; themeRadical: 頁; Stroke count: 15; HSK level: 2; General Standard: #3233; Frequency rank: 218</defn></entry><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">六月</headword><headword charset="tc">六月</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">liu4yue4</pron><defn>noun 1 June 2 sixth month of the lunar year; sixth moon 六月雪 liù yuè xuě snowing in June—unjust charge (or verdict)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26130176"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">日</headword><headword charset="tc">日</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ri4</pron><defn>noun 1 sun; solar 日落月出。 rì luòyuè chū. The sun has set and the moon risen. 酷日当空。 Kù rì dāngkōng. The hot sun is high in sky. 2 daytime; day (opp. 夜) 单日 dānrì odd days 结算日 jiésuànrì settling day See 69442019日复一日ri4fu4yi1ri4日复一日 3 day 一日, 老王来我家。 Yī rì, lǎo wáng lái wǒ jiā. One day, Lao Wang came to my place. 4 daily; every day; with each passing day 日工资 rìgōngzī daily wages 日周期 rì zhōuqī daily rhythm 日降水量 rì jiàngshuǐliàng daily precipitation 日服三次 rì fú sān cì three times daily 产量日增。 Chǎnliàng rì zēng. Output is going up every day. 5 time 近日 jìnrì recently 6 season 春日 chūnrì springtime; spring 7 special day; specified day 生日 shēngrì birthday 消费者权益日 xiāofèizhě quányì rì Consumer Rights and Interests Day 
noun abbreviation Japan 在日期间 zài rì qījiān during one’s stay in Japan</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="29072896"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">星期日</headword><headword charset="tc">星期日</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Xing1qi1ri4</pron><defn>Sunday (Sun.)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33467904"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">星期一</headword><headword charset="tc">星期一</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Xing1qi1yi1</pron><defn>Monday (Mon.)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33468928"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">星期二</headword><headword charset="tc">星期二</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Xing1qi1er4</pron><defn>Tuesday (Tues.)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33467392"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">星期三</headword><headword charset="tc">星期三</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Xing1qi1san1</pron><defn>Wednesday (Wed.)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33468160"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">星期四</headword><headword charset="tc">星期四</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Xing1qi1si4</pron><defn>Thursday (Thur. or Thurs.)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33468416"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">星期五</headword><headword charset="tc">星期五</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Xing1qi1wu3</pron><defn>Friday (Fri.)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33468672"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">星期六</headword><headword charset="tc">星期六</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Xing1qi1liu4</pron><defn>Saturday (Sat.)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33467648"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">打</headword><headword charset="tc">打</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">da3</pron><defn>verb 1 strike; hit; knock 打稻子 dǎ dàozi thresh rice 钟打了十下。 Zhōng dǎ le shí xià. The clock struck ten. 2 break; smash 我打了一个碗。 Wǒ dǎ le yī ge wǎn. I broke a bowl. 3 beat; fight; attack 打硬仗 dǎ yìngzhàng fight a hard battle 两个人打了起来。 Liǎng ge rén dǎ le qǐlai. The two men came to blows. 4 deal with sb. or sth. 打官司 dǎguānsi engage in a lawsuit 5 construct; build 打坝 Dǎ bà construct a dam 打田埂 dǎ tiángěng build low ridges between paddy fields 6 make (articles of daily use) 打把刀 dǎ bǎ dāo forge a knife 打家具 dǎ jiāju make furniture 7 mix; stir; beat 打鸡蛋 dǎ jīdàn beat eggs 打糨子 dǎ jiàngzi mix paste 8 tie up; pack 打成捆 dǎ chéng kǔn tie (things) up in a bundle 打行李 dǎ xíngli pack one’s luggage; pack up 9 knit; weave 打草鞋 dǎ cǎoxié weave straw sandals 打毛衣 dǎ máoyī knit a sweater 10 draw; paint; make a mark on 打方格儿 dǎ fānggér draw squares 打个问号 dǎ ge wèn hào put a question mark; put a query 11 spray; spread 打农药 dǎ nóngyào spray insecticide 给地板打蜡 gěi dìbǎn dǎ là wax the floor 12 open; dig 打井 dǎjǐng dig (or sink) a well 打炮眼 dǎ pàoyǎn drill a blasting hole 13 hold up; hoist; raise 打伞 dǎsǎn hold up an umbrella 打灯笼 dǎ dēnglong carry a lantern 打起精神来 dǎ qǐ jīngshén lái raise one’s spirits; cheer up 14 send; dispatch; project 打炮 dǎpào fire a cannon 打电报 dǎ diànbào send a telegram 打电话 dǎ diànhuà make a phone call 打手电 dǎ shǒudiàn flash a torch 打信号 dǎ xìnhào give a signal; signal 15 dialect issue or receive (a certificate, etc.) 打介绍信 dǎ jièshàoxìn write a letter of introduction (for sb.); get a letter of introduction (from one’s organization) 16 remove; get rid of 打蛔虫 dǎ huíchóng take medicine to get rid of roundworms; take worm medicine 17 ladle; draw 打粥 dǎ zhōu ladle gruel 打盆水 dǎ pén shuǐ fetch a basin of water 从井里打水 cóng jǐng lǐ dǎ shuǐ draw water from a well 18 buy 打票 dǎpiào buy a (train, bus, etc.) ticket 打酱油 dǎ jiàngyóu buy soy sauce (in a small quantity with one’s own container) 19 catch; hunt 打鱼 dǎyú catch fish 20 gather in; collect; reap 打柴 dǎchái gather firewood 打了八百斤麦子 dǎ le bābǎi jīn màizi get in 400 kilos of wheat 21 estimate; calculate; reckon 成本打二百块钱 chéngběn dǎ èrbǎi kuài qián estimate (or reckon) the cost at 200 yuan 损耗已经打进去了。 Sǔnhào yǐjing dǎ jìnqu le. Allowances have been made for damages. 22 work out 打个稿 dǎ ge gǎo work out a draft 23 do; engage in 打短工 dǎ duǎngōng work as a day or seasonal labourer; be a temporary worker 24 play 打篮球 dǎ lánqiú play basketball 打扑克 dǎ pūkè play cards 打秋千 dǎ qiūqiān have a swing 25 go through (or perform) (some physical action) 打喷嚏 dǎ pēntì sneeze 打手势 dǎ shǒushì make a gesture; gesticulate 打个跟斗 dǎ ge gēndou turn (or do) a somersault 26 adopt; use 打个比方 dǎ ge bǐfang draw an analogy 27 [used to give a clue to the answer when setting a riddle] 打一字。 dǎ yīzìr Guess what character it is. 28 take 打的 dǎdī take a taxi 
preposition dialect from; since 打那以后 dǎ nà yǐhòu since then 打门缝里往外看 dǎ ménfèng lǐ wǎng wài kàn look out through a crack in the door 你打哪儿来？ Nǐ dǎ nǎr lái？ Where have you come from?</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19326464"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">跟</headword><headword charset="tc">跟</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">gen1</pron><defn>noun heel 脚跟 jiǎogēn heel 高跟鞋 gāogēnxié high-heeled shoes 平跟鞋 píng gēn xié flat(-heeled) shoes 
verb 1 follow 跟我来。 Gēn wǒ lái. Come along with me. or Follow me. 请跟我念。 Qǐng gēn wǒ niàn. Please read after me. 你们走得太快, 我跟不上。 Nǐmen zǒu de tài kuài, wǒ gēnbushàng. You all walk too fast. I can’t keep up with you. 紧跟形势 jǐngēn xíngshì keep abreast of the current situation 2 (of a woman) marry sb. 他要是老这样游手好闲我就不跟他。 Tā yào shì lǎo zhèyàng yóushǒuhàoxián, wǒ jiù bù gēn tā. I won’t marry him if he doesn’t stop fooling around. 
preposition 1 [indicating accompaniment, relationship, involvement, etc.] with 跟父母住一块儿 Gēn fùmǔ zhù yīkuàir live with one’sparents 这件事跟他没有关系。 Zhè jiàn shì gēn tā méiyǒu guānxi. It has nothing to do with him. 2 [introducing the recipient of an action] 我有几句话跟你讲。 Wǒ yǒu jǐ jù huà gēn nǐ jiǎng. There’s something I want to talk to you about. 3 [expressing comparison] as; from 跟他一样高 gēn tā yīyàng gāo as tall as him 跟去年相比, 产量增加了百分之十。 Gēn qùnián xiāngbǐ, chǎnliàng zēngjiā le bǎifēn zhī shí. Output has increased by 10% over last year. 
conjunction and; with 他跟我都是四川人。 Tā gēn wǒ dōu shì Sìchuān rén. He and I are both from Sichuan.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="21626624"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">见面</headword><headword charset="tc">見面</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jian4//mian4</pron><defn>verb meet; see each other 初次见面 chū cì jiànmiàn meet for the first time 思想见面 sīxiǎng jiànmiàn each stating frankly what’s on his mind 要使产销直接见面 yào shǐ chǎn-xiāo zhíjiē jiànmiàn establish direct links between the producer and the seller 他俩经常见面。 Tā liǎ jīngcháng jiànmiàn. They see a lot of each other. 这个话剧将通过电视与观众见面。 Zhège huàjù jiāng tōngguò diànshì yǔ guānzhòng jiànmiàn. This play will be shown on the TV.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="23819008"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">看</headword><headword charset="tc">看</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">kan4</pron><defn>verb 1 see; look at; watch 看电视 kàn diànshì watch TV 看电影 kàn diànyǐng see a film; go to the movies 看球赛 kàn qiú sài watch a ball game 看演出 kàn yǎnchū attend a performance 看展览 kàn zhǎnlǎn visit an exhibition 2 read (silently) 看报 kànbào read a newspaper 看谱 kànpǔ read music score 看书 kànshū read (a book) 3 think; consider; judge 看清形势 kàn qīng xíngshì make a correct appraisal of the situation 全面地看问题 quánmiàn de kàn wèntí look at (or approach) an issue from all angles 你看她这个人可靠吗？ Nǐ kàn tā zhège rén kěkào ma？ Do you think she’s reliable? 你对这件事怎么看？ Nǐ duì zhè jiàn shì zěnme kàn？ What’s your view on this matter? 4 look upon; regard 把公众的利益看得高于一切 bǎ gōngzhòng de lìyì kàn de gāoyú yīqiè put the interests of the public above all else 5 see (or consult) (a doctor); treat (a patient or an illness) 李大夫把她的肺炎看好了。 Lǐ dàifu bǎ tā de fèiyán kàn hǎo le. Dr. Li has cured her of pneumonia. 有病就该去看。 Yǒu bìng jiù gāi qù kàn. You ought to go and see a doctor when you are ill. 6 look after 衣帽自看。 Yī-mào zì kàn. Take care of your own hats and coats. 7 call on; visit; see 我明天去看他。 Wǒ míngtiān qù kàn tā. I’ll go and see him tomorrow. 有空我来看你。 Yǒukòng wǒ lái kàn nǐ. I’lldrop in on you when I have time. 8 depend on; rely on; fall back on 我们明天是不是出游, 得看天气。 wǒmen míngtiān shìbushì chūyóu, děikàn tiānqì. Whether we’ll go on a sightseeing trip tomorrow will depend on the weather. 9 mind; watch out 别跑这么快！看摔着！ Bié pǎo zhème kuài! Kàn shuāi zhe! Don’t run so fast! Mind you don’t fall. 10 [before some verbs or adjectives] tend to; be expected See 24863488看跌kan4die1看跌 
auxiliary 1 [after a reduplicated verb or a verb phrase] try and see (what happens) 试试看 shìshikàn have a try 等一等看 děng yī děng kàn wait and see 尝尝看。 Chángchang kàn. Just taste this. 2 [in exclamations to express surprise or rebuke, esp. in the phrase 看你 or 你看你] 看你, 水都烧干了。 Kàn nǐ, shuǐ dōu shāo gān le. Look what you’ve done! The water has all boiled away. 你看你！怎么满头大汗啊！ Nǐ kàn nǐ! Zěnme mǎntóudàhàn a! Look at yourself! How come you’re bathed in sweat!</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="24859392"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">书</headword><headword charset="tc">書</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shu1</pron><defn>noun 1 book 一本关于中国历史的新书 yī běn guānyú Zhōngguó lìshǐ de xīnshū a new work on Chinese history 2 style of calligraphy; script 楷书 kǎishū regular script 3 literary letter 家书 jiāshū letter from home 4 document 证书 zhèngshū certificate; credential 
verb literary write 振笔直书 zhènbǐzhíshū take up the pen and write vigorously</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30410752"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">上班</headword><headword charset="tc">上班</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shang4//ban1</pron><defn>verb go to work; start work; be on duty (opp. 下班儿) 她上班去了。 Tā shàngbān qù le. She’s gone to work. 下午不上班。 Xiàwǔ bù shàngbān. We’ll take the afternoon off. or No work this afternoon. 我们每天早上八点钟上班。 Wǒmen měitiān zǎoshang bā diǎn zhōng shàngbān. We start work at 8 every morning. 他一般骑车上下班。 Tā yībān qíchē shàngxiàbān. He usually rides bike to and from work.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="29567232"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">学</headword><headword charset="tc">學</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xue2</pron><defn>noun 1 learning; knowledge 博学 bóxué learned; erudite 2 subject of study; branch of learning 数学 shùxué mathematics 文学 wénxué literature 3 school; college 大学 dàxué university; college 上学 shàngxué go to school; attend school; be at school 
verb 1 study; learn 学外语 xué wàiyǔ learn (or study) a foreign language 学文化 xué wénhuà acquire an elementary education; learn to read and write 学先进 xué xiānjìn emulate the advanced 学游泳 xué yóuyǒng learn swimming 把新技术学到手 bǎ xīn jìshù xué dào shǒu master a new skill 学而不化, 不如不学。 xué ér bù huà, bùrú bù xué. Better unlearned than ill-learned. 学而不思则罔；思而不学则殆。(《论语》) xué ér bù sī zé wǎng; sī ér bù xué zé dài. Learning without thought means labour lost; thought without learning is perilous. 2 imitate; mimic 这孩子学他爸爸走路的样子。 Zhè háizi xué tā bàba zǒulù de yàngzi. The boy imitates his father’s way of walking.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33758720"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">派对</headword><headword charset="tc">派對</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">pai4dui4</pron><defn>noun transliteration colloquial party; gathering (usu. social) 新年派对 xīnnián pàiduì New Year’s party</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="42570674"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">这个</headword><headword charset="tc">這個</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zhe4ge5</pron><defn>pronoun 1 this one; this 这个比那个沉。 Zhège bǐ nàge chén. This one is heavier than that. 这个孩子真乖。 Zhège háizi zhēn guāi. This child is a little dear. 他为了这个忙了好几天。 Tā wèile zhège máng le hǎojǐ tiān. He’s been busy with this for quite a few days. 2 colloquial [before a verb or adjective to give force to it] so; such 看见大象吹口琴, 孩子们这个乐啊！ Kànjian dàxiàng chuī kǒuqín, háizi men zhège yuè a! When they saw the elephant blowing the mouth organ, the children squealed with laughter. 3 [repeated to show hesitation] 他叫这个这个我想不起来了。 Tā jiào zhège zhège wǒ xiǎng bù qǐlai le. His name is...ah...I cannot remember.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35939840"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">下个</headword><headword charset="tc">下個</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xia4ge5</pron><defn>1 second (of two parts) 2 next (week etc) 3 subsequent 4 the following</defn></entry><catassign category="Lektion6"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">上个</headword><headword charset="tc">上個</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shang4ge5</pron><defn>1 first (of two parts) 2 last (week etc) 3 previous 4 the above</defn></entry><catassign category="Lektion6"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">去年</headword><headword charset="tc">去年</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">qu4nian2</pron><defn>noun last year 去年此时 qùnián cǐshí this time last year 去年十二月 qùnián Shí&apos;èryuè last December</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="28803840"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">今年</headword><headword charset="tc">今年</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jin1nian2</pron><defn>noun this year</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="24220160"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">明年</headword><headword charset="tc">明年</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ming2nian2</pron><defn>noun next year</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26928128"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">昨天</headword><headword charset="tc">昨天</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zuo2tian1</pron><defn>noun yesterday</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="37104640"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">明天</headword><headword charset="tc">明天</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ming2tian1</pron><defn>noun 1 tomorrow 2 near future 光辉灿烂的明天 Guānghuīcànlàn de míngtiān bright future</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26932480"/><catassign category="Lektion6"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">周末</headword><headword charset="tc">週末</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zhou1mo4</pron><defn>noun weekend 长周末 cháng zhōumò a long weekend 周末不营业 zhōumò bù yíngyè closed over the weekend 我们在三亚度过了一个愉快的周末。 wǒmen zài sān yà dùguò le yī ge yúkuài dezhōumò. We spent a lovely weekend in Sanya.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="36475136"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">有</headword><headword charset="tc">有</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">you3</pron><defn>verb 1 have; possess; own 有办法 yǒubànfǎ be resourceful; have a way 有背景 yǒu bèijǐng have powerful connections 有奔头 yǒu bèntóu have a bright prospect 有出息 yǒu chūxī be promising 有版权的作品 yǒu bǎnquán de zuòpǐn work in private domain 有百利而无一弊 Yǒu bǎi lì ér wú yī bì have every advantage and no drawback 有儿才知父母恩。 yǒu r cái zhī fùmǔ ēn. Only when one has children does he know what parental love is. 她有热情, 有朝气。 Tā yǒu rèqíng, yǒu zhāoqì. She is full of vigour and enthusiasm. 2 there is; exist; contain 有必要 yǒu bìyào oblige; be necessary 有电话找你。 yǒu diànhuà zhǎo nǐ. A phone call for you. 有饭大家吃。 yǒu fàn dàjiā chī. If there is food, let everyone share it. 屋里有人吗？ Wū lǐ yǒurén ma？ Anybody in the room? 这座位有人吗？ Zhè zuò wèi yǒu rén ma？ Is this seat taken? 还有许多工作要做。 Háiyǒu xǔduō gōngzuò yào zuò. Much still remains to be done. 3 [making an estimate or a comparison] 他有十岁了吧？ Tā yǒu shí suì le ba？ He is about ten, I guess. 问题有那么严重吗？ Wèntí yǒu nàme yánzhòng ma？ Is the problem that serious? 我不知道鱼还有那么贵。 Wǒ bù zhīdao yú háiyǒu nàme guì. I didn’t know fish was that expensive. 4 [indicating action] 有很大进步 yǒu hěn dà jìnbù make great progress 一有问题就去解决 yī yǒu wèntí jiù qù jiějué deal with a problem as soon as it crops up 有消息就通知我。 yǒu xiāoxi jiù tōngzhī wǒ. Keep me informed. 形势有了新发展。 Xíngshì yǒu le xīn fāzhǎn. There are new developments in the situation. 5 [denoting condition or concession] 有水便有鱼。 yǒu shuǐ biànyǒu yú. If there’s water, there must be fish. 6 [expressing the idea of having plenty of or lasting a long period] 有本事 yǒu běnshi be capable 有经验 yǒu jīngyàn be experienced 有学问 yǒuxuéwèn be well-learned; be a scholar 有了年纪 yǒu le niánjì be getting on in years 她结婚可有些年头了。 Tā jiéhūn kě yǒu xiē niántóu le. She has married for years. 7 [expressing an indefinite reference] 有保留 yǒu bǎoliú with a hook at the end 有时候 yǒushíhou sometimes 有人说可以, 有人说不可以。 Yǒurén shuō kěyǐ, yǒurén shuō bù kěyǐ. Some say yes, some say no. 有些事还需要商量。 Yǒuxiē shì hái xūyào shāngliang. Certain things are still open to discussion. 有一天我在街上碰见他了。 Yǒu yī tiān wǒ zài jiēshang pèngjiàn tā le. One day I ran into him in the street. 这个措施有地方适用, 有地方不适用。 Zhège cuòshī yǒu dìfang shìyòng, yǒu dìfang bù shìyòng. This measure is suited to some localities, but not to others. 8 [after certain monosyllabic verbs to form single words] 这家伙怀有不可告人的目的。 Zhè jiāhuo huáiyǒu bùkěgàorén de mùdì. That fellow has an underhand scheme. 这种水果含有多种维生素。 Zhèzhǒng shuǐguǒ hányǒu duōzhǒng wéishēngsù. This fruit contains vitamins. 9 [expressing politeness] See 35079936有劳you3lao2有劳;35090944有请you3qing3有请 10 [answering a roll call] here; present “王钢！”“有！” “wáng gāng!” “yǒu!” “Wang Gang!” “Present!” 
auxiliary dialect have 我有去过那里。 Wǒ yǒu qù guò nàli. I have been there. 
affix literary [before the names of certain dynasties] 有夏 Yǒuxià the Xia Dynasty 有宋一代 yǒu Sòng yīdài the Song period 诗至有唐为极盛。 Shī zhì yǒu táng wéi jí chéng. During the Tang period poetry attained the acme of its development.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35063040"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">时间</headword><headword charset="tc">時間</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shi2jian1</pron><defn>noun 1 (the concept of) time 时间与空间 Shíjiān yǔ kōngjiān time and space 时间就是金钱。 shíjiān jiùshì jīnqián. Time is money. 时间过得真快呀, 不知不觉三年过去了。 shíjiān guò de zhēn kuài ya, bùzhībùjué sān nián guòqule. Where has the time gone! Three years have slipped by unnoticed. 2 (the duration of) time 时间掌握得好 shíjiān zhǎngwò de hǎo good timing; well-timed 费时间 fèi shíjiān time-consuming 办公时间 bàngōng shíjiān office hours 不给对手喘息的时间 bù gěi duìshǒu chuǎnxī de shíjiān give one’s opponent no breathing space 时间到了。 Shíjiān dào le. Time’s up. 时间紧, 任务重。 shíjiān jǐn, rènwu zhòng. Time is pressing and the task heavy. 你做这事用了多少时间？ Nǐ zuò zhè shì yòng le duōshaoshíjiān? How much time did you spend on this? 3 (a point in) time 北京时间十九点整 Běijīng shíjiān shíjiǔ diǎn zhěng 19 hours Beijing Time 现在的时间是四点(零)五分。 Xiànzài deshíjiān shì sì diǎn wǔfēn. The time now is five minutes past four.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30074112"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">要</headword><headword charset="tc">要</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">yao4</pron><defn>noun main points; essentials 择要记录 Zéyào jìlù note down the essential points 
adjective important; essential 要法 yào fǎ important method; necessary way 上述规定希严格执行为要。 Shàngshù guīdìng xī yángé zhíxíng wéi yào. It is imperative that the above rules be strictly observed. 
verb 1 want; ask for; wish; desire 谁没有票, 问她要。 Shuí méi yǒu piào, wèn tā yào. Anyone without a ticket can ask her for one. 他要一架手风琴。 Tā yào yī jià shǒufēngqín. He wants an accordion. 我要了两个菜。 Wǒ yào le liǎng ge cài. I ordered two dishes. 这双鞋我还要呢。 Zhè shuāng xié wǒ háiyào ne. I want to keep these shoes. 2 ask (or want) sb. to do sth. 不是你要我来的吗？ Bù shì nǐ yào wǒ lái de ma？ Wasn’t it you who asked me to come? 3 need; take 这活儿要不了这么多人。 Zhè huór yàobuliǎo zhème duō rén. You don’t need so many people for this job. 这项任务要十天才能完成。 Zhè xiàng rènwu yào shí tiān cái néng wánchéng. It will take ten days to get the work done. 
verb 1 must; should; it is necessary (or imperative, essential) 借东西要还。 Jiè dōngxi yào huán. One should return what one borrows. 我要不要留下来？ Wǒ yào bù yào liú xià lái？ Shall I stay? 这个问题要仔细考虑。 Zhège wèntí yào zǐxì kǎolǜ. This question calls for careful consideration. 2 shall; will; be going to 要下雨了。 Yào xià yǔ le. It’s going to rain. 他快要回来了。 Tā kuàiyào huílai le. He will soon be back. 天要黑了, 快走吧。 Tiān yào hēi le, kuài zǒu ba. It’s getting dark. Let’s hurry up! 会议要到月底才能结束。 Huìyì yào dào yuèdǐ cái néng jiéshù. The conference will not end till the end of the month. 3 want to; wish to 他要学游泳。 Tā yào xué yóuyǒng. He wants to learn swimming. 我还有几句话要说。 Wǒ háiyǒu jǐ jù huà yào shuō. I’d like to say a few more words. 4 [in comparisons to indicate an estimate] 树荫底下比屋子里要凉快些。 shùyīn dǐxia bǐ wūzi lǐ yào liángkuai xiē. It is cooler under the tree than in the room. 
conjunction 1 if; suppose; in case 明天要下雨, 我们就不去了。 Míngtiān yào xiàyǔ, wǒmen jiù bù qù le. If it rains tomorrow, we won’t go. 他要来不了呢？ Tā yào láibuliǎo ne？ Suppose he can’t come? 我要赶不回来, 你替我说一声。 Wǒ yào gǎn bù huílai, nǐ tì wǒ shuō yī shēng. In case I can’t get back in time, please apologize for me. 这有什么可怕的, 要我就不怕。 Zhè yǒu shénme kěpà de, yào wǒ jiù bù pà. What is there to be afraid of? I wouldn’t be afraid if I were you. 2 [usu. with 就 or 就是] or; either... or... 要就去跳舞, 要就去听音乐, 别处我不去。 Yào jiù qù tiàowǔ,  yào jiù qù tīng yīnyuè, biéchù wǒ bù qù. Let’s go either to the dance or to the concert. I won’t go anywhere else.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34253568"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">爷爷</headword><headword charset="tc">爺爺</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ye2ye5</pron><defn>noun colloquial 1 (paternal) grandfather 2 [respectful form of addressing any old man] grandpa</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34274816"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">计划</headword><headword charset="tc">計劃</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ji4hua4</pron><defn>noun plan; project; programme 河流开发计划 héliú kāifā jìhuà river development programme 切实可行的计划 qièshíkěxíng de jìhuà feasible (or workable) plan 有计划地进行 yǒu jìhuà de jìnxíng proceed in a planned way 
verb map out; plan 计划好了再动手干。 Jìhuà hǎo le zài dòngshǒu gàn. Map it out before you start.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="23519232"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">没有</headword><headword charset="tc">沒有</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">mei2you5</pron><defn>verb 1 not have; be without 没有矛盾, 就没有世界。 Méiyǒu máodùn, jiù méiyou shìjiè. Without contradictions nothing would exist. 我没有多余的录音带。 Wǒ méiyou duōyú de lùyīndài. I don’t have cassettes to spare. 2 there is not 屋里没有人。 Wū lǐ méiyou rén. There is no one in the room. 3 [before 谁 or 哪个 to mean “nobody”] 没有哪个说过这样的话。 méiyou nǎge shuō guò zhèyàng de huà. No one ever said that. 4 not be as...as 谁都跑得没有他快。 Shuí dōu pǎo de méiyou tā kuài. No one runs as fast as he. 5 [before numerals] less than; not more than 他来了还没有三天就走了。 Tā lái le hái méiyou sān tiān jiù zǒu le. He was here less than three days. 这间屋子没有十平方米。 Zhè jiān wūzi méiyou shí píngfāngmǐ. This room is not more than 10 square metres. 
adverb 1 [before a verb to deny the occurrence or accomplishment of action] 昨天没有下雨。 zuótiān méiyou xiàyǔ. It didn’t rain yesterday. 2 [before an adjective to deny condition] not yet 衣服还没有干。 Yīfu hái méiyou gān. The clothes aren’t dry yet. 3 [at the end of a sentence to indicate objective question] 去了没有？ Qùleméiyou? Did you go there? 4 [in an interrogative sentence to express suspicion or surprise] 你没有听到这个消息(吗)？ Nǐ méiyou tīngdào zhège xiāoxi? You didn’t hear the news? 5 [answering questions] 你看见他了没有？——没有。 Nǐ kànjian tā le méiyou？ —— méiyou. Did you see him? — No, I didn’t.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26615296"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">一起</headword><headword charset="tc">一起</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">yi1qi3</pron><defn>adverb 1 in the same place 住在一起 Zhù zài yīqǐ live in the same place 2 together; in company 我不跟他一起走。 Wǒ bù gēn tā yīqǐ zǒu. I won’t go along with him. 让我们团结在一起, 战斗在一起, 胜利在一起。 Ràng wǒmen tuánjié zài yīqǐ,  zhàndòu zài yīqǐ, shènglì zài yīqǐ. Let us stand together, fight together and win together. 3 dialect altogether; in all 这几件东西一起多少钱？ Zhè jǐ jiàn dōngxi yī qǐ duōshao qián？ How much is that altogether? 
noun dialect same group; same side 你们是一起的吗？ Nǐmen shì yīqǐ de ma? Are you of the same group?</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34398464"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">几点</headword><headword charset="tc">幾點</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ji3dian3</pron><defn>1 what time? 2 when?</defn></entry><dictref dictcreator="19125399" dictid="-1278474637" entryid="29"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">点</headword><headword charset="tc">點</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">dian3</pron><defn>noun 1 drop (of liquid) 雨点儿 yǔdiǎnr raindrop 2 spot; dot; speck 墨点儿 mòdiǎnr ink spots 3 dot stroke (in Chinese characters) 4 mathematics point 两点成一直线。 Liǎng diǎn chéng yī zhíxiàn. A straight line is formed by connecting two points. 5 decimal point; point 三点儿五 Sāndiǎnr wǔ three point five (3.5) 6 place; point 突破一点 tūpò yīdiǎn make a breakthrough at one point 7 aspect; feature 从这点上看 cóng zhè diǎn shàng kàn viewed from this aspect 对这一点没人怀疑。 Duì zhè yīdiǎn méi rén huáiyí. Nobody has any doubt about that. 8 finance point 上证指数收涨44点。 Shàngzhèng Zhǐshù shōu zhǎng 44 diǎn. The Shanghai Composite Index ended up 44 points. 
verb 1 place a dot 点三个点儿表示省略 diǎn sān ge diǎnr biǎoshì shěnglüè a sequence of three dots marks an omission 2 touch on very briefly; skim 他用篙一点就把船撑开了。 Tā yòng gāo yīdiǎn jiù bǎ chuán chēng kāi le. He pushed the boat off with a shove of the pole. 她发言时点(到)了这件事。 tā fāyán shí diǎn le zhè jiàn shì. She touched on the matter in her speech. 3 drip 点眼药 diǎn yǎnyào put drops in the eyes 4 sow in holes; dibble 点豆子 diǎn dòuzi dibble beans 5 check one by one; count 点货 diǎnhuò check over goods; take stock 请把钱点一点。 Qǐng bǎ qián diǎn yī diǎn. Please count the money. 6 select; choose 他点了牛排。 Tā diǎn le niúpái. He ordered a steak. 7 hint; point out 一点他就明白了。 Yīdiǎn tā jiù míngbai le. He quickly took the hint. 8 light; burn; kindle 点灯 diǎn dēng light a lamp 他是火爆性子, 一点就着。 Tā shì huǒbào xìngzi, yīdiǎn jiùzhe. He’s got a fiery temper and flares up very quickly. 9 embellish; decorate 装点 zhuāngdiǎn furnish; decorate 
measure word 1 a little; a bit; some 读点儿鲁迅 Dú diǎn r Lǔ Xùn read some of Lu Xun’s works 给我点儿纸。 gěi wǒ diǎn r zhǐ. Give me some paper, will you? 他今天好点儿了。 Tā jīntiān hǎo diǎn r le. He’s feeling a bit better today. 人的认识一点儿也不能离开实践。 Rén de rènshi yī diǎn r yě bùnéng líkāi shíjiàn. Human knowledge cannot be separated from practice. 2 [for items] 我有几点不成熟的想法。 Wǒ yǒu jǐ diǎn bù chéngshú de xiǎngfa. I have some tentative suggestions. 
noun 1 o&apos;clock 上午九点(钟) Shàngwǔ jiǔ diǎn zhōng nine o’clock in the morning 现在几点了？ Xiànzài jǐ diǎn le？ What time is it now? 2 appointed time 到点了 Dào diǎn le it’s time (to do sth.) 3 VARIANT OF 76626147云板yun2ban3云板 dated iron bell or clapper (used by government offices or influential families to give time or announce an event) 
noun refreshments 茶点 chádiǎn tea and pastries 
noun printing point (a unit of measurement for type bodies)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19967744"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">半</headword><headword charset="tc">半</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ban4</pron><defn>number half 半年 bànnián six months; half a year 半小时 bàn xiǎoshí half an hour 价格减半 Jiàgé jiǎn bàn a 50% discount; halve the price 一个半月 yī ge bàn yuè a month and a half; one and a half months 与某人对半分 yǔ mǒurén duì bàn fēn go halves with sb. 增加一倍半 zēngjiā yī bèi bàn increase by 150% 
adjective 1 half; semi- 半机械化 bànjīxièhuà semi-mechanized 2 in the middle; halfway 半山腰 bànshānyāo halfway up a hill 半开玩笑地说 Bàn kāi wánxiào de shuō say half jokingly 房门半开着。 Fángmén bàn kāizhe. The door was half open. 3 very little; the least bit 他连半句话都不说。 Tā lián bàn jù huà dōu bù shuō. He didn’t breathe a word. or He said nothing.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="17141248"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">开始</headword><headword charset="tc">開始</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">kai1shi3</pron><defn>noun beginning; outset; commencement 一开始 yī kāishǐ at the very beginning 一种新的工作, 开始总会遇到一些困难。 Yī zhǒng xīn de gōngzuò, kāishǐ zǒng huì yùdào yīxiē kùnnan. You always run into some difficulties at the beginning of a new job. 
verb begin; start; commence 开始生效 kāishǐ shēngxiào take effect; come into effect (or force) 从头开始 cóngtóu kāishǐ start from the very beginning 开始讨论实质性问题 Kāishǐ tǎolùn shízhìxìng wèntí come to substantive questions 今天从第五课开始。 Jīntiān cóng dì-wǔ kè kāishǐ. Today we’ll begin with Lesson 5. 他们开始了旅行中最危险的阶段。 Tāmenkāishǐ le lǚxíng zhōng zuì wēixiǎn de jiēduàn. They entered upon the most dangerous part of the journey.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="24819456"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">电影院</headword><headword charset="tc">電影院</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">dian4ying3 yuan4</pron><defn>cinema; movie theater; movie (house)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="20032512"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">门口</headword><headword charset="tc">門口</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">men2kou3</pron><defn>noun entrance; doorway; threshold 在门口等候 Zài ménkǒu děnghòu wait at the door (or gate) 把客人送到门口 bǎ kèren sòng dào ménkǒu see the guest to the door</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26681344"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">见</headword><headword charset="tc">見</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jian4</pron><defn>noun view; opinion 依我之见 Yī wǒ zhī jiàn in my opinion; to my mind 
verb 1 see; catch sight of 只见一个人影闪过墙角 Zhǐjiàn yī ge rényǐng shǎn guò qiángjiǎo catch sight of sb. turning the corner 从来没见过这种鸟。 Cónglái méi jiàn guò zhèzhǒng niǎo. I’ve never seen a bird like that before. 2 meet with; be exposed to 见困难就上, 见荣誉就让 jiàn kùnnan jiùshàng, jiàn róngyù jiùràng dash forward where there are difficulties to overcome and draw back when honours are to be conferred; take difficulty for oneself and leave honours to others 冰见热就化。 Bīng jiàn rè jiù huà. Ice melts with heat. 这种药怕见光。 Zhèzhǒng yào pà jiàn guāng. This medicine is not to be exposed to daylight. 见人就献媚, 谁见谁讨厌。 jiàn rén jiù xiànmèi, shuí jiàn shuí tǎoyàn. Those who seek to please everybody please nobody. 3 show evidence of; appear to be 见诸报端 jiàn zhū bàoduān appear in newspapers 见之于行动 jiànzhīyúxíngdòng be translated into action 并不见瘦 bìng bù jiàn shòu not seem to be any thinner 4 refer to; see; vide 见第三十六页 jiàn dì-sān shíliù yè see page 36 情况已见好转。 Qíngkuàng yǐ jiàn hǎozhuǎn. The condition is improving. 5 meet; call on; see 待会儿见。 Dāihuir jiàn. See you later. 你见到他了没有？ Nǐ jiàndào tā le méiyǒu？ Did you meet him? 我不想见他。 Wǒ bù xiǎng jiàn tā. I don’t wish to see him. 她今天下午要来见你。 Tā jīntiān xiàwǔ yào lái jiàn nǐ. She’ll call on you this afternoon. 
verb literary 1 [before a verb to indicate the passive] 见爱 jiàn&apos;ài be loved (or liked); be regarded highly 2 [before a verb in polite requests] See 23814656见告jian4gao4见告</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="23810816"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">太</headword><headword charset="tc">太</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">tai4</pron><defn>adjective 1 highest; greatest 太空 tàikōng outer space 2 re-motest 太古 tàigǔ remote antiquity 3 more or most senior 太老伯 tàilǎobó grand-uncle; great-uncle 太老师 tàilǎoshī one’s teacher’s father; one’s father’s teacher 
adverb 1 excessively; too; over 那太过分了。 Nà tài guòfèn le. That’s going too far. 你太夸奖了。 Nǐ tài kuājiǎng le. You flatter me. 您太客气了。 Nín tài kèqi le. You are being too modest. or You are too kind. 你太相信这家伙了。 Nǐ tài xiāngxìn zhè jiāhuo le. You place too much trust in this fellow. 你车开得太快, 不安全。 Nǐ chē kāi de tài kuài, bù ānquán. You’re driving too fast, it&apos;s not safe. 水太热, 烫手。 Shuǐ tài rè, tàng shǒu. The water is scalding to the touch. 他太坚持己见了。 Tā tài jiānchí jǐjiàn le. He is much too stubborn in his opinions. 这座城市人口太多。 Zhè zuò chéngshì rénkǒu tài duō. The city is over-populated. 2 [expressing admiration or exclamation with 了 at the end of a sentence] 长城太伟大了。 Chángchéng tài wěidà le. The Great Wall is really amazing. 哥儿俩长得太像了。 Gērliǎ zhǎng de tài xiàng le. The two brothers are very much alike. 她的发音太好了。 Tā de fāyīn tài hǎo le. Her pronunciation is excellent. 我太感激你了。 Wǒ tài gǎnjī nǐ le. I can’t thank you enough. 又见到您, 太高兴了。 Yòu jiàndào nín, tài gāoxìng le. I’mso happy to see you again. 3 [before another adverb 不 to emphasize negation] 你太不虚心了。 Nǐ tài bù xūxīn le. You’re too proud. 这太不好了。 Zhè tài bù hǎo le. This is terrible. 这太不像话了！ Zhè tài bù xiànghuà le! This is simply outrageous! or This is too much! 这个人太不讲道理。 Zhège rén tài bù jiǎng dàoli. This man is absolutely unreasonable. 4 [after 不 to soften the tone of negation] 不太好 Bù tài hǎo not very good 你这样做不太合适吧。 Nǐ zhèyàng zuò bù tài héshì ba. That’s probably not very appropriate. 他不太愿意结交新朋友。 Tā bù tài yuànyi jiéjiāo xīn péngyou. He’s reluctant to make new friends. 这车看起来不太漂亮, 可就是快。 Zhè chē kàn qǐlai bù tài piàoliang, kě jiù shì kuài. The car isn’t much to look at, but it’s fast.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="31076608"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">了</headword><headword charset="tc">了</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">le5</pron><defn>auxiliary 1 [after a verb or an adjective to indicate the completion of an action, at a point in the past or before the beginning of another action, or an expected or presumed action] 把书读了两遍 bǎ shū dú le liǎng biàn have read the book twice 我下了班就去。 wǒ xià le bān jiù qù. I’ll go right after work. 水位低了两米。 Shuǐwèi dī le liǎng mǐ. The water level fell by two metres. 2 [at the end of a sentence, usu. after 了 for completed action, to indicate that sth. has taken place] 小说看了一半了。 Xiǎoshuō kàn le yībàn le. I have read half of the novel. 我等了半天了。 Wǒděng le bàntiān le. I’ve been waiting a long time. 3 [at the end of a sentence to indicate a change of situation or state, whether actual or envisaged] 他胖了。 Tā pàng le. He’s put on weight. 下雨了。 Xiàyǔ le. It’s raining. 东西贵了。 Dōngxi guì le. Things have gone up. or Things are expensive now. 树叶红了。 Shùyè hóng le. The leaves are turning red. 今天去不成了。 Jīntiān qù bù chéng le. We can’t go today. (Before the situation changed, we had thought we could go.) 你早来一天就见着他了。 Nǐ zǎo lái yī tiān jiù jiàn zhe tā le. If you’d come a day sooner you would have seen him. 我喝了五杯了, 不能再喝了。 Wǒ hē le wǔ bēi le, bùnéng zài hē le. I have drunk five glasses and can’t drink any more. 4 [after an adjective, with or without 太 “too”, to express an excessive degree, i.e. to indicate that sth. has gone to the extreme] 汤咸了。 Tāng xián le. The soup is too salty. 袖子长了。 Xiùzi cháng le. The sleeves are too long. 这种工作太累了。 Zhèzhǒng gōngzuò tài lèi le. This job is too fatiguing. 他现在太老了, 不能工作了。 Tā xiànzài tài lǎo le, bù néng gōngzuò le. He’s too old to work now. 5 [in commands or requests in response to a changed situation] 吃饭了！ Chīfàn le! Let’s eat now. 别说话了！ Bié shuōhuà le! Stop talking! 走了, 不能再等了！ Zǒu le, bùnéng zài děng le! Let’s go. We can’t wait any longer.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="25492224"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">朋友</headword><headword charset="tc">朋友</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">peng2you5</pron><defn>noun 1 friend 广交朋友 Guǎngjiāo péngyou make many friends 2 boyfriend or girlfriend 谈朋友 tánpéngyou have a boyfriend (or girlfriend); go steady; date</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27722752"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">晚上</headword><headword charset="tc">晚上</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">wan3shang5</pron><defn>noun (in the) evening; (at) night 晚上好。 Wǎnshang hǎo. Good evening.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="32070144"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">事</headword><headword charset="tc">事</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shi4</pron><defn>noun 1 matter; affair; thing; business 国家大事 guójiā dàshì state affairs 这事儿不好办。 zhè shì r bù hǎobàn. This matter is hard to manage. 这是怎么回事儿？ Zhè shì zěnme huí shì r? What’s this all about? or What’s happening? 2 trouble; accident 出事 chūshì meet with a mishap; have an accident 3 job; work 她找到事儿了。 Tā zhǎo dào shìr le. She’s got a job. or She’s found a job. 4 responsibility; involvement 没你的事。 Méi nǐ de shì. It’s none of your business. 这件案子里还有他的事儿呢。 Zhè jiàn ànzi lǐ hái yǒu tā deshì r ne. He was involved in this case too. 有我什么事儿, 干吗怪我？ Yǒu wǒ shénmeshì r, gànmá guài wǒ? I had nothing to do with it, so why blame me? 
verb literary 1 wait upon; serve 事父母 shì fùmǔ wait upon one’s parents 2 be engaged in 不事营生 bù shì yíngsheng lead an idle life</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30215936"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">上午</headword><headword charset="tc">上午</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shang4wu3</pron><defn>noun morning; forenoon (opp. 下午)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="29617152"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">分</headword><headword charset="tc">分</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">fen1</pron><defn>verb 1 divide; separate; part (opp. 合) 分组讨论 fēnzǔ tǎolùn hold discussions in groups 分阶段实行 Fēn jiēduàn shíxíng carry out stage by stage 一年分四季。 Yī nián fēn sìjì. The year is divided into four seasons. 这药分三次吃。 Zhè yào fēn sān cì chī. This medicine is to be taken in three separate doses. 他的头发往右边分。 Tā de tóufa wǎng yòubianfēn. He parts his hair on the right side. 一条河把县城分成两半。 Yī tiáo hé bǎ xiànchéng fēn chéng liǎngbàn. A river divides the county town into two parts. 2 distribute; assign; allot 她分到了一套新房子。 Tā fēn dào le yī tào xīn fángzi. She has been allotted a new flat. 把这个任务分给我们吧。 Bǎ zhège rènwu fēn gěi wǒmen ba. Assign (or Give) this task to us, please. 音乐会的票都已经分完了。 Yīnyuèhuì de piào dōu yǐjing fēn wán le. The tickets for the concert have all been distributed. 大学毕业后, 他就分到外交部工作。 Dàxué bìyè hòu, tājiù fēn dào Wàijiāobù gōngzuò. After his graduation from college, he was assigned to work at the Foreign Ministry. 3 distinguish; differentiate 是非不分 shìfēibùfēn make no distinction between right and wrong 现在还分不出个胜负来。 Xiànzài hái fēn bù chū ge shèng-fù lái. It’s still quite impossible to tell who’ll win. 这对双胞胎长得一模一样, 简直分不出谁是谁。 Zhè duì shuāngbāotāi zhǎng de yīmúyīyàng, jiǎnzhí fēn bù chū shuí shì shuí. The twins look so much alike that you can hardly tell them apart. 
adjective branch (of an organization) 新华社上海分社 Xīnhuáshè Shànghǎi fēnshè the Shanghai Branch of the Xinhua News Agency 
measure word 1 fraction 约分 yuēfēn reduction of a fraction 2 [in spoken forms of fractions and percentages] 三分之一 sānfēn zhīyī one-third 十分之七 shífēn zhī qī seven-tenths 百分之四 bǎifēn zhī sì four per cent 3 one tenth (of certain units of the metric system) 4 fen (of the traditional system of weights and measures) a a traditional unit of length, equal to 0.01 chi (市尺), and equivalent to 0.333 centimetre or 0.131 inch b a traditional unit of weight, equal to 0.001 jin (市斤), and equivalent to 0.5 gram or 0.175 ounce c a traditional unit of area, equal to 0.1 mu (市亩) and equivalent to 0.667 acre or 79.73 square yards d a unit of weight equal to 0.1 qian (钱) or 0.01 liang (两) 5 fen (equal to one hundredth of a yuan (元)) 六元三角五分 liù yuán sānjiǎo wǔfēn 6.35 yuan 6 minute (equal to one sixtieth of an hour) 7 minute (equal to one sixtieth of a degree of angle or arc) 成 36 度 30分角 chéng 36 dù 30fēn jiǎo form an angle of 36 degrees 30 minutes (36°30′) 东经 129 度 15分 dōngjīng 129 dù 15 fēn 129 degrees 15 minutes (129°15′) east longitude 8 a unit of interest rate a 1% monthly interest 月利一分二厘. yuèlì yī fēn èr lí 1.2% monthly interest b 10% annual interest 年利一分二厘. niánlì yī fēn èr lí 12% annual interest 9 point; mark 六十分为及格。 Liùshí fēnwéi jígé. Sixty is the passing mark. 甲队罚球连得二分。 Jiǎ duì fáqiú lián de èrfēn. Team A scored two successive points by free throws. 他今天考试得了一百分。 Tā jīntiān kǎoshì déle yībǎi fēn. He got full marks in today’s exam. 10 [for nonphysical things] one-tenth 七分成绩, 三分错误 Qī fēn chéngjì, sānfēn cuòwù 70 per cent achievements, 30 per cent mistakes 他已经有三分醉了。 Tā yǐjing yǒu sānfēn zuì le. He’s a bit tipsy already. 我的牙痛好了几分。 Wǒ de yátòng hǎo le jǐ fēn. My toothache has been partly relieved. 这消息使我多了一分希望。 Zhè xiāoxi shǐ wǒ duō le yī fēn xīwàng. The news raised my hopes a little.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="20944128"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">中午</headword><headword charset="tc">中午</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zhong1wu3</pron><defn>noun noon; midday</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="36386816"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">菜</headword><headword charset="tc">菜</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">cai4</pron><defn>noun 1 vegetable; greens 种菜 zhòngcài grow vegetables 2 (non-staple) food 上街买菜 shàngjiē mǎi cài go to the market to buy food 3 dish; course 川菜 Chuāncài Sichuan dishes; Sichuan cuisine 做菜 zuòcài prepare the dishes; do the cooking 一道菜 yī dào cài a course 做四道菜 zuò sì dào cài prepare a four-course meal 地方风味菜 dìfang fēngwèi cài local cuisine 4 (edible) wild herbs 吃糠咽菜 chī kāng yàn cài barely keep alive on chaff and wild herbs 5 oil seed rape; rape</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="18104576"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">下午</headword><headword charset="tc">下午</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xia4wu3</pron><defn>noun afternoon (opp. 上午) 下午见！ Xiàwǔ jiàn! See you this afternoon! 下午有场电影。 Xiàwǔ yǒu chǎng diànyǐng. There’s a movie this afternoon.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="32837888"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">跑步</headword><headword charset="tc">跑步</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">pao3//bu4</pron><defn>verb 1 run; march at the double 跑步走！ Pǎobù zǒu! [word of command] At the double, quick march! 跑步前进！ Pǎobù qiánjìn! [word of command] Double time! 2 (a form of physical exercise) jog</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27643904"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">写</headword><headword charset="tc">寫</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xie3</pron><defn>verb 1 write 写封信 xiě fēng xìn write a letter 写副对联 Xiě fù duìlián write a couplet 写得一手好字 xiě de yī shǒu hǎo zì have good handwriting; write a good hand 我喜欢写钢笔字, 不喜欢写毛笔字。 Wǒ xǐhuan xiě gāngbǐ zì, bù xǐhuan xiě máobǐ zì. I like to write with a pen and not with a writing-brush. 这支笔不好写。 Zhè zhī bǐ bù hǎo xiě. This pen doesn’t write well. 2 compose; write (as an author, reporter, etc.) 写诗 xiěshī compose a poem 写论文 xiě lùnwén write a paper (or thesis) 写日记 xiě rìjì make an entry in one’s diary; keep a diary 写小说 Xiě xiǎoshuō write a novel 文章写成了吗？ Wénzhāng xiě chéng le ma？ Have you finished writing the article? 3 describe; depict 写人物的心理活动 xiě rénwù de xīnlǐ huódòng depict the characters’ mental activities 这个人物叫他写活了。 Zhège rénwù jiào tā xiě huó le. His portrayal of the character is vivid and true to life. 4 paint; draw See 33305344写生xie3sheng1写生</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33304320"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">电子邮件</headword><headword charset="tc">電子郵件</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">dian4zi3you2jian4</pron><defn>email</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="42426546"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">唱歌</headword><headword charset="tc">唱歌</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">chang4//ge1</pron><defn>verb sing (a song) 她很会唱歌。 Tā hěn huì chànggē. She is a good singer.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="18429952"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">奶奶</headword><headword charset="tc">奶奶</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">nai3nai5</pron><defn>noun 1 colloquial (paternal) grandmother; grandma 2 colloquial respectful form of address for an old woman 3 dialect young mistress of the house</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27141376"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">到</headword><headword charset="tc">到</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">dao4</pron><defn>verb 1 arrive; reach 到！ Dào! [answer to roll call] Here! 到了多少人？ Dào le duōshao rén？ How many people were present? 火车到站了。 Huǒchē dào zhàn le. The train has arrived at the station. 时间到了。 Shíjiān dào le. Time’s up. 2 go to; leave for 到兰州去 Dào Lánzhōu qù go to Lanzhou 3 [as a verb complement to show the result of an action] 办得到 bàndedào can be done 说到做到 shuōdàozuòdào be as good as one’s word 想不到你来了。 Xiǎng bù dào nǐ lái le. I didn’t expect you would come. 
preposition up until; up to 到目前为止 dào mùqián wéizhǐ up to the present; until now; so far 工作到深夜 Gōngzuò dào shēnyè work late into the night 从星期三到星期五 cóng Xīngqīsān dào Xīngqīwǔ from Wednesday to Friday 温度降到零下二十度。 Wēndù jiàng dào língxià èrshí dù. The temperature dropped to minus 20 degrees centigrade. 
adjective thoughtful; considerate 不到之处请原谅。 Bù dào zhī chù qǐng yuánliàng. Please excuse me if I have been inconsiderate in any way.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19719424"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">运动</headword><headword charset="tc">運動</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">yun4dong4</pron><defn>verb 1 motion; movement 运动的形式 yùndòng de xíngshì form of motion 运动中的物质 yùndòng zhòngdì wùzhì matter in motion 行星的运动 xíngxīng de yùndòng movement of a planet 运动是物质的存在方式。 Yùndòng shì wùzhì de cúnzài fāngshì. Motion is the mode of existence of matter. 乘敌运动之际, 打击敌人。 Chéng dí yùndòng zhījì, dǎjī dírén. Attack the enemy while he is on the move. 2 sports; athletics; exercise 室外运动 Shìwài yùndòng outdoor sports 散步也是一种运动。 Sànbù yě shì yī zhǒng yùndòng. Walking is also a form of exercise. 游泳是我喜爱的运动。 Yóuyǒng shì wǒ xǐ&apos;ài de yùndòng. Swimming is my favourite sport. 
noun (political or cultural) movement; campaign; drive 竞选运动 Jìngxuǎn yùndòng election campaign 技术革新运动 jìshù géxīn yùndòng drive for technological innovation</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35531008"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">晚饭</headword><headword charset="tc">晚飯</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">wan3fan4</pron><defn>noun supper; dinner</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="32066560"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">音乐</headword><headword charset="tc">音樂</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">yin1yue4</pron><defn>noun music 古典音乐 gǔdiǎnyīnyuè classical music 流行音乐 liúxíngyīnyuè popular (or pop) music 你喜欢什么音乐？ Nǐ xǐhuan shénme yīnyuè？ What kind of music do you like?</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34712832"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">听</headword><headword charset="tc">聽</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ting1</pron><defn>verb 1 listen; hear 听广播 Tīng guǎngbō listen to the radio 听, 好像有人敲门。 tīng, hǎoxiàng yǒurén qiāo mén. Listen, it sounds like someone knocking at the door. 听声音不像他。 Tīng shēngyīn bù xiàng tā. The voice didn’t sound like him. 请听我说完。 Qǐng tīng wǒ shuō wán. Please hear me out. 请听一下电话。 Qǐng tīng yī xià diànhuà. Answer the phone, please. 厂长要你听电话。 Chǎngzhǎng yào nǐ tīng diànhuà. The director wants you on the phone. 打开收音机听听新闻。 Dǎkāi shōuyīnjī tīngtīng xīnwén. Turn on the radio and listen to the news. 到群众中走一走, 听听他们的意见。 Dào qúnzhòng zhōng zǒu yī zǒu, tīngtīng tāmen de yìjian. Go among the people and hear what they have to say. 你听着, 我在给你讲呢！ Nǐ tīng zhe, wǒ zài gěi nǐ jiǎng ne! Listen to me, I’m talking to you! 他的话听起来不诚恳。 Tā de huà tīng qǐlai bù chéngkěn. He did not sound sincere. or His words rang hollow. 他的四川口音我听不出来。 Tā de Sìchuān kǒuyin wǒ tīng bù chūlai. I can’t detect his Sichuan accent. 他唆了半天, 我实在听不下去了。 Tā suō le bàntiān, wǒ shízài tīng bùxià qùle. He rambled on for hours and I could stand it no longer. 我没听过这样好的音乐。 Wǒ méi tīng guò zhèyàng hǎo de yīnyuè. I’ve never heard such beautiful music before. 这一句我没听清。 Zhè yī jù wǒ méi tīng qīng. I didn’t quite catch that sentence. 这些话听起来倒也有些道理。 Zhèxiē huà tīng qǐlai dào yě yǒuxiē dàoli. That actually sounds quite reasonable. 2 heed; obey; listen to 对批评听不进去 Duì pīpíng tīng bù jìnqu turn a deaf ear to criticism 听我的没错儿。 Tīng wǒ de méicuòr. Do as I say and you won’t go wrong. 我劝他别去, 他不听。 Wǒ quàn tā bié qù, tā bù tīng. I advised him not to go, but he wouldn’t listen. 家里的事我都听她的。 Jiālǐ de shì wǒ dōu tīng tā de. When it comes to household matters, I listen to her. 工地上一切都听他指挥。 Gōngdì shàng yīqiè dōu tīng tā zhǐhuī. Everything on the construction site is under his command. 老了, 胳膊腿儿不听使唤了。 Lǎo le, gēbo tuǐr bù tīng shǐhuan le. I’m getting old. My limbs don’t obey me anymore 她要听了我的话, 哪会有今天。 Tā yào tīng le wǒ dehuà, nǎ huì yǒu jīntiān. If she’d heeded me, things would be different today. 3 administer; manage 听政 tīngzhèng conduct a hearing; hold count 
verb allow; let 听由老板摆布 tīng yóu lǎobǎn bǎibu be at the mercy of the boss 
measure word transliteration tin; can 六听啤酒 liù tīng píjiǔ six cans of beer 三听咖啡 Sān tīng kāfēi three tins of coffee</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="31531264"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">音乐会</headword><headword charset="tc">音樂會</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">yin1yue4hui4</pron><defn>concert</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34713344"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">生日卡</headword><headword charset="tc">生日卡</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">sheng1 ri4 ka3</pron><defn> 生 life, living, lifetime; birthRadical: 生; Stroke count: 5; HSK level: 1; General Standard: #263; Frequency rank: 34 日 sun; day; daytimeRadical: 日; Stroke count: 4; HSK level: 2; General Standard: #112; Frequency rank: 101 卡 card, punch card; calorieRadical: 卜; Stroke count: 5; HSK level: 3; General Standard: #226; Frequency rank: 717</defn></entry><dictref dictcreator="19125399" dictid="-1278474637" entryid="57"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">博客</headword><headword charset="tc">博客</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">bo2ke4</pron><defn>noun internet blog; weblog</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="42455730"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">售货员</headword><headword charset="tc">售貨員</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shou4huo4yuan2</pron><defn>noun salesperson; shop assistant; salesclerk 男售货员 Nán shòuhuòyuán salesman 女售货员 nǚshòuhuòyuán saleswoman; salesgirl; shopgirl</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30404864"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">买</headword><headword charset="tc">買</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">mai3</pron><defn>verb 1 buy; purchase 买东西 Mǎi dōngxi buy things; go shopping 太贵了, 买不起。 Tài guì le, mǎi bù qǐ. It’s too expensive. I can’t afford it. 2 buy off; bribe See 66410979买官mai3guan1买官 
noun (Mǎi) a surname</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26471424"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">衣服</headword><headword charset="tc">衣服</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">yi1fu5</pron><defn>noun clothing; clothes 衣服里子 yīfu lǐzi lining 外边冷, 多穿些衣服。 Wàibian lěng, duō chuān xiē yīfu. It’s cold outside. Put on more clothes.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34446848"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">条</headword><headword charset="tc">條</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">tiao2</pron><defn>noun 1 twig 这棵葡萄长出了许多新条。 Zhè kē pútao zhǎng chū le xǔduō xīn tiáo. This grapevine has grown many new twigs. 2 long narrow piece; strip; slip 把一块布撕成条 Bǎ yī kuài bù sī chéng tiáo tear a piece of cloth into strips 3 brief informal note 经理不在, 请你给他留个条吧。 Jīnglǐ bù zài, qǐng nǐ gěi tā liú ge tiáo ba. The manager is out. Will you leave a note for him, please? 4 item; article 这项条约的正文共八条。 Zhè xiàng tiáoyuē de zhèngwén gòng bā tiáo. The main body of the treaty consists of eight articles. 5 order 有条不紊 yǒutiáobùwěn in an orderly way 
measure word 1 [for long, or narrow, or thin objects] 两条鱼 Liǎng tiáo yú two fish 三条船 sān tiáo chuán three ships 一条床单 Yī tiáo chuángdān a bed sheet 一条大街 yī tiáo dàjiē an avenue 一条肥皂 yī tiáo féizào a bar of soap 一条裤子 yī tiáo kùzi a pair of trousers 一条香烟 yī tiáo xiāngyān a carton of cigarettes 2 [for certain nouns] 两条新闻 liǎng tiáo xīnwén two pieces (or items) of news 三条人命 sān tiáo rénmìng three human lives 四条建议 sì tiáo jiànyì four proposals 一条好汉 yī tiáo hǎohàn a brave man 一条妙计 yī tiáo miàojì a brilliant scheme 一条好嗓子 yī tiáo hǎo sǎngzi a good voice</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="31447552"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">裙子</headword><headword charset="tc">裙子</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">qun2zi5</pron><defn>noun skirt</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="28888832"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">来</headword><headword charset="tc">來</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">lai2</pron><defn>verb 1 come (to); arrive 来得不巧 Láide bùqiǎo come at an unsuitable time (or moment) 来得正好 láide zhènghǎo come in good time; come just at the right time 就来！ jiù lái! I’m coming. 快来！ Kuài lái! Come along! 来客人了。 Lái kèren le. We have a guest. 客人来了。 Kèren lái le. The guests are here. 他今天来过两次。 Tā jīntiān lái guò liǎng cì. He came twice today. 他已经来了。 Tā yǐjinglái le. He has already come. 她明天来北京。 Tā míngtiān lái Běijīng. She is coming to Beijing tomorrow. 有空来玩。 Yǒukòng lái wán. Come round when you have time. 远处来了一条小船。 Yuǎnchù lái le yī tiáo xiǎochuán. A small boat came into view in the distance. 2 cause to come; happen; crop up; take place 问题来了。 Wèntí lái le. A problem has come up. 这事儿怎么来的？ Zhè shìr zěnme lái de？ How did it come about? 3 obtain; get 这差事来得不容易。 Zhè chāishilái de bù róngyì. This job is hard to come by. 4 [as a substitute for some other verb] 来份糖醋鱼。 lái fèn tángcùyú. A sweet-and-sour fish, please. 你来块糖。 Nǐ lái kuài táng. Have some candy. 再来一个！ Zàilái yī ge! [call for another performance] Encore! 慢慢儿来, 别忙。 Mànmànr lái, bié máng. Take it easy. No hurry. 我累了, 你来吧。 Wǒ lèi le, nǐ lái ba. I’m tired. Why don’t you take over (or carry on). 咱们来一盘棋。 Zánmenlái yī pán qí. Let’s have a game of chess. 你歇歇, 让我来吧。 Nǐ xiēxie, ràng wǒ lái ba. You take a rest. Let me do it. 我自己来吧, 别客气。 Wǒ zìjǐ lái ba, bié kèqi. Please don’t bother. I’ll do it myself. 我们打篮球, 你来不来？ Wǒmen dǎ lánqiú, nǐ lái bù lái？ We’re going to play basketball. Will you join in? 5 [with 得 or 不, indicating possibility or impossibility, capability or incapability] 上海话我说不来。 Shànghǎi huà wǒ shuō bù lái. I don’t speak Shanghai dialect. 我吃不来四川菜。 Wǒ chī bù lái Sìchuān cài. I can’t get used to Sichuan cuisine. 西餐我吃得来。 Xīcān wǒ chī de lái. Western food suits me all right. 这道题我做不来。 Zhè dào tí wǒ zuò bù lái. I can’t do this problem. 这个歌我唱得来。 Zhège gē wǒ chàng de lái. I can sing this song. 6 [before a verb, indicating an intended or suggested action] 你来试试。 Nǐ lái shìshi. Have a try. 我来说两句。 Wǒ láishuō liǎng jù. Let me say a few words. 大家来想办法。 Dàjiā lái xiǎng bànfǎ. Let’s think of a way (to solve the problem). or Let’s put our heads together and see how to do it. 7 [after a verb or verbal expression] come in order to 他回家探亲来了。 Tā huíjiā tànqīn lái le. He’s come home to see his parents. 我们道喜来了。 Wǒmen dàoxǐ lái le. We’ve come to congratulate you (or offer our congratulations). 8 [between two verbs or verbal expressions to indicate the purpose of the former] in order to 想办法来解决问题 Xiǎng bànfǎ lái jiějué wèntí think of a way to solve the problem 你又能用什么理由来说服他呢？ Nǐ yòu néng yòng shénme lǐyóu lái shuōfú tā ne？ And what arguments can you use to convince him? 9 (of electricity, tap water, gas, etc.) be on again 来电了。 lái diàn le. The power is on again. 来水了。 lái shuǐ le. There’s running water again. 
auxiliary 1 colloquial [at the end of a sentence to indicate what has happened in the past, same as 来着] 你这是何苦来？ Nǐ zhè shì hékǔlái? Why did you do that (and made yourself unhappy)? 2 [after a time expression, indicating a period of time that extends from the past up to the present] ever since 几天来 jǐ tiān lái for the last few days 一年来 yī nián lái during the past year 3 [after a round number or after a numeral plus a measure] approximately; about; around; round 二十来个 èrshí lái ge about 20 四十来岁 sìshí lái suì round 40 (years old) 十来块钱 shí lái kuài qián somewhere over 10 yuan 两米来高 liǎng mǐ lái gāo about two metres high 百十来里地 bǎishí lái lǐ dì a distance of about 100 li 4 [after the numerals 一, 二, and 三, indicating points in an explanation or argument] 我不要, 一来我不喜欢,  二来我也没钱。 Wǒ bùyào, yī lái wǒ bù xǐhuan, èr lái wǒ yě méiqián. I don’t want it. In the first place, I don’t like it; in the second place, I don’t have the money. 
adjective future; coming; next 来月 láiyuè coming month 
noun (Lái) a surname 
auxiliary [as a syllable filler in folk ballads] 正月里来是新春。 Zhēngyuè lǐ lái shì xīnchūn. The first month is the beginning of spring. 你敲锣来我打鼓。 Nǐ qiāoluó lái wǒ dǎgǔ. You beat the gong while I play the drum.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="25308160"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">这边</headword><headword charset="tc">這邊</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zhe4bian1</pron><defn>pronoun this side; here 到这边来。 Dào zhèbiān lái. Come over here. 正义在我们这边。 Zhèngyì zài wǒmen zhè biān. Justice is on our side. 踏遍青山人未老, 风景这边独好。(毛泽东) Tà biàn qīngshān rén wèi lǎo, fēngjǐng zhèbiān dú hǎo. (Máo Zédōng) Crossing these blue hills adds nothing to one’s years, | The landscape here is beyond compare.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35938560"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">红</headword><headword charset="tc">紅</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hong2</pron><defn>noun 1 red cloth, bunting, etc. used on festive occasions 披红 pīhóng drape a band of red silk over one’s shoulders as a token of honour 2 bonus; dividend 分红 fēnhóng share profits; draw dividends 
adjective 1 red 红墙绿瓦 hóng qiáng lǜ wǎ a red ochre wall with green tiles 脸上红一阵白一阵 Liǎnshàng hóng yīzhèn bái yīzhèn flush and turn pale by turns 他的眼睛都熬红了。 Tā de yǎnjing dōu áo hóng le. His eyes become bloodshot from lack of sleep. 2 revolutionary; red 红五月 Hóngwǔyuè the red month of May 3 successful; popular 他是个很红的歌星。 Tā shì ge hěn hóng de gēxīng. He’s a very popular singer.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22652416"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">蓝色</headword><headword charset="tc">藍色</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">lan2se4</pron><defn>noun blue 蓝色痣 lánsè zhì blue nevus</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="65126115"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">黑色</headword><headword charset="tc">黑色</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hei1se4</pron><defn>noun black (colour) 
adjective shady; illegal</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22592256"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">好看</headword><headword charset="tc">好看</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hao3kan4</pron><defn>adjective 1 good-looking; nice 你戴那顶帽子很好看。 Nǐ dài nà dǐng màozi hěn hǎokàn. That hat looks nice on you. 这花布做裙子一定很好看。 Zhè huābù zuò qúnzi yīdìng hěn hǎokàn. This piece of cotton print would surely make a very beautiful skirt. 2 interesting 这本小说很好看。 Zhè běn xiǎoshuō hěn hǎokàn. This novel is very interesting. 3 honoured; proud 儿子立了功, 我这做娘的脸上也好看。 Érzi lì le gōng, wǒ zhè zuò niáng de liǎnshàng yě hǎokàn. My son has won distinction; as his mother, I share the honour. 4 embarrassing 等着吧, 有他的好看。 Děngzhe ba, yǒu tā de hǎokàn. You can be sure he’ll soon find himself on the spot. 让我上台表演, 这不是要我的好看吗？ Ràng wǒ shàngtái biǎoyǎn, zhè bù shì yào wǒ de hǎokàn ma？ Me, on the stage? Do you want me to make a fool of myself?</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22437120"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">试</headword><headword charset="tc">試</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shi4</pron><defn>verb try; test 试产 shìchǎn trial production 试穿 shìchuān try on (a garment, shoes, etc.) 试一试 shìyīshì have a try 试试绳子结实不结实 shìshì shéngzi jiēshi bù jiēshi test the strength of a rope 
noun examination; test 口试 kǒushì oral examination (or test)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30198784"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">不错</headword><headword charset="tc">不錯</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">bu4cuo4</pron><defn>adjective 1 correct; right 这个答案一点儿不错。 Zhège dá&apos;àn yīdiǎnr bùcuò. This answer is perfectly correct. 2 colloquial not bad; pretty good 录音不错。 lùyīn bùcuò The recording is pretty good. 这个主意不错。 Zhège zhǔyi bùcuò. This idea is not bad. 庄稼长得挺不错。 Zhuāngjia zhǎng de tǐng bùcuò. The crops are doing well. 3 [used alone to express agreement] yes 不错, 他是这么说的。 Bùcuò, tā shì zhème shuō de. Yes, that’s what he said.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="17895168"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">钱</headword><headword charset="tc">錢</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">qian2</pron><defn>noun 1 copper coin; cash 铜钱 tóngqián copper cash 2 money; wealth 有钱有势 yǒuqiányǒushì be wealthy and powerful 这个多少钱？ Zhège duōshao qián？ How much is this? 3 fund; sum 买房的钱 mǎi fáng deqián the wherewithal to buy a flat 这笔钱是专为保健事业用的。 Zhè bǐ qián shì zhuān wèi bǎojiàn shìyè yòng de. This fund is earmarked for public health services. 4 copper coin-shaped object See 36236288纸钱zhi3qian2纸钱;35217152榆钱儿yu2qian2r0榆钱儿 5 (Qián) a surname 
measure word qian (a traditional unit of weight, equal to 0.01 jin (市斤), and equivalent to 5 grams or 0.176 ounce)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="28357888"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">百</headword><headword charset="tc">百</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">bai3</pron><defn>number hundred 百花盛开 Bǎihuā shèngkāi a hundred flowers in bloom; luxuriant 几百本书 jǐ bǎi běn shū several hundred books 数以百计的听众 shùyǐbǎijì de tīngzhòng hundreds of listeners 
adjective numerous; all kinds of 百忙之中 bǎi máng zhīzhōng in the midst of pressing affairs; despite many claims on one’s time 百吃不厌 bǎi chī bù yàn never tire of eating sth.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="17053952"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">块</headword><headword charset="tc">塊</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">kuai4</pron><defn>noun 1 piece; lump; chunk 块煤 kuàiméi lump coal 糖块儿 Táng kuàir hard candy; fruit drops; lumps of sugar 把肉切成块儿 bǎ ròu qiē chéng kuàir cut the meat into cubes 2 computing block 块复制 kuài fùzhì block copy 数据块 shù jù kuài data block 
measure word 1 piece; lump 两块肥皂 liǎng kuài féizào two cakes of soap 一块面包 yī kuài miànbāo a piece (or hunk) of bread 一块手表 yī kuài shǒubiǎo a wrist watch 一块桌布 yī kuài zhuōbù a table cloth 2 colloquial [for gold or silver dollars, Renminbi, and certain paper money] 三块钱 sān kuài qián three yuan 块儿八毛 kuàirbāmáo one yuan or slightly less 两块银洋 liǎng kuài yínyáng two silver dollars 一千块港币 yīqiān kuài Gǎngbì 1, 000 1,000 Hong Kong dollars</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="25161472"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">便宜</headword><headword charset="tc">便宜</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">pian2yi5</pron><defn>noun VARIANT OF 22431744好处hao3chu5好处 2 gain; profit See 31242496讨便宜tao3pian2yi5讨便宜;35779328占便宜zhan4pian2yi5占便宜 
verb let sb. off lightly; give sb. unmerited advantage 这次便宜了他。 Zhècì piányi le tā. This time we let him off lightly. 
adjective cheap 便宜货 piányihuò bargain 价钱相当便宜。 Jiàqian xiāngdāng piányi. It’s a real bargain. or It’s quite cheap.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27829504"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">一点儿</headword><headword charset="tc">一點兒</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">yi1dian3r5</pron><defn>noun 1 a bit; a little 有一点累 Yǒu yīdiǎn lèi feel a bit tired 这事我知道一点。 zhè shì wǒ zhīdaoyīdiǎn. I know a little (or something) about it. 还有一点希望。 Hái yǒu yīdiǎn xīwàng. There is still a gleam of hope. 2 [after 这么 or 那么, or with a negative expression] the least bit 一点也不累 yīdiǎn yě bù lèi not feel the least bit tired 一点都不知道 yīdiǎn dōu bùzhīdào have not the faintest idea 一点用处也没有 yīdiǎn yòngchu yě méiyǒu utterly useless</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34355200"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">价钱</headword><headword charset="tc">價錢</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jia4qian5</pron><defn>noun price 价钱公道 jiàqian gōngdào fair (or decent, reasonable) price 讲价钱 jiǎng jiàqian haggle over the price; bargain 价钱在涨。 Jiàqian zài zhǎng. The prices are rising. 西红柿什么价钱？ Xīhóngshì shénme jiàqian？ How much are the tomatoes? 这张书桌你是什么价钱买的？ Zhè zhāng shūzhuō nǐ shì shénme jiàqian mǎi de？ What price did you pay for this desk?</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="23696896"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">贵</headword><headword charset="tc">貴</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">gui4</pron><defn>adjective 1 expensive; costly; dear (opp. 贱) 我买贵了。 Wǒ mǎi guì le. I paid too much for it. 丝绸比棉布贵。 Sīchóu bǐ miánbù guì. Silk is more expensive than cotton. 2 highly valued; valuable 兵贵精, 不贵多。 Bīng guì jīng, bù guì duō. Troops are valued for their quality, not their number. 3 of high rank; noble (opp. 贱) 贵妇人 guìfùrén a noble lady 4 courteous your 贵国 guìguó your (honourable) country 喜得贵子 xǐ de guì zǐ (gratulate you on) having just got your son 请问(您)贵姓？ qǐngwèn guì xìng? May I ask your name? or What’s your name, please? 
noun (Guì) abbreviation Guizhou Province</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22129152"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">吧</headword><headword charset="tc">吧</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ba5</pron><defn>auxiliary 1 [indicating a suggestion, request or mild command] 咱们走吧。 Zánmen zǒu ba. Let’s go. 你好好儿想想吧！ Nǐ hǎohāor xiǎngxiang ba! Just think it over. 2 [indicating consent or approval] 明天就明天吧。 Míngtiān jiù míngtiān ba. All right, let’s make it tomorrow. 好吧, 就这么办吧！ Hǎo ba, jiù zhème bàn ba! O.K., that’s what we’ll do. 3 [in a leading question which asks for confirmation of a supposition] 他会来吧？ Tā huì lái ba？ He’ll come, won’t he? 你是中国人吧？ Nǐ shì Zhōngguó rén ba？ You are Chinese, I suppose (or I take it)? 4 [indicating some doubt in the speaker&apos;s mind] 他们走了吧。 Tāmen zǒu le ba. I suppose they’ve left. 他好像是这么说的吧。 Tā hǎoxiàng shì zhème shuō de ba. That seems to be what he said. 5 [marking a pause after suppositions as alternatives] 去吧, 不好；不去吧, 也不好。 qù ba, bù hǎo; bù qù ba, yě bù hǎo. If I go, it’s no good; if I don’t, it’s no good either.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="17006080"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">书店</headword><headword charset="tc">書店</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shu1dian4</pron><defn>noun bookshop; bookstore; bookseller&apos;s 新华书店 Xīnhuá Shūdiàn Xinhua Bookstore</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30415104"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">服装</headword><headword charset="tc">服裝</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">fu2zhuang1</pron><defn>noun dress; clothing; costume 服装整齐 fúzhuāng zhěngqí be neatly dressed 民族服装 mínzú fúzhuāng national or ethnic costume</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="21176320"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">市场</headword><headword charset="tc">市場</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shi4chang3</pron><defn>noun 1 marketplace; market; bazaar 市场疲软 shìchǎng píruǎn sluggish market; slow market 市场竞争日益加剧 shìchǎng jìngzhēng rìyì jiājù increasing market competition 国内外市场 guónèiwài shìchǎng domestic and foreign markets 买方市场 mǎifāng shìchǎng buyer’s market 卖方市场 màifāng shìchǎng seller’s market 市场繁荣。 Shìchǎng fánróng. The market is brisk. 市场混乱。 Shìchǎng hùnluàn. The market is in a chaotic state. 市场供应充足。 Shìchǎng gōngyìng chōngzú. There is an ample supply of commodities. or Markets are well-stocked. 2 figurative sphere of influence 这种理论在群众中的市场越来越小。 zhèzhǒng lǐlùn zài qúnzhòng zhòngdì shìchǎng yuèláiyuè xiǎo. This theory is losing popular support.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30165504"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">裤子</headword><headword charset="tc">褲子</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ku4zi5</pron><defn>noun trousers; pants; breeches; pantaloon 裤子背带 kùzi bēidài braces; suspenders 一条裤子 yī tiáo kùzi a pair of trousers</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="25136128"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">Ｔ恤</headword><headword charset="tc">Ｔ恤</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">T5 xu4</pron><defn>T-shirt</defn></entry><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">白色</headword><headword charset="tc">白色</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">bai2se4</pron><defn>noun 1 white (colour) 2 White (as a symbol of political reaction) 白色据点 Báisè jùdiǎn White stronghold; stronghold of reactionaries 白色政权 báisè zhèngquán White regime; reactionary government (referring mainly to the Kuomintang government in the 1920’s and 1930’s) 
noun (white) plastic</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="17038336"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">有名</headword><headword charset="tc">有名</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">you3//ming2</pron><defn>adjective well-known; famous; celebrated 有名的产品 yǒumíng de chǎnpǐn brand name product 有名的地方 yǒumíng de dìfang well-known place 有名的科学家 yǒumíng de kēxuéjiā celebrated scientist 特别有名的跳水运动员 tèbié yǒumíng de tiàoshuǐ yùndòngyuán tremendously famous diver 他是个有名的调皮鬼。 tā shì ge yǒumíng de tiáopíguǐ. He held the reputation of being naughty.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35085056"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">购物中心</headword><headword charset="tc">購物中心</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">gou4wu4zhong1xin1</pron><defn>shopping centre (or mall)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="69436720"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">这里</headword><headword charset="tc">這裡</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zhe4li3</pron><defn>pronoun here 我们这里一年种两季稻子。 Wǒmen zhèlǐ yī nián zhòng liǎng jì dàozi. We grow two crops of rice a year here.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35940608"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">双</headword><headword charset="tc">雙</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shuang1</pron><defn>adjective 1 two; twin; both; dual (opp. 单) 双频手机 shuāng pín shǒujī dual-band mobile phone 双排扣西服 shuāng pái kòu xīfú double-breasted suit 双发动机飞机 shuāng fādòngjī fēijī twin-engined plane 粮食, 棉花双丰收 liángshi, miánhuashuāng fēngshōu bumper harvests of both grain and cotton 2 even (opp. 单) See 30585088双数shuang1shu4双数 3 double; twofold 双份 shuāngfèn double the amount; twice as much 
measure word [for shoes, socks, chopsticks, etc.] pair 一双鞋 yī shuāng xié a pair of shoes 一双袜子 yī shuāng wàzi a pair of socks</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30571264"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">鞋</headword><headword charset="tc">鞋</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xie2</pron><defn>noun shoes 鞋厂 xiéchǎng shoe factory 鞋店 xiédiàn shoe shop 鞋盒 xiéhé shoe box</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33299968"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">件</headword><headword charset="tc">件</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jian4</pron><defn>noun 1 single item 工件 gōngjiàn workpiece 零件 língjiàn part 2 letter; correspondence; paper; document 来件 láijiàn mail received 密件 mìjiàn confidential letter 
measure word 1 [for matters in general] 大件 dàjiàn big piece; bulky piece 一件事 Yī jiàn shì a matter; a thing 一件工作 yī jiàn gōngzuò a piece of work; a job 2 [for clothing, furniture, luggage, etc.] 一件大衣 yī jiàn dàyī an overcoat 一件家具 yī jiàn jiāju a piece of furniture 三件行李 sān jiàn xíngli three pieces of luggage 一件一件地点查 Yī jiàn yī jiàn dìdiǎn chá check piece by piece</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="23829248"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">大衣</headword><headword charset="tc">大衣</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">da4yi1</pron><defn>noun overcoat; topcoat</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19496704"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">每</headword><headword charset="tc">每</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">mei3</pron><defn>pronoun every; each; per 每次 měicì each time 每小时 měi xiǎoshí per hour 每星期五 měi xīngqī wǔ every Friday 每两周开一次会 měi liǎng zhōu kāi yī cì huì hold a meeting every other week 每人一张票 měirén yī zhāng piào a ticket for each person 每四小时服一次 měi sì xiǎoshí fú yī cì to be taken once every four hours 
adverb 1 on each occasion; each time; per 每逢春节, 我都要去看老师。 Měiféng Chūnjié, wǒ dōu yào qù kàn lǎoshī. I always go to see my teachers during the Spring Festival. 2 literary often 春秋佳日, 每作郊游。 Chūnqiū jiā rì, měi zuò jiāoyóu. On fine spring and autumn days, we often go for outings in the country.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26646784"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">很多</headword><headword charset="tc">很多</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hen3duo1</pron><defn>Sehr viele</defn></entry><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">超市</headword><headword charset="tc">超市</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">chao1shi4</pron><defn>noun abbreviation colloquial = 18451712超级市场chao1ji2shi4chang3超级市场 supermarket</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="42426290"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">东西</headword><headword charset="tc">東西</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">dong1xi5</pron><defn>noun 1 thing 她买东西去了。 Tā mǎi dōngxi qù le. She’s out shopping. or She’s gone shopping. 他收拾好东西就走了。 Tā shōushi hǎo dōngxi jiù zǒu le. He packed his things and left. 一成不变的东西是没有的。 Yīchéngbùbiàn de dōngxi shì méiyǒu de. Nothing is immutable. 分析形势要注意全局性的东西。 Fēnxi xíngshì yào zhùyì quánjú xìng de dōngxi. When analysing a situation, pay attention to things that affect it as a whole. 2 [referring to a person or animal] thing; creature 这小东西真可爱。 Zhè xiǎo dōngxi zhēn kě&apos;ài. What a sweet little thing! 真不是东西！ Zhēn bù shì dōngxi! What a despicable creature!</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="20187136"/><catassign category="Lektion8"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">左右</headword><headword charset="tc">左右</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zuo3you4</pron><defn>noun 1 left and right sides 左右摇摆 zuǒ-yòu yáobǎi vacillating; unsteady; hesitant 主席台左右, 红旗迎风飘扬。 Zhǔxítái zuǒyòu, hóngqí yíngfēng piāoyáng. Red flags are fluttering on both sides of the rostrum. 2 [after a numeral] about; or so 八点钟左右 bā diǎn zhōng zuǒyòu around eight o&apos;clock 一个月左右 yī ge yuè zuǒyòu a month or so 身高一米七左右 Shēngāo yī mǐ qī zuǒyòu be about 1.70 metres in height 价值十元左右。 Jiàzhí shí yuán zuǒyòu. It&apos;s worth about 10 yuan. 3 those in close attendance; retinue 屏退左右 Píng tuì zuǒyòu order one&apos;s attendants to clear out 
verb master; control; influence 左右局势 zuǒyòu júshì be master of the situation; in control 为人所左右 wéi rén suǒ zuǒyòu controlled by another; fall under another’s influence 他这个人不是别人能左右得了的。 Tā zhège rén bù shì biéren néng zuǒyòu déle de. He is not a man to be influenced by others. 
adverb dialect anyway; anyhow; in any case 左右闲没事, 我就陪你走一趟吧。 Zuǒyòu xiánzhe méishì, wǒ jiù péi nǐ zǒu yī tàng ba. Ānyway I’m free now so let me go with you.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="37115648"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">北边</headword><headword charset="tc">北邊</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">bei3bian5</pron><defn>noun 1 north; the northern side 加拿大在美国的北边。 Jiānádà zài Měiguó de běibian. Canada lies north of the United States of America. 2 colloquial VARIANT OF 17341440北方bei3fang1北方2 the northern part of China, esp. the area north of the Huang He River; the North</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="56177379"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">西边</headword><headword charset="tc">西邊</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xi1bian5</pron><defn>noun to the west 西面的窗子 Xīmian de chuāngzi window facing west 电影院西面 diànyǐngyuàn xīmian (to the) west of the cinema</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="42463922"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">东边</headword><headword charset="tc">東邊</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">dong1bian5</pron><defn>noun east; east side; eastern</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="42463666"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">南边</headword><headword charset="tc">南邊</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">nan2bian5</pron><defn>noun 1 south; the southern side 2 colloquial the southern part of the country, esp. the area south of the Yangtze River; the South</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27167744"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">前边</headword><headword charset="tc">前邊</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">qian2bian5</pron><defn>noun 1 above; preceding 前面的一章 qiánmian de yī zhāng the preceding chapter 前面提到的原则 Qiánmian tídào de yuánzé the above-mentioned principle 2 in front; at the head; ahead 在房子前面 zài fángzi qiánmian in front of the house 走在队伍前面 Zǒu zài duìwu qiánmian march at the head of the column  前面有座位。 Qiánmian yǒu zuòwèi. There are seats in the front rows. 前面就是宿营地。 Qiánmian jiùshì sùyíngdì. The campsite is right ahead. 前面来了一个人。 Qiánmian lái le yī ge rén. A man was coming towards us. 科学研究应当走在经济建设的前面。 Kēxué yánjiū yīngdāng zǒuzài jīngjì jiànshè deqiánmian. Scientific research should anticipate economic construction.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="28320768"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">后边</headword><headword charset="tc">後邊</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hou4bian5</pron><defn>noun 1 back; rear 后面儿还有座位。 hòumianr hái yǒu zuòwèi. There are vacant seats at the back. 2 later time; future 这个问题我后面儿还要讲。 zhège wèntí wǒ hòumianr háiyào jiǎng. I’ll come back to this question later.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22720256"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">离</headword><headword charset="tc">離</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">li2</pron><defn>verb 1 leave; part from 离京赴穗 lí jīng fù suì leave Beijing for Guangzhou 远离家乡 yuǎnlí jiāxiāng go far away from home 农民离土不离乡, 发展乡镇企业。 nóngmín lí tǔ bù lí xiāng, fāzhǎn xiāng-zhèn qǐyè. Peasants leave the land but not their home to develop rural enterprises. 2 be at a distance from; be away from 离这里不远 lí zhèlǐ bù yuǎn be not far from here; a little way off 离国庆节只有十天了。 Lí Guóqìngjié zhǐ yǒu shí tiān le. National Day is only ten days away. 3 lack; be short of 他离不了酒。 Tā líbuliǎo jiǔ. He can’t stay away from the bottle. 发展工业离不了钢铁。 Fāzhǎn gōngyè líbuliǎo gāngtiě. Industry cannot develop without steel. 4 deviate from; shift from See 65399267离谱儿li2pu3r5离谱儿 
noun li (one of the Eight Trigrams (八卦) which represents fire ())</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="25563392"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">近</headword><headword charset="tc">近</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jin4</pron><defn>verb approach; approximate; be close to 年近六十 nián jìn liùshí approaching sixty; getting on for sixty 观众近万人。 Guānzhòng jìn wàn rén. There were nearly 10,000 spectators. 
adjective 1 near; close 近百年史 Jìn bǎinián shǐ history of the last hundred years 住得近 Zhù de jìn live nearby 歌声由远而近。 Gēshēng yóu yuǎn ér jìn. The singing came closer and closer. 离国庆节很近了。 Lí Guóqìngjié hěn jìn le. National Day is drawing near. or It’ll soon be National Day. 2 intimate; closely related 两家走得挺近。 Liǎng jiā zǒu de tǐng jìn. The two families are on intimate terms. 3 easy to understand 浅近 qiǎnjìn simple; easy to understand</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="24318976"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">邮局</headword><headword charset="tc">郵局</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">you2ju2</pron><defn>noun post office</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34990336"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">饭馆</headword><headword charset="tc">飯館</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">fan4guan3</pron><defn>noun (small) restaurant; eating house 下饭馆 xià fànguǎn eat (or dine) in a restaurant</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="20763648"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">银行</headword><headword charset="tc">銀行</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">yin2hang2</pron><defn>noun bank 储备银行 chǔbèi yínháng reserve bank 储蓄银行 Chǔxù yínháng savings bank</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34736384"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">往</headword><headword charset="tc">往</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">wang3</pron><defn>verb go 往哪儿？ wǎng nǎr Where to go? 
preposition in the direction of; towards; to 往东走 wǎng dōng zǒu go eastwards 往前看 wǎng qián kàn look forward 往左拐 wǎng zuǒ guǎi turn to the left 
adjective past; previous 往初 wǎngchū literary in ancient times</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="32123392"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">哪儿</headword><headword charset="tc">哪兒</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">na3r5</pron><defn>pronoun colloquial 1 where 他上哪儿去啦？ Tā shàng nǎr qù la？ Where has he gone? 这本书你是哪儿弄来的？ Zhè běn shū nǐ shì nǎr nòng lái de? Where did you get this book? 2 wherever; anywhere 哪儿都找不到他。 Nǎr dōu zhǎo bù dào tā. He is nowhere to be found. 哪儿需要, 我就上哪儿去。 Nǎr xūyào, wǒ jiù shàng nǎr qù. I’ll go wherever I’m needed. 昨天你没上哪儿去过吗？ Zuótiān nǐ méi shàng nǎr qù guò ma? Did you go anywhere yesterday? 
adverb [in rhetorical questions to express negation] 我哪儿知道他不吃牛肉。 Wǒ nǎr zhīdao tā bù chī niúròu. How was I to know he doesn’t eat beef? 这么多的词儿, 我哪儿记得住。 Zhème duō de cír, wǒ nǎr jì de zhù. How could I remember all those words?</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27120896"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">这儿</headword><headword charset="tc">這兒</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zhe4r5</pron><defn>pronoun colloquial 1 here 2 [after 打, 从 or 由] now; then 打这儿起我就要天天学英语了。 Dǎ zhèr qǐ wǒ jiùyào tiāntiān xué Yīngyǔ le. From now on I’m going to study English every day. 从这儿以后我再也没见着他。 Cóng zhèr yǐhòu wǒ zài yě méi jiàn zhe tā. Since then I haven’t seen him again.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35938048"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">楼</headword><headword charset="tc">樓</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">lou2</pron><defn>noun 1 storied building; tower 钟楼 zhōnglóu bell (or clock) tower 公寓楼 gōngyùlóu apartment building 教学楼 jiàoxuélóu classroom building 写字楼 xiězìlóu office building 2 storey; floor 一楼 yīlóu ground floor (UK); first floor (US) 二楼 èrlóu first floor (UK); second floor (US) 3 superstructure 城楼 chénglóu gate tower 4 [in the names of certain kinds of shops, restaurants, etc.] 酒楼 jiǔlóu restaurant 5 ornamental archway; ceremonial gateway 门楼儿 ménlóur arch over a gateway 6 (Lóu) a surname</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26171392"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">走</headword><headword charset="tc">走</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zou3</pron><defn>verb 1 walk; go 走遍全国 zǒubiàn quánguó travel the length and breadth of the country 走很远的路 zǒu hěn yuǎn de lù walk a long distance 走下主席台 zǒu xià zhǔxítái step down from the rostrum 走群众路线 zǒu qúnzhòng lùxiàn follow the mass line 走社会主义道路 zǒu shèhuìzhǔyì dàolù take the socialist road 走在游行队伍的前列 zǒu zài yóuxíng duìwu de qiánliè march in the van of the procession 走前人没有走过的道路 zǒu qiánrén méiyǒu zǒu guò de dàolù break new paths; take untrodden paths 一直往前走 Yī zhí wǎng qián zǒu go straight ahead 这船一小时走十五海里。 Zhè chuán yī xiǎoshí zǒu shíwǔ hǎilǐ. The ship makes 15 knots. 2 run; move 钟不走了。 Zhōng bù zǒu le. The clock has stopped. 你这步棋走坏了。 Nǐ zhè bù qí zǒu huài le. You’ve made a bad move. 这个表走得很准。 Zhège biǎo zǒu de hěn zhǔn. This watch keeps good time. 打得赢就打, 打不赢就走。 Dǎ de yíng jiù dǎ, dǎ bù yíng jiù zǒu. Fight when you can win, leave when you can’t. 3 leave; go away 走开！ Zǒukāi! Get away! or Clear off! 我们该走了。 Wǒmen gāi zǒu le. It’s time we left. or We must be off now. 他把蓝图拿走了。 tā bǎ lántú ná zǒu le. He’s taken the blueprint away. 4 demonstrate a certain tendency See 78185187走高zou3gao1走高;78194147走强zou3qiang2走强 5 visit; call on 他们两家走得很近。 Tāmen liǎng jiā zǒu de hěn jìn. The two families often visit each other. 6 euphemistic pass away 昨夜他安详地走了。 Zuóyè tā ānxiáng de zǒu le. He died peacefully last night. 7 through; from 咱们走这个门进去吧。 Zánmen zǒu zhège mén jìnqu ba. Let’s go in through this door. 8 leak; let out; escape 走气了。 Zǒu qì le. The gas is leaking. or The air is escaping. 9 depart from the original; lose the original shape, flavour, etc. 把原来的意思讲走样了 bǎ yuánlái de yìsi jiǎng zǒu yàng le fail to get the original meaning across; distort the original meaning</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="36990976"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">分钟</headword><headword charset="tc">分鐘</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">fen1zhong1</pron><defn>noun minute</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="42424754"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">出租</headword><headword charset="tc">出租</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">chu1zu1</pron><defn>verb hire out; rent; let 出租柜台 chūzū guìtái rent out the counters 房屋出租。 Fángwū chūzū. Houses to let. 游船按小时出租。 Yóuchuán àn xiǎoshí chūzū. Rowboats for hire by the hour. 这家公司出租轿车, 汽车。 Zhè jiā gōngsī chūzū jiàochē, qìchē. This company has cars and buses for hire. 
noun abbreviation colloquial VARIANT OF 42424242出租车chu1zu1che1出租车 taxicab; taxi; cab 咱们坐出租吧。 Zánmen zuò chūzū ba. Let’s take a taxi.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="18900736"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">房子</headword><headword charset="tc">房子</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">fang2zi5</pron><defn>noun 1 house; building 一幢房子 yī zhuàng fángzi a house 2 flat; apartment 一套两室一厅的房子 yī tào liǎng shì yī tīng defángzi a flat with two bedrooms and a living room</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="20823808"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">先生</headword><headword charset="tc">先生</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xian1sheng5</pron><defn>noun 1 teacher 要做人民的先生, 先做人民的学生。 Yào zuò rénmín de xiānsheng, xiān zuò rénmín de xuésheng. To be a teacher of the people, one must first be their pupil. 2 Mister (Mr); gentleman; sir 总统先生 Zǒngtǒng xiānsheng Mr President 女士们, 先生们！ Nǚshì men, xiānsheng men! Ladies and Gentlemen! 3 husband 她先生出差去了。 Tā xiānsheng chūchāi qù le. Her husband is away on business. 我先生不在家。 Wǒ xiānsheng bù zàijiā. My husband is out. 4 dialect doctor 5 dated [usu. after a profession] 算命先生 suànmìng xiānsheng fortune-teller 账房先生 zhàngfángxiānsheng bookkeeper</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="32872960"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">平方米</headword><headword charset="tc">平方米</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ping2fang1mi3</pron><defn>square metre (sq. m., m2)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27913728"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">联系</headword><headword charset="tc">聯繫</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">lian2xi4</pron><defn>noun contact; touch; connection; relation 保持联系 bǎochí liánxì keep in contact (or touch) with 取得联系 qǔdé liánxì get in touch with; establish contact with 失去联系 shīqù liánxì lose contact 事物的内部联系 Shìwù de nèibù liánxì internal relations of things 事物的外部联系 shìwù de wàibù liánxì external relations of things 有广泛的社会联系 yǒu guǎngfàn de shèhuì liánxì have wide social connections 
verb 1 arrange; get in touch with 联系住处 liánxì zhùchù arrange accommodation 看电影的事, 找俱乐部联系。 kàn diànyǐng de shì, zhǎo jùlèbù liánxì. As for movies, please contact the club. 随时跟我联系。 Suíshí gēn wǒ liánxì. Keep in touch with me. 2 integrate; relate; link 理论联系实际 lǐlùn liánxì shíjì integrate theory with practice; apply theory to reality 密切联系群众 mìqiè liánxì qúnzhòng maintain close ties with the masses 中国的前途同世界的前途紧密地联系在一起。 Zhōngguó de qiántú tóng shìjiè de qiántú jǐnmì de liánxì zài yīqǐ. The future of China is closely linked with that of the whole world.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="25758976"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">方便</headword><headword charset="tc">方便</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">fang1bian4</pron><defn>verb 1 make things convenient for sb. 方便群众 fāngbiàn qúnzhòng make things convenient for the people 2 euphemistic have money to spare or lend 手头不方便 shǒutóu bù fāngbiàn have little money to spare 3 euphemistic go to the lavatory 你要不要方便一下？ Nǐ yào bù yào fāngbiàn yīxià？ Do you want to use the lavatory (or wash your hands)? 稍候, 我去方便方便。 Shāohòu, wǒ qù fāngbiàn fāngbiàn. Wait a few minutes. I’m just going to wash my hands. 
noun convenience; favour 把困难留给自己, 把方便让给别人 Bǎ kùnnan liúgěi zìjǐ, bǎ fāngbiàn ràng gěi biéren take difficulties on oneself and make things easy for others 请您行个方便吧。 qǐng nín xíng ge fāngbiàn ba. Do me a favour, will you?</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="20775680"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">宿舍</headword><headword charset="tc">宿舍</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">su4she4</pron><defn>noun hostel; living quarters; dormitory 集体宿舍 jítǐ sùshè dormitory 学生宿舍 xuésheng sùshè students’ hostel (or dormitory) 职工宿舍 zhígōng sùshè living quarters for staff and workers</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30935296"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">地铁站</headword><headword charset="tc">地鐵站</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">di4tie3zhan4</pron><defn>subway station; metro station</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="68428843"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">交通</headword><headword charset="tc">交通</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jiao1tong1</pron><defn>noun 1 traffic; communications 交通便利 jiāotōng biànlì have transport facilities 交通不便 Jiāotōng bùbiàn be inconveniently located; have poor transport facilities 交通不畅 jiāotōng bù chàng traffic congestion 交通繁忙 jiāotōng fánmáng heavy traffic 交通瘫痪 jiāo tōng tān huàn traffic paralysis; traffic tie-up 交通阻塞 Jiāotōng zǔsè. traffic jam (or block); traffic hold-up 妨碍交通 Fáng&apos;ài jiāotōng interfere with the traffic 公路交通 Gōnglù jiāotōng highway traffic 陆上交通 lùshàng jiāotōng land traffic 市区交通 shìqū jiāotōng urban traffic 中西交通 Zhōng-Xī jiāotōng communications between the West and China 2 liaison; liaison man 跑交通 pǎo jiāo tōng do liaison work 
verb literary 1 be connected; be linked 阡陌交通。 Qiānmòjiāotōng. Linking paths lead everywhere. 2 associate with; collude with 与权贵交通 yǔ quánguì jiāotōng try to make friends with the bigwigs</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="23941632"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">怎么</headword><headword charset="tc">怎麼</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zen3me5</pron><defn>pronoun 1 how; what; why 怎么办？ Zěnme bàn？ What’s to be done? or Now what? 怎么你不告诉他？ Zěnme nǐ bù gàosu tā？ Why don’t you tell him? 你怎么啦？ Nǐ zěnme la？ What’s the matter with you? or Is anything the matter? 你怎么不去？ Nǐ zěnme bù qù？ Why aren’t you going? 你怎么搞的！ Nǐ zěnme gǎo de! See what you’ve done! 你是怎么来的？ Nǐ shì zěnme lái de？ How did you get here? 这是怎么回事？ Zhè shì zěnme huí shì？ What’s all this about? or What’s happening? 这个字怎么写？ Zhège zì zěnme xiě？ How do you write this character? 我怎么没听说过这事儿？ Wǒ zěnme méi tīngshuō guò zhè shìr？ How come I never heard of it? 2 in a certain way; in any way; no matter how 该怎么办就怎么办 Gāi zěnme bàn jiù zěnme bàn do what must be done 你怎么说, 我就怎么做。 Nǐ zěnme shuō, wǒ jiù zěnme zuò. I’ll do just as you say. or I’ll do whatever you say. 不知道怎么一来我就滑倒了。 Bù zhīdao zěnme yī lái wǒ jiù huá dǎo le. Somehow I just slipped and fell. 健康的重要性, 怎么强调也不过分。 Jiànkāng de zhòngyàoxìng, zěnme qiángdiào yě bù guòfèn. The importance of good health cannot be emphasized too strongly (or cannot be overemphasized). 他把怎么来怎么去都告诉了大家。 Tā bǎ zěnme lái zěnme qù dōu gàosu le dàjiā. He told us everything, from beginning to end. 这本词典怎么贵我也要买。 Zhè běn cídiǎn zěnme guì wǒ yě yào mǎi. I’ll buy the dictionary no matter how expensive. 3 [used in the negative as an understatement] (not) very; (not) much; (not) quite; (not) too 那个不怎么贵。 Nàge bùzěnme guì. That’s not very expensive. 他不怎么说话。 Tā bù zěnme shuōhuà. He doesn’t talk much. 今天我不怎么舒服。 Jīntiān wǒ bù zěnme shūfu. I’m not very well today. 这个地方我不怎么熟。 Zhège dìfang wǒ bù zěnme shú. I’m not very familiar with the place. 这首歌我还没怎么学会。 Zhè shǒu gē wǒ hái méi zěnme xué huì. I haven’t quite learnt the song yet. 4 [used by itself at the beginning of a sentence to show surprise] what 怎么连你都不知道！ Zěnme lián nǐ dōu bù zhīdao! What? Even you don’t know! 怎么, 他还没来吗？ Zěnme, tā hái méi lái ma？ What? Isn’t he here yet?</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35693056"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">路人</headword><headword charset="tc">路人</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">lu4ren2</pron><defn>noun 1 passerby; wayfarer 2 stranger 形同路人 xíng tóng lù rén treat sb. like a stranger</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26241536"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">附近</headword><headword charset="tc">附近</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">fu4jin4</pron><defn>adjective nearby; neighbouring 附近地区 fùjìn dìqū nearby regions 附近的城市 fùjìn de chéngshì neighbouring (or adjacent) towns 
noun vicinity; neighbourhood 住在工厂附近 zhù zài gōngchǎng fùjìn live close to the factory 附近有没有邮局？ Fùjìn yǒu méi yǒu yóujú？ Is there a post office near here? 就在附近, 几分钟就走到了。 jiù zài fùjìn, jǐ fēnzhōng jiù zǒudào le. It’s only a few minutes’ walk from here.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="21272064"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">南京</headword><headword charset="tc">南京</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Nan2jing1</pron><defn>Nanjing (capital of Jiangsu province)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27173376"/><catassign category="Lektion9"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">颜色</headword><headword charset="tc">顏色</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">yan2se4</pron><defn>noun 1 colour; colourity 你最喜欢什么颜色？ Nǐ zuì xǐhuan shénme yánsè？ What colour do you like most? 2 countenance; facial expression 给他一点儿颜色看看 Gěi tā yīdiǎnryánsè kànkan make it hot for him; teach him a lesson 脸上现出不悦的颜色 liǎn shàng xiànchū bùyuè deyánsè look unhappy 3 countenance; appearance; looks 颜色枯槁 yánsè kūgǎo look haggard</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34042112"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">需要</headword><headword charset="tc">需要</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xu1yao4</pron><defn>noun need 从群众的需要出发 Cóng qúnzhòng de xūyào chūfā make the needs of the masses our starting point 适应形势发展的需要 shìyìng xíngshì fāzhǎn de xūyào adapt to the needs of the developing conditions 
verb need; want; require; demand 这本书我非常需要。 Zhè běn shū wǒ fēicháng xūyào. I need this book badly. 这所房子需要修理。 Zhè suǒ fángzi xūyào xiūlǐ. The house wants repairing. 这种情况需要立即采取措施。 Zhèzhǒng qíngkuàng xūyào lìjí cǎiqǔ cuòshī. This situation requires (or demands) immediate action. 坏习惯一旦养成, 需要很长的时间才能根除。 Huài xíguàn yīdàn yǎngchéng, xūyào hěn cháng de shíjiān cái néng gēnchú. A bad habit once contracted takes a very long time to uproot (or root up).</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33659648"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">一些</headword><headword charset="tc">一些</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">yi1xie1</pron><defn>measure word a number of; certain; some; a few; a little 有一些国家 yǒu yīxiē guójiā some (or a number of) countries 作一些适当的调整 zuò yīxiē shìdàng de tiáozhěng make certain appropriate readjustments</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34427136"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">三里屯</headword><headword charset="tc">三里屯</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">San1li3tun2</pron><defn>Sanlitun (Beijing street name)</defn></entry><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">坐</headword><headword charset="tc">坐</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zuo4</pron><defn>verb 1 sit 请坐。 Qǐngzuò. Please sit down. 请进来坐坐。 Qǐng jìnlai zuò zuò. Please come in and sit for a while. 他忽然坐起来了。 Tā hūrán zuò qǐlai le. He sat up suddenly. 我愿意站着, 你坐下吧。 Wǒ yuànyi zhànzhe, nǐ zuòxia ba. I’ll love to stand, you sit. 2 travel by or on (any conveyance except those which are straddled) 坐火车去 zuò huǒchē qù go by train 坐公共汽车 zuò gōnggòng qìchē ride on a bus 坐电梯上去 zuò diàntī shàng qù go up by lift; take the elevator 3 (of a building) have its back towards 这所房子坐北朝南。 Zhè suǒ fángzi zuò běi cháo nán. This house faces south. 4 put (a pan, pot, kettle, etc.) on a fire 把壶坐上 Bǎ hú zuò shàng put the kettle on (the fire) 5 (of a building) sink; subside 这个房子向后坐了。 Zhège fángzi xiàng hòu zuò le. This house is beginning to lean backwards. 6 (of rifles, guns, etc.) recoil; kick back See 37131008坐力zuo4li4坐力 7 bear (fruit) See 37127168坐果zuo4guo3坐果 8 be punished See 20743680反坐fan3zuo4反坐 9 contract (or have) a disease; suffer from a disease 年轻时坐下了腿寒的毛病 niánqīng shí zuòxià le tuǐ hán de máobing got one’s cold legs during one’s youth 
noun VARIANT OF 37165824座zuo4座1 seat; place 
preposition literary because; for the reason that 坐此解职 zuòcǐxièzhí be dismissed for this reason 
adverb literary without any reason or cause; for no reason 惊砂坐飞 jīngshā zuò fēi dust flew without wind</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="37120512"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">公共汽车</headword><headword charset="tc">公共汽車</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">gong1gong4 qi4che1</pron><defn>noun (public) bus 上公共汽车 shàng gōnggòng qìchē get on the bus 下公共汽车 Xià gōnggòngqìchē get off the bus 双层公共汽车 shuāngcénggōnggòngqìchē double-decker bus 乘1路公共汽车去西单。 chéng 1 lù gōnggòngqìchē qù xī dān. Take Bus No.1 to Xidan.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="21698304"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">还是</headword><headword charset="tc">還是</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hai2shi5</pron><defn>adverb 1 still; yet 废物还是可以利用的。 Fèiwù háishi kěyǐ lìyòng de. Waste materials can still be made use of. 这次还是他做我们的向导。 Zhècì háishi tā zuò wǒmen de xiàngdǎo. He is still our guide for this trip. 尽管旱情严重, 今年的小麦还是丰收了。 Jǐnguǎn hànqíng yánzhòng, jīnnián de xiǎomài háishi fēngshōu le. Despite the serious drought, the wheat harvest this year was good. 2 [expressing a preference for an alternative] 还是坐飞机快。 Hái shi zuò fēijī kuài. It’s much faster to travel by air after all. 还是你来吧, 我在家等你。 Hái shi nǐ lái ba, wǒ zài jiā děng nǐ. It would be better for you to come; I’ll be at home waiting for you. 天冷了, 你还是多穿点儿吧。 Tiān lěng le, nǐ hái shi duō chuān diǎnr ba. It’s getting cold, you’d better put on more clothes. 3 [expressing realization or discovery] 还是厉害的人有办法。 háishi lìhai de rén yǒu bànfǎ. It’s the pushing type that gets on. 这个人还是真了不起。 Zhège rén hái shi zhēn liǎobuqǐ. This chap is really great. 
conjunction 1 or 你去, 还是他去？ Nǐ qù, háishi tā qù? Are you going or is he? 先去上海还是先去西安还没有定。 Xiān qù Shànghǎi háishi xiān qù Xī&apos;ān hái méiyǒu dìng. We haven’t decided yet whether we go to Shanghai or Xi’an first. 2 no matter what; whether...or...; regardless of 不管刮风还是下雨, 他天天准时到校。 Bùguǎn guāfēng háishi xiàyǔ, tā tiāntiān zhǔnshí dào xiào. He goes to school on time every day no matter whether it rains or blows. 无论唱歌还是跳舞, 她都行。 Wúlùn chànggē háishi tiàowǔ, tā dōu xíng. Singing or dancing, she is good at both.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22250496"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">然后</headword><headword charset="tc">然後</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ran2hou4</pron><defn>conjunction then; after that; afterwards 我们先研究一下, 然后再决定。 Wǒmen xiān yánjiū yīxià, ránhòu zài juédìng. We’ll consider the problem carefully before coming to any decision. 我们看了一场电影, 然后就回家了。 Wǒmen kàn le yī chǎng diànyǐng, ránhòu jiù huíjiā le. We saw a film, and then (we) went home.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="28901120"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">当然</headword><headword charset="tc">當然</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">dang1ran2</pron><defn>adverb without doubt; certainly; of course 这样做当然最好。 Zhèyàng zuò dāngrán zuì hǎo. Of course this is the best way to do it. 借你的笔用一下可以吗？——当然可以。 Jiè nǐ de bǐ yòng yī xià kěyǐ ma？ —— dāngrán kěyǐ. May I borrow your pen? —Certainly! or Sure! 
adjective 1 natural 当然同盟军 Dāngrán tóngméngjūn natural ally 你取得成功是当然的。 Nǐ qǔdé chénggōng shì dāngrán de. It is quite natural that you should succeed. 2 ex officio 当然成员 Dāngrán chéngyuán an ex officio member (of a committee, etc.) 当然继承人 dāngrán jìchéngrén heir apparent</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19651584"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">意大利</headword><headword charset="tc">意大利</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Yi4da4li4</pron><defn>Italy</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34648320"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">餐厅</headword><headword charset="tc">餐廳</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">can1ting1</pron><defn>noun 1 dining room; dining hall 2 restaurant 旋转餐厅 xuánzhuǎn cāntīng revolving restaurant 自助餐厅 zìzhù cāntīng cafeteria; automat</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="18126080"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">地铁</headword><headword charset="tc">地鐵</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">di4tie3</pron><defn>noun abbreviation 1 = 19921920地下铁道di4xia4tie3dao4地下铁道 subway; underground; metro; tube 2 underground train</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19915008"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">火车</headword><headword charset="tc">火車</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">huo3che1</pron><defn>noun train 乘火车 chéng huǒchē go by train</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="23261952"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">旅行</headword><headword charset="tc">旅行</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">lü3xing2</pron><defn>verb travel; journey; tour 旅行结婚 lǚxíng jiéhūn get married on a trip 秋季旅行 qiūjì lǚxíng autumn tour (or travel) 徒步旅行 túbù lǚxíng walking tour 去欧洲旅行 qù Ōuzhōu lǚxíng take a trip to Europe 作长途旅行 Zuò chángtú lǚxíng make a long journey 组织外国留学生到南方旅行 zǔzhī wàiguó liúxuéshēng dào nánfāng lǚxíng arrange a tour to the South for foreign students</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26266880"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">暑假</headword><headword charset="tc">暑假</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shu3jia4</pron><defn>noun summer vacation (or holidays) 我校每年七月放暑假。 wǒ xiào měi nián Qīyuè fàng shǔjià. Our school begins summer vacation in July every year.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30493184"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">第一个</headword><headword charset="tc">第一個</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">di4-yi1 ge4</pron><defn>noun 2 the first (person) 他是首位横渡英吉利海峡的残疾人。 tā shì shǒuwèi héngdù Yīngjílì Hǎixiá de cánjírén. He is the first handicapped man to swim across the English Channel.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="74324139"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">桂林</headword><headword charset="tc">桂林</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Gui4lin2</pron><defn>noun Guilin (a city and tourist resort in Guangxi) 桂林山水甲天下。 Guìlín shānshuǐ jiǎ tiānxià. Guilin’s scenery ranks first in the world.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="61449443"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">船</headword><headword charset="tc">船</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">chuan2</pron><defn>noun boat; ship 上船 shàngchuán board a ship; go on board; embark 乘船去大连 chéngchuán qù Dàlián go to Dalian by boat; embark (on a ship) for Dalian</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19002368"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">游览</headword><headword charset="tc">遊覽</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">you2lan3</pron><defn>verb go sight-seeing; tour; visit 游览长城 yóulǎn Chángchéng visit the Great Wall 游览西湖 yóulǎn Xī Hú go sight-seeing on the West Lake</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35041536"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">爬山</headword><headword charset="tc">爬山</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">pa2shan1</pron><defn>verb 1 (-//-) climb a mountain 去爬山 Qù páshān go climbing 2 colloquial sports mountain climbing; mountaineering</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="42427058"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">拍照</headword><headword charset="tc">拍照</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">pai1//zhao4</pron><defn>verb take a picture or have a picture taken; photograph 我拍了十几张照(片)。 Wǒ pāi le shíjǐ zhāng zhào. I took about a dozen pictures. or I had a dozen pictures taken.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27550208"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">参观</headword><headword charset="tc">參觀</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">can1guan1</pron><defn>verb visit; have a look around 参观工厂 cānguān gōngchǎng visit a factory 参观游览 cānguān yóulǎn visit places of interest; go sightseeing 参观名胜古迹 cānguān míngshènggǔjì go sightseeing to scenic spots and historical monuments 欢迎参观。 Huānyíng cānguān. Visitors are welcome.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="18116096"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">景点</headword><headword charset="tc">景點</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jing3dian3</pron><defn>noun scenic spot 观光景点 guānguāng jǐngdiǎn scenic spot; sight</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="42548914"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">足球</headword><headword charset="tc">足球</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zu2qiu2</pron><defn>noun 1 soccer; football 踢足球 Tī zúqiú play soccer (or football) 美式足球 Měishìzúqiú American football 英式足球 yīngshì zúqiú soccer; association football 2 football (used in the game)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="37022976"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">想</headword><headword charset="tc">想</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xiang3</pron><defn>verb 1 think; ponder; consider 想办法 xiǎng bànfǎ think of a way; seek a solution (or a way out) 想问题 xiǎng wèntí think over a problem 让我想一想。 Ràng wǒ xiǎng yī xiǎng. Let me think it over. or Let me see. 你想得真周到。 Nǐ xiǎng de zhēn zhōudao. You have really thought of everything. 你想清楚了没有？ Nǐ xiǎng qīngchu le méiyǒu？ Have you thought it out (or through)? 我们也要想想困难。 Wǒmen yě yào xiǎngxiǎng kùnnan. We must also anticipate difficulties. 我在想下一步棋该怎么走。 Wǒ zài xiǎng xià yī bù qí gāi zěnme zǒu. I’m considering my next (chess) move. 2 think back; try to remember; recall; recollect 回想往事 huí xiǎng wǎngshì recall the past 你好好想想钥匙搁哪儿了。 Nǐ hǎohāo xiǎngxiǎng yàoshi gē nǎr le. Think back carefully where you could have put the key. 3 suppose; reckon; consider; think 我想不至于吧。 Wǒ xiǎng bùzhìyú ba. I don’t believe things could get that bad. or Surely as bad as that! 我想我该走了。 Wǒ xiǎng wǒ gāi zǒu le. I’m afraid I must be going now. 你想他能买到票吗？ Nǐ xiǎng tā néng mǎi dào piào ma？ Do you suppose he can get the tickets? 我想他今天不会来。 Wǒ xiǎng tā jīntiān bù huì lái. I don’t think he’ll come today. 4 want to; wish to; feel like (doing sth.) 我也想试试。 Wǒ yě xiǎng shìshi. I’d like to try too. 他很想上大学。 Tā hěn xiǎng shàng dàxué. He longs to go to college. 你想看足球赛吗？ Nǐ xiǎng kàn zúqiúsài ma？ Do you want to see (or feel like seeing) a football match? 她不想跟我们去。 Tā bù xiǎng gēn wǒmen qù. She doesn’t wish to come with us. 5 remember with longing; miss 你走了以后, 我们都很想你。 Nǐ zǒu le yǐhòu, wǒmen dōu hěn xiǎng nǐ. After you left, we all missed you. 王大娘想女儿都想病了。 Wáng dàniáng xiǎng nǚ&apos;ér dōu xiǎng bìng le. Auntie Wang misses her daughter so much she’s fallen ill.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33072896"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">球</headword><headword charset="tc">球</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">qiu2</pron><defn>noun 1 sphere; globe See 28737792球体qiu2ti3球体 2 anything shaped like a ball 雪球 xuěqiú snowball 3 game; match 看球去。 Kàn qiú qù. Let’s go to watch the game. 4 the globe; the earth 地球 dìqiú the earth; the globe 
noun 1 ball 传球 chuán qiú pass a ball 球王 qiúwáng ball king 2 marbles</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="28731136"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">比赛</headword><headword charset="tc">比賽</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">bi3sai4</pron><defn>noun match; competition 射击比赛 shèjī bǐsài shooting contest 象棋比赛 xiàngqí bǐsài chess tournament 选美比赛 xuǎnměibǐsài beauty contest 足球比赛 zúqiú bǐsài football match 自行车比赛 zìxíngchē bǐsài bicycle race 力量悬殊的比赛 Lìliang xuánshū debǐsài uneven match; one-sided match 势均力敌的比赛 shìjūnlìdí debǐsài tight match; close match 
verb contend; compete 比赛划船 bǐsài huáchuán rowing match 比赛射击 bǐsài shèjī compete in a shooting match</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="17463296"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">队</headword><headword charset="tc">隊</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">dui4</pron><defn>noun 1 row of people; line 排成两队 pái chéng liǎng duì fall into two lines; stand in two rows 2 team; group 篮球队 lánqiúduì basketball team 3 abbreviation Young Pioneers 队鼓 duì gǔ Young Pioneer’s drum 
measure word file; line; row 一队战士 yī duì zhànshì a file of soldiers</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="20378368"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">英格兰</headword><headword charset="tc">英格蘭</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Ying1ge2lan2</pron><defn>noun England</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="75837155"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">体育场</headword><headword charset="tc">體育場</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ti3yu4chang3</pron><defn>noun 1 sports field (or ground) 2 stadium</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="31334144"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">希望</headword><headword charset="tc">希望</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xi1wang4</pron><defn>verb hope; wish; expect 希望你明天能来。 Xīwàng nǐ míngtiān néng lái. I hope you’ll come tomorrow. 他希望长大了当医生。 Tā xīwàng zhǎngdà le dāng yīshēng. He wants to be a doctor when he grows up. 
noun 1 hope; wish; expectation 把希望变成现实 Bǎ xīwàng biànchéng xiànshí turn hopes into reality 大有成功的希望 dà yǒu chénggōng de xīwàng promise high hopes of success; stand a very good chance of success 他康复的希望不大。 Tā kāngfù de xīwàng bù dà. There is little hope of his recovery. or He is unlikely to recover. 2 that on which hope is placed 青少年是我们的未来, 是我们的希望。 Qīng-shàonián shì wǒmen de wèilái, shì wǒmen de xīwàng. The youth is our future and our hope.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="32649728"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">赢</headword><headword charset="tc">贏</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ying2</pron><defn>verb 1 win; beat (opp. 输) 我象棋下不赢他。 Wǒ xiàngqí xià bù yíng tā. I can’t beat him at Chinese chess. 这场比赛谁赢了？ Zhè chǎng bǐsài shuí yíng le？ Who won the game? 2 gain (profit)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34859520"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">网球</headword><headword charset="tc">網球</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">wang3qiu2</pron><defn>noun 1 tennis 软式网球 ruǎnshì wǎngqiú soft tennis 2 tennis ball</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="32118016"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">会</headword><headword charset="tc">會</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hui4</pron><defn>noun 1 meeting; gathering; party; get-together; conference 报告会 bàogàohuì public lecture 研讨会 yántǎohuì seminar 2 association; society; union 帮会 bānghuì secret soceity 协会 xiéhuì association 3 temple fair 庙会 miàohuì temple fair 4 association of worshippers 香会 xiānghuì company of Buddhist pilgrims 5 revolving credit association (people who regularly contribute to a common fund and draw from it by turns) 6 chief city; capital 都会 dūhuì metropolis 7 literary opportunity; occasion 适逢其会 shìféngqíhuì happen to be present at the right moment 
verb 1 get together; assemble 聚会 jùhuì meet; get together 2 meet; see 昨天我没有会着他。 Zuótiān wǒ méiyǒu huì zhe tā. I didn’t see him yesterday. 3 literary happen to 会有客来。 Huì yǒu kè lái. A visitor happened to come by. 4 literary should; ought to 
verb 1 understand; grasp 误会 wùhuì misunderstand 2 know 他还会两出京戏。 Tā hái huì liǎng chū Jīngxì. He knows a few airs of Beijing opera. 我会英语, 不会日语。 Wǒ huì Yīngyǔ, bù huì Rìyǔ. I know English but not Japanese. 3 can; be able to 会滑冰 Huì huábīng can skate 这孩子刚会走路, 还不大会说话。 Zhè háizi gāng huì zǒulù, hái bù dà huì shuōhuà. The infant has just learnt to walk but not to speak yet. 4 excel at; be good at; be skillful in 会修钟表 huì xiū zhōngbiǎo skilled in repairing clocks and watches 很会这一套 hěn huì zhè yī tào be a past master of this sort of game 5 be likely to; be sure to 他会来的。 Tā huì lái de. He’s sure to come. 他会在家吗？ Tā huì zài jiā ma？ Is he likely to be at home? 没想到(事情)会这么顺利。 méi xiǎngdào huì zhème shùnlì. I didn’t expect things to go so smoothly. 
verb pay (or foot) a bill 饭钱我会过了。 Fàn qián wǒ huì guò le. I’ve paid for the meal. 
noun colloquial moment 来了一会儿了 Lái le yī huì r le have been here for a while</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="23167488"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">跳舞</headword><headword charset="tc">跳舞</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">tiao4//wu3</pron><defn>verb 1 dance (in a performance) 2 dance (socially)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="31490048"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">过</headword><headword charset="tc">過</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">guo4</pron><defn>verb 1 cross; pass 过河 guòhé cross a river 爬雪山, 过草地 pá xuěshān, guò cǎodì climb snow-topped mountains and cross the grasslands 游行队伍要从我们街区过。 yóuxíng duìwu yào cóng wǒmen jiēqū guò. The parade will pass through our neighbourhood. 2 spend (time); pass (time) 过生日 guò shēngri celebrate one’s birthday 春节在工地上过 Chūnjié zài gōngdì shàng guò spend the Spring Festival at the construction site 假期过得怎样？ Jiàqī guò de zěnyàng？ How did you spend your holiday? 日子越来越好过了。 Rìzi yuèláiyuè hǎo guò le. Life is getting better and better. 3 transfer; move to 你的工资已过到账上。 nǐ de gōngzī yǐ guò dào zhàng shàng. Your salary has been transferred to your account. 4 go through; undergo (a process) See 22212864过秤guo4cheng4过秤 5 review; go over 咱们把稿子再过一遍。 Zánmen bǎ gǎozi zài guò yī biàn. Let’s go over the draft once again. 6 go beyond; after (a certain point of time) 我过两天再来。 Wǒ guò liǎng tiān zài lái. I’ll come again in a couple of days. 过了夏至, 天就开始变短。 Guò le Xiàzhì, tiān jiù kāishǐ biàn duǎn. The days get shorter after the Summer Solstice. 过了好几个月我才收到他的信。 Guò le hǎojǐ ge yuè wǒ cái shōudào tā de xìn. Several months passed before I heard from him. 7 exceed; go beyond 雪深过膝。 Xuě shēn guò xī. The snow is more than knee-deep. 亩产过千斤。 Mǔchǎn guò qiān jīn. The yield is over 1,000 jin per mu. 树长得过了房。 Shù zhǎng de guò le fáng. The tree has grown taller than the house. 小心别坐过了站。 Xiǎoxīn bié zuò guò le zhàn. Make sure you don’t go past your station. 8 visit See 22216192过访guo4fang3过访 9 euphemistic pass away; die 老太太过了好几天了。 Lǎotàitaiguò le hǎojǐtiān le. The old woman died several days ago. 
noun fault; mistake (opp. 功) See 22213376过错guo4cuo4过错 
adverb 1 excessively; over 过长 guò cháng too long; unduly long 过早 guòzǎo too early; premature 雨水过多 Yǔshuǐ guò duō excessive rainfall; too much rain 2 physics chemistry per-; super-; over- 过熔 guò róng superfusion See 61551843过氧化物guo4yang3hua4wu4过氧化物 3 [after a verb plus 得 or 不 to indicate winning or deserving] 要说跑, 咱们谁也比不过他。 Yào shuō pǎo, zánmen shuí yě bǐ bù guò tā. None of us runs as fast as he. 这样的大学生, 我们信得过。 Zhèyàng de dàxuéshēng, wǒmen xìndeguò. We have confidence in college students like this sort.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22210048"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">游泳</headword><headword charset="tc">游泳</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">you2yong3</pron><defn>verb swim 去游泳 qù yóuyǒng go for a swim; go swimming 参加游泳比赛 cānjiā yóuyǒng bǐsài take part in a swimming contest 在游泳中学习游泳 zài yóuyǒng zhōng xuéxí yóuyǒng learn to swim by swimming 
noun sports swimming</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35053568"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">休闲</headword><headword charset="tc">休閒</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xiu1xian2</pron><defn>verb enjoy one&apos;s free time; leisure; go on holidays 休闲娱乐 xiūxián yúlè entertainment 
verb argriculture lie fallow</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33591808"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">问卷</headword><headword charset="tc">問卷</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">wen4juan4</pron><defn>noun questionnaire</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="73020387"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">性别</headword><headword charset="tc">性別</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xing4bie2</pron><defn>noun sex distinction; sex; gender</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33538560"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">男</headword><headword charset="tc">男</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">nan2</pron><defn>adjective 1 man; boy; male (opp. 女) 男病房 nánbìngfáng men’s ward 男护士 nánhùshi male nurse 男学生 nánxuésheng boy student 男佣人 nányòngrén manservant 男主人公 nánzhǔréngōng hero 2 (of certain animals) male 男猫 nánmāo male cat 
noun literary son; boy 长男 zhǎngnán one’s eldest son 
noun baron See 27161344男爵nan2jue2男爵</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27157760"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">女</headword><headword charset="tc">女</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">nü3</pron><defn>adjective 1 woman; female (opp. 男) 女教师 nǚjiàoshī woman teacher 女民兵 nǚ mínbīng militiawoman 女学生 nǚxuésheng girl student 女演员 nǚyǎnyuán actress 女医生 nǚyīshēng woman doctor 女英雄 nǚyīngxióng heroine 女职工 nǚzhígōng female staff or employees 女飞行员 nǚ fēixíngyuán female aviator; woman pilot 女售货员 nǚshòuhuòyuán saleswoman 女运动员 nǚyùndòngyuán sportswoman 2 dialect (of certain animals) female 女猫 nǚ māo female cat 
noun 1 daughter; girl 儿女 érnǚ son and daughter; children 2 archaic astronomy nü (the tenth of the twenty-eight constellations (二十八宿) into which the celestial sphere was divided, consisting of four stars in the shape of a sieve in Aquarius)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27478272"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">踢</headword><headword charset="tc">踢</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ti1</pron><defn>verb 1 kick 踢开绊脚石 Tī kāi bànjiǎoshí kick away a stumbling block 把凳子踢翻 bǎ dèngzi tī fān kick over a stool 一脚把门踢开 yī jiǎo bǎmén tī kāi open the door with a kick; kick the door open 小心这马踢人！ Xiǎoxīn zhè mǎ tī rén! Be careful! This horse kicks. 2 kick; play (football) 踢毽子 tī jiànzi kick the shuttlecock 踢足球 Tī zúqiú play football 踢进一个球 tī jìn yī ge qiú kick (or score) a goal 他踢中锋。 Tā tī zhōngfēng. He plays centre forward.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="31291136"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">冲浪</headword><headword charset="tc">衝浪</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">chong1lang4</pron><defn>verb sports surf; surfboard 网上冲浪 wǎngshàng chōnglàng surf the net; Internet surfing</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="18750464"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">滑雪</headword><headword charset="tc">滑雪</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hua2//xue3</pron><defn>verb ski</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22920192"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">潜水</headword><headword charset="tc">潛水</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">qian2shui3</pron><defn>verb (-//-) go under water; dive 
noun geology phreatic water</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="28367616"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">蹦极</headword><headword charset="tc">蹦極</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">beng4ji2</pron><defn>noun sports bungee jumping 去蹦极 qù bèngjí go bungee jumping 玩儿了一回蹦极 wánr le yīhuí bèngjí do (or make) a bungee jump</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="42490290"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">其他</headword><headword charset="tc">其他</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">qi2ta1</pron><defn>pronoun other; else 见到其他人了吗？ Jiàndào qítā rén le ma？ Did you see anybody else? 老李在这儿, 其他人呢？ Lǎo lǐ zài zhèr, qítā rén ne？ Lao Li’s here. Where are the others? 先拣重要的说, 再说其他。 Xiān jiǎn zhòngyào de shuō, zàishuō qítā. Say what you think is most important first, then go on to other things. 还有什么其他事情要我们做吗？ Háiyǒu shénme qítā shìqing yào wǒmen zuò ma？ Is there anything else you want us to do? 除了小冯以外, 其他人都去了。 Chúle Xiǎo Féng yǐwài, qítā rén dōu qùle. Everybody went except Xiao Feng. 我同意老王的建议, 没有其他意见。 Wǒ tóngyì lǎo wáng de jiànyì, méiyǒu qítā yìjian. I agree with Lao Wang on his proposal and have nothing else to add.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="28113152"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">小时</headword><headword charset="tc">小時</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xiao3shi2</pron><defn>noun hour 按小时计费 àn xiǎoshí jìfèi pay by the hour</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33212416"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">时候</headword><headword charset="tc">時候</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shi2hou5</pron><defn>noun 1 (the duration of) time 农忙的时候 nóngmáng de shíhou busy farming season 战争的时候 Zhànzhēng deshíhou during the war 2 (a point in) time; moment 就在这时候 jiù zài zhèshí hou just at this moment 时候不早了。 shíhou bù zǎo le. It’s getting late. 到时候我来叫你。 Dào shíhou wǒ lái jiào nǐ. I’ll call you when it’s time. 现在是什么时候了？ Xiànzài shì shénme shíhou le？ What time is it?</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30072320"/><catassign category="Lektion11"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">打算</headword><headword charset="tc">打算</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">da3suan5</pron><defn>verb plan; intend 他打算当教师。 Tā dǎsuan dāng jiàoshī. He intends to become a teacher. 代表团打算去西安访问。 Dàibiǎotuán dǎsuan qù Xī&apos;ān fǎngwèn. The delegation plans to visit Xi’an. 
noun consideration; calculation 各有各的打算。 Gè yǒu gè de dǎsuan. Each has a plan of his own. or Each has his own calculations. 为自己作打算 wèi zìjǐ zuò dǎsuan further one’s own interests 作最坏的打算 Zuò zuì huài de dǎsuan be prepared for the worst</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19368192"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">或者</headword><headword charset="tc">或者</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">huo4zhe3</pron><defn>adverb perhaps; maybe 快点走, 或者还赶得上他。 Kuài diǎn zǒu, huòzhě hái gǎndeshàng tā. Hurry up, we may catch up with him yet. 这个建议对于改进工作或者有点儿好处。 zhège jiànyì duìyú gǎijìn gōngzuò huòzhě yǒudiǎnr hǎochu. This suggestion may help to improve our work. 
conjunction 1 or; either... or... 请你把这本书交给小王或者小李。 Qǐng nǐ bǎ zhè běn shū jiāo gěi xiǎo wáng huòzhě xiǎo lǐ. Please give this book to either Xiao Wang or Xiao Li. 2 no matter what, how, etc. 不论大事或者小事, 大家都愿意找他商量。 Bùlùn dàshì huòzhě xiǎoshì, dàjiā dōu yuànyi zhǎo tā shāngliang. Everybody likes to consult with him about their problems, large or small.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="23299328"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">回</headword><headword charset="tc">回</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hui2</pron><defn>verb circle; wind 巡回 xúnhuí tour; make a tour of 
verb 1 return; go back 回国 huíguó return to one’s native land 回家 huíjiā go home 回到原地 huídào yuándì return to the source; go back to where they were 回到生产第一线 huí dào shēngchǎn dì-yī xiàn go back to one’s post on the production front 2 turn round 回过身来 huí guò shēn lái turn round 3 answer; reply 回函 huíhán reply; letter in reply 4 dated report back (to one&apos;s superior) 回大人的话 huí dàren dehuà let me report, Sir 5 decline (an invitation, etc.); refuse; cancel; dismiss 我把保姆回了。 wǒ bǎ bǎomǔ huí le. I sent away my maid. 
measure word 1 chapter 这部小说共一百回。 Zhè bù xiǎoshuō gòng yībǎi huí. This novel has one hundred chapters. 2 time; occasion 来过一回 Lái guò yī huí have been here once 完全是两回事 Wánquán shì liǎng huí shì two entirely different matters 有一回我在路上碰到他。 Yǒu yī huí wǒ zài lùshang pèngdào tā. Once, I ran into him in the street. 
noun Hui ethnic group See 23152384回族hui2zu2回族</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="23115264"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">别</headword><headword charset="tc">別</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">bie2</pron><defn>verb 1 leave; part 别故乡 bié gùxiāng leave one’s native place 辞别 cíbié say goodbye 不辞而别 bùcí&apos;érbié take French leave; leave without saying goodbye 挥泪而别 huīlèi ér bié part in tears 久别重逢 jiǔbiéchóngféng meet after a long separation 2 dialect turn; change 她把头别了过去。 Tā bǎ tóu bié le guòqu. She turned her head away. 这个人的脾气一时别不过来。 Zhège rén de píqi yīshí bié bù guòlai. There is no changing his temper. 
adjective other; another See 56541667别处bie2chu4别处 
noun 1 difference; distinction 男女有别 nánnǚyǒubié make a distinction between the sexes 天壤之别 tiānrǎngzhībié as different as light from darkness; totally different 2 classification; category 职别 zhíbié official rank 
verb literary differentiate; distinguish 别其真伪 Bié qí zhēn-wěi determine whether it’s genuine or false 
verb 1 fasten with a pin or clip 把表格别在一起 bǎ biǎogé bié zài yīqǐ pin (or clip) the forms together 胸前别着大红花 xiōngqián bié zhe dà hónghuā with a big red flower pinned on one’s breast 2 stick in 腰里别着旱烟袋 yāo lǐ bié zhe hànyāndài with a pipe stuck in one’s belt 把门别上。 Bǎ mén bié shàng. Bolt the door. 
adverb 1 [giving commands or advice] don&apos;t; better not 别忙。 Bié máng. No hurry. or Take your time. 别管我。 bié guǎn wǒ. Leave me alone. 别忘了。 Bié wàng le. Don’t forget. 2 [expressing anxiety that sth. undesirable may happen] 明天可别下雨。 Míngtiān kě bié xià yǔ. I hope it doesn’t rain tomorrow. 他别睡过头了, 误了火车。 Tā bié shuì guò tóu le, wù le huǒchē. Hope he won’t oversleep and miss the train.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="17674496"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">地方</headword><headword charset="tc">地方</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">di4fang5</pron><defn>noun 1 place; space; room 给钢琴腾出地方 Gěi gāngqín téngchū dìfang make room for the piano 你是什么地方人？ Nǐ shì shénme dìfang rén？ Where are you from? 我这个地方有点儿疼。 wǒ zhège dìfang yǒudiǎnr téng. I’ve got a pain here. 这张桌子太占地方。 Zhè zhāng zhuōzi tài zhàn dìfang. That desk takes up too much space (or room). 2 part; respect 你说的话有对的地方, 也有不对的地方。 Nǐ shuō de huà yǒu duì de dìfang, yě yǒu bùduì de dìfang. What you say is partly right.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19884800"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">新加坡</headword><headword charset="tc">新加坡</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Xin1jia1po1</pron><defn>Singapore</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33403136"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">那么</headword><headword charset="tc">那麼</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">na4me5</pron><defn>pronoun 1 like that; in that way; so 你不该那么做。 Nǐ bù gāi nàme zuò. You shouldn’t have done that. or You oughtn’t to have acted that way. 她不好意思那么说。 Tā bù hǎoyìsi nàme shuō. She was embarrassed to say that. 你那么喜欢它, 就送给你作个纪念吧。 Nǐ nàme xǐhuan tā, jiù sòng gěi nǐ zuò ge jìniàn ba. Since you like it so much, take it as a keepsake. 说说容易, 做起来可并不那么容易。 Shuōshuo róngyì, zuò qǐlai kě bìng bù nàme róngyì. It’s easier said than done. 问题没有他想象的那么复杂。 Wèntí méiyǒu tā xiǎngxiàng denàme fùzá. The problem is not as complicated as he imagines. 2 [before numerals to indicate approximation] about; or so 估计得走那么三四个钟头才能到。 Gūjì de zǒu nàme sān, sì ge zhōngtóu cái néng dào. I think it will take three or four hours to get there. 再有那么三公斤就够了。 Zài yǒu nàme sān gōngjīn jiù gòu le. Another three kilograms or so will probably be enough. 
conjunction [used to connect a clause expressing a logical consequence to a conditional clause] then; in that case 既然这样不行, 那么你打算怎么办呢？ Jìrán zhèyàng bùxíng, nàme nǐ dǎsuan zěnme bàn ne？ Since that’s impossible, what are you going to do? 如果你们都要去, 那么我就一个人留下吧。 Rúguǒ nǐmen dōu yào qù, nàme wǒ jiù yī ge rén liúxià ba. Since you all want to go, I’ll stay home alone.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27126016"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">以后</headword><headword charset="tc">以後</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">yi3hou4</pron><defn>noun (of time) after; afterwards; later; hereafter 从今以后 cóngjīnyǐhòu from now on 从那以后 cóng nà yǐhòu from then on 全国解放以后 Quánguó jiěfàng yǐhòu after (or following) the liberation of the whole country 至于以后怎么样, 我就不知道了。 Zhìyú yǐhòu zěnmeyàng, wǒ jiù bù zhīdao le. I don’t know what happened later on. 别着急, 以后你会有机会去的。 Bié zháojí, yǐhòu nǐ huì yǒu jīhuì qù de. Don’t worry. You’ll have a chance to go. 会议今天开始, 大概一星期以后结束。 Huìyì jīntiān kāishǐ, dàgài yī xīngqī yǐhòu jiéshù. The conference begins today and will probably close in a week’s time.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34546432"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">京剧</headword><headword charset="tc">京劇</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jing1ju4</pron><defn>noun Beijing opera</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="24353280"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">年</headword><headword charset="tc">年</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">nian2</pron><defn>noun 1 year 年复一年 niánfùyīnián year after year; year in year out 三年 Sān nián three years 2 annual; yearly See 67485923年产量nian2chan3liang4年产量 3 age 年过六十 nián guò liùshí over sixty (years old) 4 period in one&apos;s life 老年 lǎonián old age 童年 tóngnián childhood 5 period in history 近年来 jìnniánlái in recent years 明朝初年 míngzhāo chū nián at the beginning of the Ming Dynasty 6 harvest 丰年 fēngnián rich harvest 7 New Year 过年 guònián celebrate the New Year 8 of or for the New Year See 27329792年货nian2huo4年货 9 archaic relationship between candidates who passed the same imperial examinations See 67505635年兄nian2xiong1年兄;67506403年谊nian2yi4 年谊 10 (Nián) a surname</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27323392"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">好玩</headword><headword charset="tc">好玩</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hao3wan2</pron><defn>adjective colloquial amusing; interesting 颐和园好玩儿极了。 Yíhéyuán hǎowánr jíle. The Summer Palace is a most delightful place. 这可不是好玩儿的！ Zhè kě bù shì hǎowánr de! This is no joking matter. 这小娃娃挺好玩儿。 Zhè xiǎo wáwa tǐng hǎo wánr. The baby is very cute.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22445056"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">说</headword><headword charset="tc">說</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shuo1</pron><defn>verb 1 speak; talk; say 说风凉话 shuōfēngliánghuà make irresponsible and carping comments 说得多做得少 Shuō de duō zuò de shǎo talk much but do little 说的比唱的好听 shuō de bǐ chàng de hǎo tīng mouth high-sounding words 说得好不如做得好。 shuō de hǎo bùrú zuòdé hǎo. Better to do well than to say well. 他说法语。 Tā shuō Fǎyǔ. He speaks French. 你说得很对。 Nǐ shuō de hěn duì. What you say is quite true. 那未免说得太轻了。 Nà wèimiǎn shuō de tài qīng le. That’s putting it too mildly. 2 explain 说不通 shuōbùtōng cannot hold water; do not make sense 我一说他就明白了。 Wǒ yī shuō tā jiù míngbai le. I told him how and he caught on at once. 他说了又说, 我还是不懂。 Tā shuō le yòu shuō, wǒ háishi bù dǒng. He explained and explained, but I still couldn’t understand. 3 scold 他父亲说了他一顿。 Tā fùqin shuō le tā yī dùn. His father gave him a scolding (or talking-to). 4 act as matchmaker 给他说个媳妇儿 Gěi tā shuō ge xífùr find a wife for him 5 refer to; indicate 你的话是说谁呢？ Nǐ de huà shì shuō shuí ne？ Who did your remarks refer to? 
noun theory; teachings; doctrine 著书立说 zhùshūlìshuō write books to expound a theory</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30714112"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">只</headword><headword charset="tc">只</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zhi3</pron><defn>adverb only; just; merely 只剩一个了。 Zhǐ shèng yī ge le. There is only one left. 我只想问一个问题。 Wǒ zhǐ xiǎng wèn yī ge wèntí. I have just one question. 这只是个时间问题。 Zhè zhǐ shìge shíjiān wèntí. It is merely a question of time. 我们这车只能带三个人。 Wǒmen zhè chē zhǐ néng dài sān ge rén. We can only take three people in our car. 屋子里只老王一个人。 Wūzi lǐ zhǐ lǎo wáng yī ge rén. Old Wang was alone in the room. 只那块地就打了八百斤小麦。 Zhǐ nà kuài dì jiù dǎ le bābǎi jīn xiǎomài. That plot alone yielded 800 jin of wheat.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="36225792"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">觉得</headword><headword charset="tc">覺得</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jue2de5</pron><defn>verb 1 feel 一点儿也不觉得累 Yīdiǎnr yě bù juéde lèi not feel tired at all 2 think; feel 你觉得这个计划怎么样？ Nǐ juéde zhège jìhuà zěnmeyàng？ What do you think of the plan? 我觉得应该先跟他商量一下。 Wǒ juéde yīnggāi xiān gēn tā shāngliang yīxià. I think we should consult him first. 我觉得他这几天情绪不好。 Wǒ juéde tā zhè jǐ tiān qíngxù bù hǎo. I think he’s been in low spirits these last few days.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="24695808"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">班</headword><headword charset="tc">班</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ban1</pron><defn>noun 1 class; team 短训班 duǎnxùnbān short training course 跳班 tiàobān skip a grade in school 作业班 zuòyèbān work team 2 shift; duty 接班 jiēbān come on shift 替班 tìbān take someone else’s shift 三班倒 sānbāndǎo work in three shifts 今晚是我的班儿。 jīnwǎn shì wǒ debān r. I’ll be on duty tonight. 3 military squad 加强班 jiāqiángbān reinforced squad 4 dated [as part of the term for a troupe] 戏班儿 xìbānr theatrical troupe; company of players 5 (Bān) a surname 
verb move troops; withdraw troops 班兵 bān bīng call back troops 
measure word 1 a group of people 这班年轻人真了不起。 Zhè bān niánqīngrén zhēn liǎobuqǐ. They’re a fine bunch of young people. 2 a trip by bus, boat, etc. 班船 bānchuán regular ship 搭下一班火车 Dā xià yī bān huǒchē take the next train 一路公共汽车每隔三分钟就有一班。 Yī lù gōnggòng qìchē měi gé sān fēnzhōng jiù yǒu yī bān. There’s a Number One bus every three minutes. 
adjective regularly-run; regular; scheduled 班机 bānjī regular air service</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="17104128"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">从</headword><headword charset="tc">從</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">cong2</pron><defn>verb 1 follow; comply with; obey 从大流 cóng dà liú follow the general public 2 join; be engaged in See 19188736从军cong2jun1从军 3 follow the principle of; employ the method of 训练要从严从难。 Xùnliàn yào cóngyán cóng nán. Training should be hard and strict. 
noun dated 1 follower; attendant 从人 cóngrén followers; retinue 2 relationship between cousins, etc. of the same paternal grandfather or great-grandfather 从兄弟 cóng xiōng-dì cousins on the paternal side; cousins 
adjective secondary; accessary 主从关系 zhǔcóng guānxi principal and subordinate relations 
preposition 1 from (a time, a place, or a point of view) 从零开始 cóng líng kāishǐ start from scratch (or nothing) 从现在起 cóng xiànzài qǐ from now on 从根本上说 cóng gēnběn shàng shuō essentially; in essence 从全局出发 cóng quánjú chūfā proceed from the situation as a whole 从这儿往西 cóng zhèr wǎng xī go west from here; west of here 从我做起, 从现在做起。 cóng wǒ zuòqǐ, cóng xiànzài zuòqǐ. Begin from myself, and begin right now. 2 via, through, or past (a place) 从门缝里往外看 cóng ménfèng lǐ wǎng wài kàn peep outside through a crevice in the door 从学校门前经过 Cóng xuéxiào mén qián jīngguò pass the school gate 你从桥上过, 我从桥下走。 Nǐ cóng qiáo shàng guò, wǒ cóng qiáo xià zǒu. You go over the bridge, I’ll go under it. 
adverb [followed by a negative] ever 从不计较个人的名誉地位 Cóngbù jìjiào gèrén de míngyù dìwèi never give any consideration to personal fame or position 从没听说过。 Cóng méi tīngshuō guò. Never heard of it. 她在成绩面前从不骄傲。 Tā zài chéngjì miànqián cóngbù jiāo&apos;ào. Her head was never turned by success.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19185152"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">西安</headword><headword charset="tc">西安</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">Xi1an1</pron><defn>noun Xi&apos;an (capital of Shaanxi Province)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="32615424"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">应该</headword><headword charset="tc">應該</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ying1gai1</pron><defn>verb [as aux.] should; ought to 你应该知道。 Nǐ yīnggāi zhīdao. You ought to know. 你应该冷静些。 Nǐ yīnggāi lěngjìng xiē. You should cool down. 事情就应该这样。 Shìqing jiù yīnggāi zhèyàng. This is as it should be.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34804480"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">兵马俑</headword><headword charset="tc">兵馬俑</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">bing1ma3yong3</pron><defn>terracotta warriors and horses buried with the dead</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="17731328"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">漂亮</headword><headword charset="tc">漂亮</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">piao4liang5</pron><defn>adjective 1 handsome; good-looking; pretty; beautiful 漂亮的色彩 piàoliang de sècǎi beautiful colours 漂亮的小姑娘 piàoliang de xiǎogūniang pretty little girl 漂亮的小伙子 piàoliang de xiǎohuǒzi handsome young man 打扮得漂漂亮亮的 dǎban de piàopiàoliangliang de be smartly dressed 2 remarkable; brilliant; splendid; beautiful 打一个漂亮仗 dǎ yī ge piàoliang zhàng fight a fine battle; win a brilliant victory 普通话说得很漂亮 pǔtōng huà shuō de hěn piàoliang speak beautiful standard Chinese 守门员这个球救得真漂亮。 Shǒuményuán zhège qiú jiù de zhēn piàoliang. The goalie made a beautiful save. 3 high-sounding (but will not come true) 光说得漂亮有什么用？ Guāng shuōdepiàoliang yǒu shénme yòng? What’s the point of simply paying lip service? or High-sounding words are no use.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27865344"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">城市</headword><headword charset="tc">城市</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">cheng2shi4</pron><defn>noun town; city</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="18631936"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">千</headword><headword charset="tc">千</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">qian1</pron><defn>number 1 thousand 2 a great amount of; a great number of 千百条建议 qiān bǎi tiáo jiànyì lots and lots of suggestions 千百年来的梦想 qiān bǎi nián lái de mèngxiǎng an age-old dream 
noun (Qiān) a surname 
meaningless bound form See 28706048秋千qiu1qian1秋千</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="28266752"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">历史</headword><headword charset="tc">歷史</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">li4shi3</pron><defn>noun 1 history 历史上 lìshǐshang in history; historically; down the ages 历史悠久 lìshǐ yōujiǔ have a long history 历史地看问题 lìshǐ dì kàn wèntí look at the problem historically 历史上的今天 lìshǐ shàng de jīntiān today in history 历史遗留问题 lìshǐ yíliú wèntí problem (or issue) left over by history (or from the past); legacy from the past 创造历史 chuàngzào lìshǐ make history 风云变幻的历史 fēngyúnbiànhuàn delìshǐ eventful history 创历史最高水平 chuàng lìshǐ zuìgāo shuǐpíng hit an all-time high 全然不顾历史事实 Quánrán bù gù lìshǐ shìshí in utter disregard of historical fact 历史不会重演。 lìshǐ bù huì chóngyǎn. History never repeats itself. 历史上有很多这样的例子。 lìshǐ shàng yǒu hěn duō zhèyàng de lìzi. There are many such examples in history. 2 past events 这件事早已成为历史。 Zhè jiàn shì zǎoyǐ chéngwéi lìshǐ. That’s already past history. 3 personal records 历史清白 lìshǐ qīngbái have a clean record 隐瞒自己的历史 yǐnmán zìjǐ de lìshǐ conceal one’s past 4 history (as a course of study) 他是研究历史的。 Tā shì yánjiū lìshǐ de. His field is history. 5 historical record (or document, data) 多读点儿历史 Duō dú diǎnrlìshǐ read more of the history</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="25646336"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">主意</headword><headword charset="tc">主意</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">zhu3yi5</pron><defn>noun 1 idea; plan 好主意！ Hǎo zhǔyi! That’s a good idea. 人多主意多。 Rén duō zhǔyi duō. The more the people the more the ideas. 领导者的责任主要是出主意, 用干部两件事。 lǐngdǎozhě de zérèn zhǔyào shì chū zhǔyi, yòng gànbù liǎng jiàn shì. A leader has two main responsibilities: proposing ideas and using the right cadres. 2 decision; definite view 打定主意 Dǎdìng zhǔyi make a decision; make up one’s mind 改变主意 gǎibiàn zhǔyi change one’s view (or mind) 拿不定主意 nábudìng zhǔyi be in two minds (about sth.); uncertain 我一时没了主意。 Wǒ yīshí méi le zhǔyi. For a moment, I was at a loss.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="36575232"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">飞机</headword><headword charset="tc">飛機</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">fei1ji1</pron><defn>noun aircraft; aeroplane; plane 我坐飞机去上海。 Wǒ zuò fēijī qù Shànghǎi. I’ll go to Shanghai by plane.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="20865024"/><catassign category="Lektion12"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">给</headword><headword charset="tc">給</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">gei3</pron><defn>verb 1 give; grant; present 给某人颜色看 gěi mǒurén yánsè kàn give sb. a lesson; make it hot for sb. 给我一杯水喝。 Gěi wǒ yī bēi shuǐ hē. Give me a cup of water (to drink). 公司给他一个月的假。 Gōngsī gěi tā yī ge yuè de jià. The company granted him a month’s leave. 杭州给我的印象很好。 Hángzhōu gěi wǒ de yìnxiàng hěn hǎo. Hangzhou left a very good impression on me. 这本书是给你的。 Zhè běn shū shì gěi nǐ de. This book is for you. 我给他一个不理睬。 Wǒ gěi tā yī ge bù lǐcǎi. I just ignored him. 2 let; allow; make 给我看看。 Gěi wǒ kànkan. Let me have a look. 开完运动会, 给我累得够呛。 Kāi wán yùndònghuì, gěi wǒ lèi de gòuqiàng. After the sports meet, I was tired out. 
preposition 1 [after a verb, indicating the handing over of sth.] 交给他一封信 jiāo gěi tā yī fēngxìn hand him a letter 我把钥匙留给你。 Wǒ bǎ yàoshi liúgěi nǐ. I’ll leave the key with you. 2 for the benefit of; for the sake of; for 给旅客送水倒茶 gěi lǚkè sòng shuǐ dàochá bring drinking water and tea for the passengers 我给你当翻译。 Wǒ gěi nǐ dāng fānyì. I’ll act as interpreter for you. 3 [introducing the recipient of an action] 他给我道歉了。 Tā gěi wǒ dàoqiàn le. He’s apologized to me. 4 [in passive sentence to introduce what has happened] 衣服给汗水湿透了。 yīfugěi hànshuǐ shītòu le. Clothes were soaked with sweat. 
auxiliary [before a verb for emphasis] 我差点儿把这事给忘了。 Wǒ chàdiǎnr bǎ zhè shì gěi wàng le. I almost forgot that. 质量不合格给换。 Zhìliàng bù hégé gěi huàn. Substandard products will be exchanged.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="21618176"/><catassign category="Lektion5"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">刻</headword><headword charset="tc">刻</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ke4</pron><defn>verb 1 carve; engrave; inscribe; cut 刻蜡版 kè làbǎn cut stencils 刻图章 kè túzhāng engrave a seal 刻电路板 kè diànlù bǎn etch a circuit board 2 colloquial VARIANT OF 64696803刻录ke4lu4刻录 imprint (CD) abbreviation 3 literary set a time limit 
noun 1 quarter (of an hour) 五点一刻 Wǔ diǎn yī kè a quarter past five 2 moment 此刻 cǐkè this moment; now 顷刻 qǐngkè in a moment 
adjective 1 unkind; harsh 苛刻 kēkè harsh 2 in the highest degree 深刻 shēnkè profound 
measure word archaic ke (unit of time measured by the regulated flow of water through a clepsydra, hence with a day and night divided into 100 ke)</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="24983040"/><catassign category="Lektion7"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">它</headword><headword charset="tc">它</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ta1</pron><defn>pronoun it 这杯牛奶你喝了它。 Zhè bēi niúnǎi nǐ hē le tā. Drink up this glass of milk. 有个东西在黑影里蹲着, 我也看不清它到底是猫还是狗。 Yǒu ge dōngxi zài hēiyǐng lǐ dūn zhe, wǒ yě kàn bù qīng tā dàodǐ shì māo háishi gǒu. Some animal was crouching in the shadow but I couldn’t make out whether it was a cat or a dog. 这些画报我都看过了, 你把它拿去吧。 Zhèxiē huàbào wǒ dōu kàn guò le, nǐ bǎ tā ná qù ba. I’ve finished with these magazines, you can have them. 
noun (Tā) a surname</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="31038208"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">出租车</headword><headword charset="tc">出租車</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">chu1zu1che1</pron><defn>noun 1 taxicab; taxi; cab 2 rental car (Taiwan) 乘出租(汽)车 Chéng chūzūchē take a taxi 叫辆出租(汽)车 jiào liàng chūzūchē call a taxi 他招手叫一辆出租(汽)车。 tā zhāoshǒu jiào yī liàng chūzūchē. He hailed a taxi.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="42424242"/><catassign category="Lektion10"/></card></cards></plecoflash>